<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The family cookery: combining elegance and economy with various receipts for
               making gravies, soups, sauces, and made dishes, directions for roasting and boiling
               game, poultry, meat, fish, and making of pastry and confectionary, directions for
               trussing and carving, rules for brewing and making wines, the art of pickling and
               preserving, the management of poultry and bees, and bills of fare for the year and
               many other useful receipts, forming a complete system of domestic management</title>
            <author>R. House</author>
            <editor>Alena Sek</editor>
            <editor>Kayrina Ben</editor>
            <editor>Birdie Bell</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This edition is a digitised copy, including a small handful of recipes, diagrams of
               how to layout dishes for a dinner party, how to manage bees, and a list of bills of
               fare for one year. It is not a digitisation of the full text. It is published online
               through resources provided by the University of Washington, Seattle. It was made for
               TXTDS 404, Texts, Publics, and Publication, as the final course project. This
               specific text was chosen because it sounded interesting to have a mix of recipe
               types; that is, this cookbook includes recipres for both eating and medicinal
               purposes.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This text can be accessed through the University of Washington, Seattle Special
               Collections, at the Allen library. It is a small book, approximately 6 inches high by
               4 inches across. The cover is brown canvas.</p>
            <ab type="publication_information">
               <bibl>
                  <title>The family cookery: combining elegance and economy with various receipts
                     for making gravies, soups, sauces, and made dishes, directions for roasting and
                     boiling game, poultry, meat, fish, and making of pastry and confectionary,
                     directions for trussing and carving, rules for brewing and making wines, the
                     art of pickling and preserving, the management of poultry and bees, and bills
                     of fare for the year and many other useful receipts, forming a complete system
                     of domestic management</title>
                  <author>R. House</author>
                  <publisher>J. Bailey, Chancery Lane</publisher>
                  <date>between 1808 and 1822?</date>
                  <idno type="Call_Number">TX705 .H68 1800</idno>
                  <idno type="OCLC_Number">261232426</idno>
                  <idno type="Alma_IZ_Record_Number">99108862500001452</idno>
                  <idno type="Alma_NZ_Record_Number">99165387910001451</idno>
               </bibl>
            </ab>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p> As we are trying to avoid completely modernizing the text, we intentionally want
                  to keep the same grammar and spelling to hold its older essence during the
                  1800s.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p> For punctuation, we are taking out hanging indents for convenience. </p>
            </punctuation>
            <interpretation>
               <p> For interpretation of the text, annotations will be important for readers to
                  properly interpret the meaning of unfamiliar words or language. This includes
                  identifying specific towns based off recipe names or historical events that
                  contribute to some recipes. Doing this can help readers understand the historical
                  context of the recipes.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p><hi rend="italic">The Family Cookery: Combining Elegance and Economy</hi> authored by
               R. House – a former head cook for the Duke of Portland – is a pocket-sized
               19th-century English cookbook published in London by John Bailey. It is believed to
               have been printed sometime between 1808-1822, with Worldcat entries suggesting a
               publication date of 1810. The cookbook touches on a variety of recipes for different
               purposes, including different types of dishes, how to cook various meats, pastry and
               confectionery, brewing and winemaking, and pickling and preserving. What makes this
               cookbook particularly interesting and unique is that it also offers advice for the
               care of poultry and bees as well as diagrams for meal placement and menus or "bills
               of fare" as reference material for readers. </p>
            <p>The focus of the original edition is a cookbook that guides readers on how to make
               specific recipes from the 19th century. The book primarily formats the recipes in a
               list with headings – the title of the recipe – and recipes – short paragraphs. Our
               edition will keep the original format, including spelling and grammar, to keep the
               essence of the cookbook being from the 19th century. We are hoping to accomplish an
               accurate, digitized publication of the cookbook that increases accessibility to meals
               that may be perceived as obscure in modern day cooking, showcasing the uniqueness of
               the type of foods during that era of time. </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
	<div>
	<pb n="10"/>
	<fw type="page_number" place="top left">10</fw>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="10 Diagram.JPEG"/>
		    <style>
			    html {
                            width: 200px;
                            margin: auto;                  
                    }
                </style>
               <figDesc>The figure shows a layout of where certain foods were to be placed ranging from
                  4 tables with Vegetables, 4 tables for Sauces, 1 big table for Ham, 2 tables for roast
                  Fowls on opposite ends of the ham table. There are bigger tables surrounding these tables
                  shaped in a oval form, which individuallly have a different type of food including soups to pies. </figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="soups">
            <pb n="18"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top left">18</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">White Poitage, with a Chicken in the
                  Middle.</head>
               <p>Take an old fowl, a knuckle of veal, scrag of mutton, some spice, some sweet herbs
                  and onions; boil all together till strong enough, have ready some barley boiled
                  very white, and strain some of it through a cullender; have some bread ready
                  toasted in a dish, with a fowl in the middle; some green herbs, minced chervil,
                  spinach, and sorrel; pour some of the broth to your bread, herbs and chicken; add
                  barley well strained, stew all together a little while, and serve it up. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Cray Fish Soup.</head>
               <p>Take three quarts of strong veal broth, made without herbs, the crumb of four
                  French rolls, the meat of a lob-ster, and fifty cray-fish pounded, with some live
                  lobster spawn; skim and rub it through a tamis cloth, season it with salt, and
                  Cayenne pepper. Cut the crust of French bread into small round pieces when served
                  up. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Oyster Soup.</head>
               <p>Take a pound of skate, four or five flounders, and two pounds of eels, clean them,
                  cut them in pieces, and cover them with water, season them with mace, pepper,
                  salt, an onion stuck with cloves, a head of celery, some parsley, and sweet herbs.
                  Simmer it an hour and a half, and strain it off. Beat the yolks of ten hard eggs,
                  with the hard part of a pint of oysters, in a mortar, and add them to the stew.
                  Simmer it all for half an hour; then strain it off, and put it and the oysters
                  (well washed and bearded) into the pan. Simmer it for five minutes. Have ready the
                  yolks of six raw eggs well beaten, and add them to the soup. Stir it on the fire
                  till it is thick and smooth, but do not let it boil. Serve all together. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Eel Soup.</head>
               <p>Take eels according to the quantity of soup you wish to make; to every pound of
                  eels put a quart of water,then add a crust of bread, two or three blades of mace,
                  some whole pepper, an onion, and a bundle of sweet herbs; cover them close, and
                  let them boil till half the liquor is <pb n="19"/><fw type="page_number"
                     place="top right">19</fw>
                  <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
                  Cookery.</fw><lb/>wasted; then strain it, and toast soem bread, cut it small, lay
                  it in the dish, and pour in your soup; set the dish over a stove for a minute, and
                  send it to tabel hot. Should your soup not be rich enough, you must let it boil
                  till the liquor is more reduced. Add a piece of carrot to brown it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Muscle Soup.</head>
               <p>Clean your muscles well, let them boil till they open, then take them off, and put
                  them into another stewpan, with a bit of butter rolled in four, some parsley, and
                  sweet herbs, with some good gravy, and let them simmer till reduced to one half,
                  add a liaison, and serve it up hot. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Milk Soup.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of milk, boil it with cinnamon, two bay leaves, and moist sugar; put
                  some sippets in a dish, pour the milk over them, and set the whole over a charcoal
                  fire to simmer till the bread is soft; take the yolks of two eggs, beat them up,
                  and mix them with a little of the milk, and throw it in; mix it altogether, and
                  serve it up. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Green Pea Soup.</head>
               <p>Pare and slice five or six cucumbers, add to these as many coss lettuces, a sprig
                  or two of mint, two or three onions, some pepper and salt, a pint and a half of
                  young peas, and a little parsley. Put together with a pound of fresh butter into a
                  saucepan, stew them gently in their own liquor, half an how; then pour two quarts
                  of boiling water on them, and stew them two hours; thicken with a bit of butter
                  rolled in flour, and serve it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">White Pea Soup.</head>
               <p>Take a pint of white peas, either split or whole, but whole in preference, and
                  after having steeped them in cold water one hour, put them into a pot with about a
                  quart of water, and let them boil till they become sufficiently tender to be
                  pulped through a sieve. Then put them into a stewpan, with some good gravy,
                  together with white pepper, and salt. Boil for half an hour, and serve up with
                  fried bread, and a little dried mint.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poultry">
            <pb n="36"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top left">36</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Pigeons.</head>
               <p>TAKE a little pepper and salt, a small piece of butter, and some parsley cut
                  small, mix these together, put them into the bellies of your pigeons, tying the
                  neck ends tight ;rumps, and the take another string, fasten one end of it to their
                  legs and rumps, the other to the mantlepiece. Keep them constantly turning round
                  and baste them with butter. When they are done, take them up, lay them in a
                  dish,and they will swim with gravy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Woodcocks or Snipes</head>
               <p>Spit them on a small bird spit; four them, and baste them with butter; have ready
                  a slice of bread toasted brown, which lay in a dish, and set it under your birds,
                  for the trail to drop on. When they are enough, take them up, and lay them on the
                  toast, put some good gravy in the dish, and some melted butter in a cup. Garnish
                  with orange or lemon. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Quails.</head>
               <p>Truss them, and stuff their bellies with beef suet, and sweet herbs shred very
                  fine, and seasoned with a little spice; when they grow warm, baste them with salt
                  and water, then dredge them and baste them with butter.For sauce, dissolve an
                  anchovy in good gravy, with two or three shallots shred very fine, and the juice
                  of a Seville orange; dish them up in this sauce, and garnish your dish with fried
                  bread crumbs, and lemon; send them to table as hot as possible. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Pheasants.</head>
               <p>TAKE a brace of pheasants, lard them with small lards of bacon: butter a piece of
                  white paper, and put over the breasts, and, about ten minutes before they are
                  done, take off the paper; flour and baste them with nice butter, that they may go
                  to table with a fine froth; put good gravy in the dish, and bread sauce, as for
                  partridges, in a boat; garnish your dish with lemon. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Partidges.</head>
               <p>When they are a little under roasted, dredge them with four, and baste them with
                  fresh butter; let them go to <pb n="37"/><fw type="page_number" place="top right"
                     >37</fw>
                  <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
                  Cookery.</fw><lb/>table with a fine froth, putting gravy sauce in the dish, and
                  bread sauce in a hason. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Plovers.</head>
               <p>Green plovers are roasted as you do woodcocks; lay them upon a toast, and put good
                  gravy sauce in the dish. Grey Plovers are roasted, or stewed thus: make a
                  forcemeat of artichoke bottoms cut small. Seasoned with pepper, salt, and nutmeg;
                  stuff the bellies, and put the birds into a saucepan, with a good gravy just to
                  cover them, a glass of white wine, and a blade of mace; cover them close, and stew
                  them softly till they are tender; then take up your plovers into the dish, put in
                  a piece of butter rolled in flour to thicken your sauce, let it boil till smooth:
                  squeeze in a little lemon; scum it clean, and pour it over the birds. Garnish with
                  orange. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Larks.</head>
               <p>Truss your larks with the legs across, and put a sage leaf over the breast; put
                  them upon a long fine skewer, and between every lark a little piece of thin bacon;
                  then tie the skewer to a spit, and roast them at a quick, clear, fire; baste them
                  with butter, and strew over them some crumbs of bread, mixed with flour; fry some
                  bread, crumbs of a nice brown, in a bit of butter; lay your larks round in your
                  dish; the bread crumbs in the middle, with sliced orange for garnish. Send good
                  gravy in a boat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Ortolans.</head>
               <p>You may lard them with bacon, or roast them without putting a vine lead between
                  each ; spit them sideways, baste them with butter, and strew bread crumbs on them
                  whilst roasting. Send them to a table with fried bread crumbs around them,
                  garnished with lemon, and good gravy sauce in a boat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Ruffs and Reefs.</head>
               <p>Draw them, and truss them cross-legged, as you do snipes, and spit them the same
                  way; lay the, upon a buttered toast, pour good gravy into the dish, and serve them
                  up hot. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="pastry">
            <pb n="117"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top right">117</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">A Spanish Cake.</head>
               <p>Take twelve eggs, three quarters of a pound of the best moist sugar, mill them in
                  a chocolate mill till they are all of a lather; then mix into one pound of flour,
                  half a pound of pounded almonds, two ounces of candied orange peel, two ounces of
                  citron, four large spoonfuls of orange or rose water, half an ounce of cinnamon,
                  and a glass of sack. It is best when baked in a slow oven. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Portugal Cake.</head>
               <p>Put a pound of fine sugar, a pound of fresh butter, five eggs, and a little mace
                  beaten, into a board pan; beat it with your hands till it is very light, and looks
                  curdling;... </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="118"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top left">118</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Dutch Cakes.</head>
               <p>TAKE five pounds of flour; two ounces of carraway seeds, half a pound of sugar,
                  and something more than a pint of milk; put into it three quarters of a pound of
                  but-ter; make a hole in the middle of the flour, and put in a full pint of good
                  ale yeast pour in the butter and milk, and make these into a paste, letting it
                  stand a quarter of an hour before the fire to rise; then mould it, and roll it
                  into cakes pretty thin, prick them all over pretty much, or they will blister, and
                  bake them a quarter of an hour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Shrewsbury Cakes.</head>
               <p>TAKE one pound of sugar, three pounds of the finest flour, a nutmeg grated, and
                  some cinnamon well beaten; the sugar and spice must be sifted into the flour, wet
                  it with three eggs, and as much melted butter as will make it of a good thickness
                  to roll into paste; mould it well and roll it; cut it into what shape you please;
                  perfume the cakes, and prick them before they go into the oven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Marlborough Cakes.</head>
               <p>TAKE eight eggs, yolks and whites, beat and strain them, and put to them a pound
                  of sugar beaten and and sifted; beat these three quarters of an hour together,
                  then put in three quarters of a pound of flour well dried, and two ounces of
                  carraway seeds; beat all well together, and bake them in broad tin pans, in a
                  brisk oven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Queen Cakes.</head>
               <p>TAKE A pound of sugar beat fine, pour in the yolks and whites of two eggs, half a
                  pound of butter, a little rose water, six spoonsful of warm cream, a pound of
                  currants, and as much flour as will make it up; stir them well together, and put
                  them into your patty pans, being well buttered; bake them in an oven, almost as
                  hot as for bread, for half an hour, then take them out and glaze <pb n="119"/><fw
                     type="page_number" place="top right">119</fw>
                  <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
                  Cookery.</fw><lb/>them, and let them stand but a little after the glazing is on,
                  to rise.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Uxbridge Cakes.</head>
               <p>TAKE a pound of wheat flour, seven pounds of currants, half a nutmeg, and four
                  pounds of butter; rub your but- ter cold well among the meal. Dress the currants
                  very well in the flour, butter, and seasoning, and knead it with so much good new
                  yeast as will make it into a pretty high paste. After it is kneaded well together,
                  let it stand an hour to rise. You may put half a pound of paste in each cake.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="recipes_for_the_sick">
            <pb n="150"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top left">150</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Calf's Feet Broth.</head>
               <p>BOIL two calf's feet with two ounces of veal, two of beef, piece of undercrust,
                  two or three blades of mace, half a nutmeg sliced, and salt, in three quarts of
                  water, reduced to half; strain, and take off the fat, Sheep's trotters are
                  excellent done the same way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Eel Broth</head>
               <p>AFTER cleaning half a pound of small eels, set them on the fire, with a quart of
                  water, a small onion, and a few pepper corns; simmer till the eels are broken, and
                  the broth good; add salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Tapioca Jelly.</head>
               <p>WASH the tapioca in three or four waters. Soak it in fresh water five hours, and
                  simmer in the same till quite clear. Add lemon juice, wine and sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Chicken Panada.</head>
               <p>Boil a chicken till three parts done, in a quart of water, take off the skin, cut
                  the white meat off when cold, and put it into a mortar; pound it to a paste with a
                  little of the water it was boiled in, season with salt, grate in nut- meg, and a
                  small bit of lemon peel. Boil gently for a few minutes; it should be such as you
                  can drink, though tolerably thick. This is exceedingly nutritious, given in small
                  quantities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Panada.</head>
               <p>Put a little water in a saucepan with a glass of wine sugar, nutmeg, and lemon
                  peel, crumbs of bread. The moment it boils, put the bread in, and let it boil
                  fast. When of a proper thickness to drink, take it off. It is very good with a
                  little rum, and a bit of butter instead of the wine. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Eggs.</head>
               <p>An egg broken into a cup of tea, or beaten up and <pb n="151"/><fw
                     type="page_number" place="top right">151</fw>
                  <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
                  Cookery.</fw><lb/>mixed with a basin of milk, makes a very nutritious breakfast. </p>
               <p>An egg divided, and the yolk and the white beaten separately, then mixed with a
                  glass of wine, will afford two very wholesome draughts, and be much better than
                  when taken together.-Beat up a new laid egg, and mix it with a quarter of a pint
                  of new milk warmed, a spoonful of capillaire, one of rose water, and a little
                  nutmeg. It should not be warmed after the egg is put in. Take it the first, and
                  last thing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Arrow Root.</head>
               <p>THIS mixed with milk, and sweetened, is very nutri- ons; but it should be the best
                  sort, to be certain of which it should be had from Apothecaries' Hall, as many
                  things are substituted by retail dealers, which have been known to have had a bad
                  effect. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Isinglass.</head>
               <p>BOIL an ounce of isinglass shavings with forty Jamaica peppercorns, and a crust of
                  bread in a quart of water, simmer to a pint, and strain it off. </p>
               <p>This makes a very pleasant jelly; it will keep well, and may be taken in wine and
                  water, milk, tea, soup, or whatever may be preferred. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">White Pot.</head>
               <p>BEAT up eight eggs, leaving out half the whites, with a little rose water, nutmeg,
                  and a quarter of a pound of sugar. Cut a roll or small loaf into thin slices, and
                  pour the milk and eggs over them. Put a piece of butter on the top, bake it for
                  half an hour, and it will be fit for use. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Bread Soup.</head>
               <p>PUT a quart of water on the fire, with as much dry crust of bread cut to pieces as
                  the top of a roll, (the drier the better) and a bit of butter. Boil, beat it with
                  a spoon, and keep boiling till the bread and water are mixed; sea. son it with
                  salt: it is very good for a weak stomach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Water Gruel.</head>
               <p>PUT a pint of water on the fire. Mix in a basin a large <pb n="152"/><fw
                     type="page_number" place="top left">152</fw>
                  <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
                  Cookery.</fw><lb/>spoonful of oatmeal with a little water; when the water boils,
                  stir in the oatmeal, let it boil up three or four times, but be careful it does
                  not boil over. Strain it through a sieve, salt, and put in a piece of butter. Stir
                  it about with a spoon till the butter is all melted, and it will be fine and
                  smooth. Sugar, or a spoonful of wine, &amp;c. may occasionally be added. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Barley Water. </head>
               <p>PUT a quarter of a pound of pearl barley to two quarts of water. When it boils,
                  strain it very clean, boil half away, and then strain it off. Add two spoonfuls of
                  white wine, and sweeten to taste.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Caudle.</head>
               <p>MAKE A smooth gruel of half grits; when well boiled, strain, and stir it now and
                  then till cold. When to be used, add sugar, wine, lemon peel, and nutmeg. Some
                  like a spoonful of brandy besides the wine; others like le- mon juice, but this
                  must depend on taste. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Rich Caudle.</head>
               <p>WHEN the water boils, pour into it some grated rice, mixed with a little cold
                  water; when of a proper consistence, add sugar, lemon peel, and cinnamon, and a
                  glass of brandy to a quart. Boil all smooth together. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Brown Caudle.</head>
               <p>MAKE A gruel with six spoonsful of oatmeal, and strain it. Then add a quart of
                  malt liquor, not bitter; boil, sweeten, and add half a pint of white wine; either
                  with spices or not, as may be preferred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Sago.</head>
               <p>SOAK it in cold water one hour, pour it off, and wash it; add more water, and
                  simmer gently till the sago is clear, with lemon peel and spice, if approved. Add
                  wine and su- gar, and boil all up together. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Ground Rice Milk.</head>
               <p>RUB smooth a spoonful of ground rice, with three pints of milk, add cinnamon,
                  lemon peel, and nutmeg. Sweeten to your taste. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="153"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top right">153</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Mustard Whey.</head>
               <p>TURN half a pint of boiling milk with a table spoonful of made mustard. Strain the
                  whey from the curd, and drink it in bed. This will give a glowing warmth; the whey
                  thus conveying mustard into the constitution.</p>
               <p>This has been known to be very efficacious in nervous affections, as well as the
                  palsy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">A very refreshing drink.</head>
               <p>Pour a table spoonful of capillaire, and one of vinegar into a tumbler of cold
                  spring water. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Butter Milk. </head>
               <p>MILK a cow into a small churn; when it has stood about ten minutes begin churning,
                  and continue till the flakes of butter swim about pretty thick, and the milk,
                  discharged of all the greasy particles, appears thin and blue. Strain it through a
                  sieve, and drink of it very fre-quently. </p>
               <p>It should form the whole of the patient's drink; the food should be biscuits and
                  rusks, in every way and sort; ripe and dried fruits of various kinds, where a
                  decline is apprehended. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">Ale Posset. </head>
               <p>Put a small piece of bread into a pint of milk, and set it over the fire. Put
                  nutmeg and sugar into a pint of ale, warm, and when your milk boils, pour it upon
                  the ale. Let it stand a few minutes to clear, and it will be fit for use. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="align(center) format(italic)">White Wine Whey. </head>
               <p>BOIL half a pint of new milk; as soon as it boils up pour in as much white wine as
                  will turn, and make it look clear; boil it up, set the saucepan aside till the
                  curd sub- sides, and do not stir it. Pour the whey off, and add to it half a pint
                  of boiling water, and a bit of white sugar. The whey will thus be cleared of milky
                  particles, and may be made as weak as you chuse. Cheese whey is a very whole- some
                  drink, particularly if the cows have fresh herbage. </p>
               <p>Whey may be made of vinegar or lemon; and, when clear, diluted with boiling water,
                  and a little sugar. This is less heating than wine, and if required to excite
                  perspiration, answers quite as well.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="bee_management">
            <pb n="184"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top center">184</fw>
            <lb/>
            <head rend="align(center) case(caps)">The Management of Bees.</head>
            <p>Bees, whether we consider them as beneficial to the poor, from the very trivial
               expence at which they are kept, and the sure returns they make, or as creatures which
               produce us a luxurious treat, are equally worthy of our consideration.</p>
            <p>The hives should be placed in such a manner as to face the south, and sufficiently
               near the house, to watch them, but so situated as not to be exposed to unpleasant
               smells, or too much noise. If near a running stream, so much the better, but if not,
               place some shallow troughs of water near them, with some small stones in it for them
               to pitch on–for water is absolutely necessary to their well being. Herbs, especially
               thyme, should be plentifully sown in the garden where they are kept: furze, broom,
               clover, and heath, are also excellent for bees.</p>
            <p>Straw hives are the best, because they keep out the cold better than any others, and
               are not liable to be over heated by the rays of the sun. Their cheapness also renders
               their purchase easy.</p>
            <p>Persons designing to keep bees, should make their purchase at the latter part of the
               year, at which time they are cheapest. The hives should be full of combs, and well
               stored with bees. The purchaser should inspect the combs, and select the whitest,
               which are always the product of that season; and when the combs are very dark, that
               hive should be rejected, because the bees are old.</p>
            <p>Bees should never be bought during the Summer, or, if purchased, should on no account
               be removed from their native place till the Autumn.</p>
            <p>Bees generally swarm in April and May, but earlier or later according to the warmth
               of the season. They rarely swarm before ten o'clock in the morning, or later than
               three in the afternoon. If the swarm fly too high, throw some sand amongst them,
               which will cause them to de-<pb n="185"/><fw type="page_number" place="top right"
                  >185</fw>
               <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
               Cookery.</fw><lb/>scend, and when they settle, they should be immediately hived, lest
               they should again take wing.</p>
            <p>The hive should not be immediately placed on the stool where it is to remain, but
               should be suffered to stand near the place where the bees were swept into it, till
               the evening, and shaded with some boughs.</p>
            <p>Bees are torpid during a great part of the winter, but revive on sunny days, in
               consequence of which, a little food supports them. Every hive should therefore be
               weighed at the end of Autumn, and each ought then to weigh twenty pounds, but should
               any weigh less, that hive must be occasionally fed with honey, or sugar and water put
               in small troughs made with elder.</p>
            <p>Bees are generally taken in September, for which purpose a hole is dug in the earth,
               and a rag dipt in melted brimstone, fastened to the end of a stick, is stuck in the
               hole so prepared. Then set it on fire, and instantly place the hive over it,
               observing to throw the earth up all round, to prevent the smoke from escaping.</p>
            <p>In fifteen or twenty minutes, the bees will be destroyed.</p>
            <p>The valuable creatures thus destroyed may, however, be preserved, by using boxes
               instead of hives; by which method two boxes of honey may be taken during the summer
               from one colony, each weighing forty pounds, and yet a sufficient supply may be left
               for the winter support of the bees in this manner preserved from destruction.</p>
            <p>Consequently, it appears that this plan combines humanity with great profit, to which
               motives we may add the pleasure of seeing them at work, and also the trouble which is
               saved during the swarming time.</p>
            <p>The bees thus secured, are also much more effectually screened from wet and cold,
               from mice, and other vermin.</p>
            <p>The boxes should be made of deal, which, from its spongy nature, sucks up the breath
               of the bees sooner than a more solid wood would do. Yellow dram deal, well seasoned,
               is the best; and an octagon form is preferable to a square. The boxes should be ten
               inches in depth, and fourteen in breadth, with a small glass window behind, a thin
               deal cover on brass hinges, and a button to shut it with.</p>
            <p>It will be of material service, when you intend to keep bees, to plant a great number
               of gooseberry and currant <pb n="186"/><fw type="page_number" place="top left"
                  >186</fw>
               <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
               Cookery.</fw><lb/>trees, on the blossoms of which they will find a large quantity of
               food.</p>
            <p>If bees are suffered to continue in one hive more than four years, they will
               degenerate both in number and strength.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="IMG_4512.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>The figure depicts a historical diagram of a formal dinner table layout.
                  Divided into a first and second course with labeled dishes arranged symmetrically
                  around a central dish, the first course centers around Green Pea Soup and the
                  second on Apricot Puffs, with a variety of meats, vegetables, and desserts
                  structured around them. </figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="bills_of_fare">
            <pb n="197"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top right">197</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <head rend="caps">Bills of Fare</head>
            <head rend="caps">For Every Month In The Year.</head>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In January.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Beef soup, made of brisket of beef; and the beef served up in the dish. Turkey and
                  chine roasted, with gravy and onion sauce; mince pies.</p>
               <p>Or, achbone of beef boiled, and carrots and savoys <pb n="198"/><fw
                     type="page_number" place="top left">198</fw>
                  <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family
                  Cookery.</fw><lb/>with melted butter; ham and fowls roasted, with rich gravy;
                  tarts.</p>
               <p>Or, vermicelli soup; fore quarter of lamb, and salad in season; fresh salmon, with
                  smelts fried, and lobster sauces; mince pies.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Chicken fricaseed; wild ducks, with rich gravy sauce; piece of sturgeon or brawn,
                  or minced pies.</p>
               <p>Or, a hare with a pudding in its belly, and a strong gravy and claret sauce; hen
                  turkey boiled with oyster sauce and onion sauce; brawn or mince pies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In February.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Chine or saddle of mutton roasted, with pickles; calf's head boiled and grilled,
                  garnished with broiled slices of bacon, and with brains mashed with parsley and
                  butter, salt, pepper, and a little vinegar, the tongue slit and laid upon the
                  brains; a boiled pudding.</p>
               <p>Or, ham, and fowls roasted, with gravy sauce, leg of lamb boiled with spinach.</p>
               <p>Or, a piece of fresh salmon, with gravy sauce, and garnish with fried smelts and
                  flounders; chickens roasted with asparagus, with gravy and plain butter.</p>
               <p>Or, Scotch collops, ducklings with rich gravy; mince pies.</p>
               <p>Or, fried soals with shrimp sauce; fore quarter of lamb roasted, with mint sauce;
                  dish of tarts and custards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In March.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Roast beef, and horseradish to garnish the dish; salt fish, with egg sauce, and
                  potatoes or parsnips, with melted butter; pease soup.</p>
               <p>Or, ham, and fowls roasted; marrow pudding.</p>
               <p>Or, leg of mutton boiled, with turnips and caper sauce; cod boiled, with oyster
                  sauce, and garnished with horseradish; a bread pudding.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="199"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top right">199</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Scolloped or fried oysters; leg of lamb, with spinach: tars and fruit.</p>
               <p>Fricasee of cocks' combs, lambs' stones, and sweet breads; pigeon pie and marrow
                  pudding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In April.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Ham and chickens roasted, with gravy sauce; a piece of boiled beef, and carrots
                  and greens.</p>
               <p>Or, a roasted shoulder of veal stuffed, and melted butter: a leg of pork boiled,
                  and pease pudding.</p>
               <p>Or, a dish of fish, (as in season); roast beef garnished with horseradish, and
                  plumb pudding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Fricasee of lambs' stones and sweetbreads, or sucking rabbits; roasted pigeons and
                  asparagus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In May.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Beef soup, with herbs well boiled; fillet of veal well stuffed and roasted; a ham
                  boiled.</p>
               <p>Or, rump of beef salted and boiled, with a summer cabbage; fresh salmon boiled,
                  and friend smelts to garnish the dish, with lobster or shrimp sauce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In June.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Leg of grass lamb boiled with capers, carrots, and turnips; shoulder or neck of
                  venison roasted, with rich gravy and claret sauce; marrow pudding.</p>
               <p>Or, a haunch of venison roasted, with rich gravy and claret sauce; tarts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Fricasee of young rabbits, roast fowls and gravy sauce; gooseberry tart.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="200"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top left">200</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In July.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Green goose, with gravy sauce; neck of veal boiled, with bacon and greens.</p>
               <p>Or, roasted pig, with proper sauce of gravy and brains pretty well seasoned;
                  mackerel boiled, with melted butter and herbs; green peas.</p>
               <p>Or, mackerel boiled, with melted butter and herbs; fore-quarter of lamb, with
                  salad of coss lettuce, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Chickens roasted, with gravy or egg sauce; lobsters or prawns: green goose.</p>
               <p>Or, stewed carp, ducklings, with gravy sauce, and peas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In August.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Ham, and fowls roasted, with gravy sauce; beans.</p>
               <p>Or, neck of venison, with gravy and claret sauce; fresh salmon, with lobster
                  sauce; apple pie hot and buttered.</p>
               <p>Or, beeg a-la-mode; green peas: haddock boiled, and fried soals or flounders to
                  garnish the dish.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>White fricasee of chickens; green peas; ducks roasted, with gravy sauce.</p>
               <p>Or, chickens or pigeons roasted, with asparagus; artichokes, with melted
                  butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In September.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner</head>
               <p>Green pea soup; breast of veal roasted; boiled plain pudding.</p>
               <p>Or, leg of lamb boiled, with turnips, spinach, and caper sauce; goose roasted,
                  with gravy, mustard, and apple sauce, and pigeon pie.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="201"/>
            <fw type="page_number" place="top right">201</fw>
            <fw type="running_header" place="top center" rend="caps">The Family Cookery.</fw>
            <lb/>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Boiled pullets, with oyster sauce, greens, and bacon; dish of fried soals.</p>
               <p>Or, a leveret, with gravy sauce; wild ducks, with gravy sauce, and onion sauce:
                  apple pie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In October.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Cod's head, with shrimp and oyster sauce; knuckle of veal and bacon, and
                  greens.</p>
               <p>Or, leg of mutton boiled, with turnips and caper sauce; Scotch collops; fresh
                  salmon boiled, with shrimp and anchovy sauce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Wild ducks, with gravy sauce; scolloped oysters; mince pies.</p>
               <p>Or, fried smelts, with anchovy sauce; boiled fowl, with oyster sauce; mince pies
                  or tarts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In November.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>A roasted goose, with gravy and apple sauce, and mustard; cod's head, with oyster
                  sauce; mince pies.</p>
               <p>Or, roast tongue and udder, roast fowls, and pigeon pie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Stewed carp; calf's head hashed; mince pies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">In December.</head>
               <head rend="caps">Dinner.</head>
               <p>Ham and fowls roasted, with greens and gravy sauce; gravy soup; fresh salmon,
                  garnished with whiting or trout, fried, and anchovy sauce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bill">
               <head rend="caps">Supper.</head>
               <p>Brawn; pullets boiled, and oyster sauce; mince pies.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <!-- n1/pigeons is on page 36 -->
            <note xml:id="n1" type="editorial" target="#enviroliteracy-pigeons">Pigeons have been a
               common food source in Western cultures for centuries, only changing with the rise of
               urbanisation during the 19th and 20th centuries. The large populations in cities
               became associated with poor sanitation and disease. At the same time, the rise in
               agriculture, particularly chicken farming, made other meats cheaper and more readily
               available. Pigeons required more specialised care and smaller-scale operations, and
               thus became more expensive in comparison.</note>
            <!-- n2/shrewsbury and n3/marlborough are on page 118 -->
            <note xml:id="n2" type="editorial" target="#duff-cakes-regional-traditional">Shrewsbury
               is a small town in the county of Shropshire, England, near the border between England
               and Wales. Thomas Plimmer, who opened a bakery in Shrewsbury in 1760, claims his
               recipe for Shrewsbury Cakes as the original; a recipe which was acquired from James
               Palin, who also owned a bakery in Shrewsbury. That said, the first known references
               to Shrewsbury Cakes date back to 1602 in several manuscripts and books.</note>
            <!-- n3 and n4 still need research! I just haven't found any sources yet. I'm requesting a couple books from the library -Birdie (I'll also add @target to these) -->
            <note xml:id="n3" type="editorial">Marlborough Cakes</note>
            <!-- n4/uxbridge will be on page 119 -->
            <note xml:id="n4" type="editorial">Uxbridge Cakes</note>
            <!-- n5 is on page 150 and should be attached to the heading/Recipes for the Sick -->
            <note xml:id="n5" type="editorial" target="#smith-medicinal-food">It was common for
               cookbooks to include a section for the sick in and around the 19th century. There was
               a cultural belief that eating the right foods was enough to cure someone of their
               ailments, rather than medicinal practices. It ultimately stems back to humoralism, as
               invented by Hippocrates and Galen. The idea was that the body has four humours;
               choler, sanguine, phlegm, and melancholy. Foods also have these humours. Health is
               achieved by balancing these four humours, which could be done by eating the right
               proportions of certain foods.</note>
            <!-- n6/isinglass is on page 151 -->
            <note xml:id="n6" type="editorial" target="#mw-isinglass">Isinglass is a
               semitransparent, whitish gelatin prepared from the swim bladders of fishes,
               particularly sturgeons. It is typically used as a clarifying agent in jellies and
               glue.</note>
            <!-- n7/caudle is on page 152 -->
            <note xml:id="n7" type="editorial" target="#mw-caudle">Caudle is a drink, usually made
               from warm ale or wine mixed with bread or gruel, eggs, sugar, and spices.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="house-family-cookery" type="book"> ---> intro <author>
                     <surname>House</surname>
                     <forename>R.</forename>
                  </author>
                  <title level="m">The Family Cookery, Combining Elegance and Economy, with Various
                     Receipts</title>
                  <publisher>Rooke Books</publisher>
                  <date>n.d.</date>
                  <ptr
                     target="https://www.rookebooks.com/the-family-cookery-combining-elegance-and-economy-with-various-receipts"
                  />
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="enviroliteracy-pigeons" type="webpage"> ---> n1 <author>
                     <surname>Enviroliteracy Team</surname>
                     <forename/>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Why Did We Stop Eating Pigeons?</title>
                  <publisher>Environmental Literacy Council</publisher>
                  <date>11 Apr. 2025</date>
                  <ptr target="https://enviroliteracy.org/why-did-we-stop-eating-pigeons/"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="duff-cakes-regional-traditional" type="book"> ---> n2 <author>
                     <surname>Duff</surname>
                     <forename>Julie</forename>
                  </author>
                  <title level="m">Cakes: Regional &amp; Traditional</title>
                  <publisher>Grub Street Cookery</publisher>
                  <date>9 Oct. 2015</date>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">50–52</biblScope>
                  <ptr
                     target="https://books.google.com/books?id=ylJ2DQAAQBAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s"
                  />
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="smith-medicinal-food" type="entry"> ---> n5 <title level="a">Medicinal
                     Food</title>
                  <editor>
                     <surname>Smith</surname>
                     <forename>Merril D.</forename>
                  </editor>
                  <title level="m">The World of the American Revolution: A Daily Life
                     Encyclopedia</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                  <publisher>Greenwood</publisher>
                  <date>2015</date>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">358–360</biblScope>
                  <ptr
                     target="https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/CX6345700141/GVRL?u=wash_main&amp;sid=bookmark-GVRL&amp;xid=4ab7b26e"
                  />
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mw-isinglass" type="webpage"> ---> n6 <author>
                     <surname>Merriam-Webster</surname>
                     <forename/>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Isinglass</title>
                  <title level="j">Merriam-Webster Dictionary</title>
                  <publisher>Merriam-Webster, Inc.</publisher>
                  <date>n.d.</date>
                  <ptr target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/isinglass"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="mw-caudle" type="webpage"> ---> n7 <author>
                     <surname>Merriam-Webster</surname>
                     <forename/>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Caudle</title>
                  <title level="j">Merriam-Webster.com Dictionary</title>
                  <publisher>Merriam-Webster, Inc.</publisher>
                  <date>n.d.</date>
                  <ptr target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/caudle"/>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
