<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Assorted Front Matter of Volume 1 of Dickens' Bleak House, as Serialized</title>
            <editor>Paige Morris, Megan Piccirillo, and Kenneth Zacher </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published for the course requirements of "Texts, Publics and Publication: Digital
               Editing and Publishing" at the University of Washington. We present a selection of
               the front matter of this text, as it is a major element of context of the original
               reading that is absent in many modern editions. This edition considers how to create
               a digital publication of the advertisements themselves as the lead into the first few
               pages of the novel.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>First volume of the serialized first edition of Dickens' "Bleak House", published in
               nineteen parts. This edition is a small booklet with a blue cover, illustrations, and
               extensive advertisements for products, services, and other publications. Held by
               University of Washington Special Collections under call number PR4556 .A1 1852. <bibl>
                  <title>Bleak House Vol. 1</title>
                  <author>Charles Dickens</author>
                  <publisher>Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
                  <date>March, 1852</date>
                  <idno type="OCLC">38689984</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original text encoded without changes.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>Punctuation retained as is.</p>
            </punctuation>
            <quotation>
               <p>Quotations have been encoded via the 'quotation' element, eliminating the
                  punctuating marks as redundancy.</p>
            </quotation>
            <correction>
               <p>[Did we notice errors?]</p>
            </correction>
            <interpretation>
               <p>In service to depicting these ads as faithfully as possible, we have maintained
                  their layouts where possible. However, we have taken only a sampling of the ads in
                  this volume, and as such their order and other contextual elements of the page
                  layout may have been lost.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart>...</titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>Bleak House is a novel written by Charles Dickens, originally published in serial
               format over the course of 20 chapters–in 19 installments–between the years of 1852
               and 1853. While the compiled novel itself is among Dickens’ many acclaimed writings,
               the serialized installments offer material that is omitted from the published novel
               format, namely in terms of the front matter used to display various advertisements
               authentic to the date of publication.</p>
            <p>This edition, in addressing the above, is focused not on Bleak House as a novel, and
               instead dedicated to the preservation of the front matter and the formatting of the
               advertisements contained within for the sake of offering an accurate glimpse into the
               various goods and services being offered to the public in the early 1850s. In
               addition, the preservation of the formatting of each advertisement, though altered
               slightly to adhere to a more uniform font code, will preserve the changes in font
               size, bold, and italicization to further provide as authentic of a digitization as
               possible.</p>
            <p>One editorial decision we will be strictly adhering to is the presentation of the
               text itself as it was written. Being a relatively recent text, we see no reason to
               alter the verbiage from how it was originally published, as adapting the speech for a
               modern audience would detract from the contextualization we aim to present with this
               document. Additionally, we will include the illustrations both as textual
               descriptions and as image files archived online to fully present each advertisement
               as it was originally published.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>This could be an original preface...</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head><hi rend="bold">TO SPORTSMEN, TOURISTS, &amp; TRAVELLERS.</hi></head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>A dead fox and birds hung over a rifle and a net, tied in ropes and belts.
                  The fox wears an alarmed expression.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <div>
               <head><orgName key="Edmiston &amp; Son">EDMISTON'S</orgName> POCKET SIPHONIA,</head>
               <p><hi rend="sans">OR WATERPROOF OVERCOAT.</hi></p>
               <p>WEIGHT 10 oz.</p>
            </div>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>A man in a tailcoat and a top hat holds his umbrella, turned inside out by
                  the wind, amidst a rainstorm.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <div>
               <p><orgName key="Edmiston &amp; Son">Sole Manufacturers</orgName> of the celebrated
                  Pocket Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for
                  Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on
                  Saddle ; the most <hi rend="italic">important</hi> feature in this <hi
                     rend="italic">Waterproofing</hi> is being mineralised, which effectually
                  resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also obviating
                  the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.—Price
                  according to size, 40s. to 55s.; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s. Measurement,
                  length of coat, and size round the chest over the coast.</p>
            </div>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>A man standing upright in the rain in a buttoned topcoat and a top
                  hat.</figDesc>
               <caption><hi rend="sans">NO UMBRELLA REQUIRED</hi></caption>
            </figure>
            <div>
               <p>NOTICE.—NAME &amp; ADDRESS STAMPED INSIDE. NONE OTHERS ARE GENUINE.</p>
               <p><name key="Edmiston &amp; Son">EDMISTON &amp; SON</name>, <address>
                     <addrLine>416 &amp; 69, STRAND</addrLine>
                  </address>,</p>
               <p>Near the <placeName>Adelphi Theatre</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>OPINIONS OF THE PRESS.</head>
               <p><hi rend="dropcap">Waterproof</hi>—<q>"The lightest and most effectual is the <hi
                        rend="dropcap">Siphonia</hi>, made by <hi rend="dropcap">Edmiston &amp;
                        Son</hi>, of 69, Strand; they can be carried in the hat or pocket; and for
                     the summer we hear they are about to have light coloured
                        Siphonias."</q>—<title><hi rend="italic">Bell's Life</hi></title>, <date><hi
                        rend="italic">April 29th</hi>, 1851</date>.</p>
               <p><q>"<hi rend="dropcap">New Invention</hi>—A newly invented waterproof garment has
                     been manufactured by <hi rend="dropcap">Edmiston &amp; Son</hi>, 69 Strand, and
                     its lightness and softness of texture exceeds all other fabrics that have been
                     brought before the notice of the public; on that account well adapted for
                     riding or walking; can easily be carried in the pocket or hat, and the most
                     important feature respecting it is the process of mineralisation, which
                     effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun—a desideratum so much
                     required, to prevent the unpleasant smell, and sticking observable in all
                     hitherto waterproof garments"</q>—<title><hi rend="italic">British Army
                        Despatch</hi></title>, <date><hi rend="italic">May 9th</hi>,
                  1851</date>.</p>
               <p><q>"A new waterproof garment adapted to the very changeable weather of the season,
                     has been manufactured by <hi rend="dropcap">Edmiston &amp; Son</hi>. It is
                     remarkably light and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an
                     ingenious substitute for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome
                     umbrella."</q>—<title><hi rend="italic">Home News</hi></title>, <date><hi
                        rend="italic">May 24th</hi>, 1851</date>.</p>
            </div>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>A shaded leg, wearing one of a pair of goloshes.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <div rend="left column">
               <list>
                  <item>Leggings or Overalls.</item>
                  <item>Yacht Jackets.</item>
                  <item>Fishing and Shooting Hats or Caps.</item>
                  <item>Driving Gloves.</item>
                  <item>Cricketing do.</item>
                  <item>Gun covers.</item>
                  <item>Gig Aprons.</item>
                  <item>Sou-Westers.</item>
                  <item>Goloshes.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <cb/>
            <div rend="right column">
               <list>
                  <item>Ladies' Capes, with Hoods.</item>
                  <item>Do. Paletots.</item>
                  <item>Air Cushions.</item>
                  <item>Do. Pillows.</item>
                  <item>Do. Beds.</item>
                  <item>India Rubber Portable Folding Baths.</item>
                  <item>Nursing Aprons.</item>
                  <item>Crib Sheets.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>The newly invented Swimming Gloves.</p>
            </div>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>A hat.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>A bust in profile, bundled up in a collared coat and a hat that covers the
                  forehead andthe back of the neck.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <cb/>
            <div>
               <p>FISHING AND SHOOTING BOOTS, soft and pliable, require no dressing, and every
                  description of India Rubber and Gutta Percha Goods, Piping, Tubing for Watering
                  Gardens, &amp;c.</p>
               <p><hi rend="sans">AGENTS APPOINTED.</hi></p>
               <p><placeName>LONDON</placeName>: <orgName key="Edmiston &amp; Son">EDMISTON &amp;
                     SON</orgName>, <address>
                     <addrLine>416 &amp; 69, STRAND</addrLine>
                  </address>, near the <placeName>Adelphi</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head><orgName key="A.R. and Sons">ROWLANDS'</orgName> MACASSAR OIL.</head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>An illustration of a package of "Rowland's Macassar Oil".</figDesc>
               <p>A COPY IN OUTLINE OF THE GENUINE LABEL.</p>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>HIS ELEGANT, FRAGRANT, and PELLUCID OIL, in its <hi rend="italic">preservative,
                  restorative,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">beautifying</hi> qualities for the Human Hair, is unequalled over the whole world. It
               <hi rend="italic">preserves</hi> and <hi rend="italic">reproduces</hi> the <hi rend="italic">hair</hi>, even at a late period of life: prevents it from <hi rend="italic">turning grey</hi>. or if so changed, 
               <hi rend="italic">restores it to its original colour</hi>; frees it from <hi rend="italic">scurf</hi> and <hi rend="italic">impurity</hi>, and renders it
               <hi rend="italic">soft, silky, curly, glossy.</hi></p>
            <p>CAUTION.--<orgName key="A.R. and Sons">A.R. and Sons</orgName> have com
               -plaints repeatedly from parties who have 
               materially suffered from the use of spurious 
               imitations; and to frustrate to some extent 
               such impositions, they here add a small 
               copy in outline of their genuine label from 
               the burin of <orgName>MESSRS. PERKINS, BACON 
                  &amp; PETCH</orgName>, the eminent engravers of 
               London, on which will be seen the names 
               and address of the Proprietors in full (these 
               are in red ink on the label), any deviation 
               from which will always prove a spurious 
               article.</p>
            <p>The Prices are 3s. 6d.; 7s.; family bottles (equal to four small) 10s.6d.; and double that size 21s. Sould by 
               <orgName key="A.R. and Sons">the Proprietors</orgName>, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">Charles Dickens was well-acquainted with the serialized form, as not
               only a novelist himself but also an editor.<ref type="biblio" target="#source1">See
                  source 1</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">In this advertisement, on the inside of the front cover itself, the
               long s is used despite the character having already been out of use. As it was
               archaic at the time, and therefore likely chosen for stylistic reasons, we have
               retained it here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Dr. John Lindley, mentioned across multiple ads contained within
               Dickens’ Bleak House front matter, was a botanist from the University of England.
               During his time at the University of England, he was actually the first professor of
               botany to work at the University; spending his time working on articles and
               editorials on botany for other academics. Amidst this, as it appears through the
               Bleak House front matter he would also spend time writing articles on more common
               houseplants and widespread information that would cater to wider audiences; further
               fueling his renown and commonplace within Bleak House ads. <ref type="biblio"
                  target="#source3">See source 3</ref>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source1">
                  <author>
                     <name>
                        <surname>Casey</surname>
                        <forename>Ellen</forename>
                     </name>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">"That Specially Trying Mode of Publication": Dickens as Editor of
                     the Weekly Serial</title>
                  <title level="j">Victorian Periodicals Review</title>
                  <date>1981</date>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source2">
                  <author>
                     <name>
                        <surname>Walk</surname>
                        <forename>Kerry</forename>
                     </name>
                  </author>
                  <title level="u">The part before the whole: The aesthetics of serial publication
                     in Dickens, Thackeray, and Eliot</title>
                  <publisher>University of California, Berkeley ProQuest Dissertations &amp;
                     Theses</publisher>
                  <date>1993</date>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source3">
                  <author>
                     <name>
                        <surname>Boulger</surname>
                        <forename>George</forename>
                     </name>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Lindley, John</title>
                  <title level="m">Vol 33 Leighton - Lluelyn</title>
                  <title level="s">Dictionary of National Biography, 1885-1900</title>
                  <publisher>Smithy, Elder &amp; Co</publisher>
                  <date>1993</date>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source4">
                  <author>
                     <name>
                        <surname>Gaskell</surname>
                        <forename>Philip</forename>
                     </name>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a">Introduction</title>
                  <title level="m">From Writer to Reader: Studies in Editorial Method</title>
                  <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                  <date>1978</date>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
