<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart> ... </titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="intro">
            <p><name type="person" ref="dickens"><forname>Charles</forname><surname>Dickens</surname></name> 
	       is one of the most well-known English authors, who had a diverse writing career as a reporter, 
	       editor and essayist. He produced 14 novels, most of which were published in serial editions. 
	       This included a 20-month serialization of Bleak House published by Bradbury and Evans with 
	       illustrations by <name type="person" ref="browne"><forename type="first">Hablot</forename> 
	       <forename type="middle">Knight</forename> <surname>Browne</surname> </name> (also known as "Phiz").
	       The story of Bleak House follows the course of a legal dispute in the British Court of Chancery, 
	       as the Jarndyce family waits over generations to receive an inheritance they believe they deserve.
               The story is a commentary on the convoluted legal system in Britain, and the corruption inherent 
	       in it. </p>
            <p>Thanks to the serial format, Bleak House reached a wide range of audiences. The
               critical perspective towards the legal system in Bleak House would have appealed to a
               more educated population. Furthermore, the relatively afforable installments, public
               readings, and library lendings would allow the working class to access the novel.
               Eventually, <name type="person"><surname>Dickens</surname></name>'s work would achieve a 
	       global audience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>Through this edition, we are interested in examining the intertextuality between
               advertisements and different groups of readers, as well as the juxtaposition of
               advertisements and the prose text of the novel. Along the way, we provide access to a
               serialized experience of the novel, as a modern parallel to how Bleak House would
               have been read when it was first published in 1852. The digital edition also augments
               searchability and increases accessibility for a 21st-century reader.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorial">
            <p>We choose not to modernize the text, since we wish to preserve the textual impact of
               the original 1852 publication. Thankfully, the language is not too far removed from
               what modern readers are comfortable with. Instead, to supply more context, we choose
               to annotate unfamiliar terms and concepts pertaining to 19th century British legal
               culture and Bleak House as a larger text.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="maintext">
            <p/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">The novel features the fictional case, Jarndyce and Jarndyce.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Royal seal of the United Kingdom.</note>
	<div type="characters">
		<note></note>
	</div>
         </div>
         <div type="biblio">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Wiki">
                  <title ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bleak_House">Wikipedia</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="University_of_New_England">
                  <title ref="http://esthersnarrative.une.edu.au/themes-1/">University of New
                     England website</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Poetry_Foundation">
                  <title ref="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/charles-dickens">Poetry
                     Foundation</title>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
	<div type="index">
        <listPerson type="real">
           <person xml:id="dickens">
              <persName>
                 <surname type="first">Charles</surname>
		 <surname type="middle">Knight</surname>    
                 <forename>Dickens</forename>
              </persName>
              <note>
                 <p> He was one of the most well-known English authors, who had a diverse writing 
		career as a reporter, editor and essayist.</p>
              </note>
           </person>
        </listPerson>

	<listPerson type="real">
           <person xml:id="browne">
              <persName>
                 <surname>Hablot</surname>
                 <forename>Browne</forename>
              </persName>
              <note>
                 <p>An illustrator for Bradbury and Evans. His nickname is "Phiz."</p>
              </note>
           </person>
        </listPerson>
     </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
