<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="../teibp/teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bleak House Volume XVII Digital Edition</title>
            <author>Charles Dickens</author>
            <editor ref="#Alysa">Alysa Meng</editor>
            <editor ref="#Karthik">Karthik Malli</editor>
            <editor ref="#Keren">Keren Truong</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TXTDS 404/504 Spring <date when="2025">2025</date> offering at the University
               of Washington</publisher>
            <pubPlace key="Seattle, WA, USA">Seattle, Washington</pubPlace>
            <date when="2025">2025</date>
            <distributor>From University of Washington Libraries Special Collections</distributor>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Bleak House</title>
               <author key="Dickens, Charles (1812-1870)">Charles Dickens</author>
               <publisher>Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
               <pubPlace key="London, UK">London</pubPlace>
               <date>1852–1853</date>
               <note>Published in 20 installations monthly, beginning in <date when="1852-03-12">12
                     March 1852</date> and ending <date when="1853-09-12">12 September 1853</date>.
                  Our edition, No. XVII, was published <date when="1853-07-12">12 July
                     1853</date>.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>We choose not to modernize the text, since we wish to preserve the textual impact of
               the original 1852 publication. Thankfully, the language is not too far removed from
               what modern readers are comfortable with. Instead, to supply more context, we choose
               to annotate unfamiliar terms and concepts pertaining to 19th century British legal
               culture and Bleak House as a larger text.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>By Charles Dickens.<date>1852-53</date></creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">The text is in English.</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
    <front>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart> ... </titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="editorial-intro">
            <p>Charles Dickens
               is one of the most well-known English authors, who had a diverse writing career as a reporter, 
               editor and essayist. He produced 14 novels, most of which were published in serial editions. 
               This included a 20-month serialization of Bleak House published by Bradbury and Evans with 
               illustrations by <ref target="#n3">Hablot Knight Browne</ref>.
               The story of Bleak House follows the course of a legal dispute in the British <ref target="#n2">Court of Chancery</ref>, 
               as the <ref target="#n1">Jarndyce family</ref> waits over generations to receive an inheritance they believe they deserve.
               The story is a commentary on the convoluted legal system in Britain, and the corruption inherent 
               in it. </p>
            <p>Thanks to the <ref target="#n4">serial format</ref>, Bleak House reached a wide range of audiences. The
               critical perspective towards the legal system in Bleak House would have appealed to a
               more educated population. Furthermore, relatively afforable installments, public
               readings, and library lendings would allow the working class to access the novel.
               Eventually, Dickens' work would achieve a 
               global audience.</p>
            <p>Through this edition, we are interested in examining the intertextuality between
               advertisements and different groups of readers, as well as the juxtaposition of
               advertisements and the prose text of the novel. Along the way, we provide access to a
               serialized experience of the novel, as a modern parallel to how Bleak House would
               have been read when it was first published in 1852. The digital edition also augments
               searchability and increases accessibility for a 21st-century reader.</p>
            <p>We choose not to modernize the text, since we wish to preserve the textual impact of
               the original 1852 publication. Thankfully, the language is not too far removed from
               what modern readers are comfortable with. To supply more context, we choose
               to annotate unfamiliar terms and concepts pertaining to 19th-century British legal
               culture and Bleak House as a larger text.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- Section for the novel -->
         <div type="bleak-house">
            <div n="54" type="chapter" xml:id="ch54">
               <pb n="513"/>
               <note type="original" place="foot">L L</note>
               <head rend="caps">Springing a mine.</head>

               <!-- Start ch 54 text -->
               <p><hi rend="caps">Refreshed</hi> by sleep, <persName ref="bucket">Mr.
                     Bucket</persName> rises betimes in the morning, and prepares for a field-day.
                  Smartened up by the aid of a clean shirt and a wet hair-brush, with which
                  instrument, on occasions of ceremony, he lubricates such thin locks as remain to
                  him after his life of severe study, <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>
                  lays in a breakfast of two mutton chops as a foundation to work upon, together
                  with tea, eggs, toast and marmalade, on a corresponding scale. Having much enjoyed
                  these strengthening matters, and having held subtle conference with his familiar
                  demon, he confidentially instructs <persName ref="mercury">Mercury</persName>
                  <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="mercury">just to mention quietly to
                        <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, <ref target="#n5">Baronet</ref>,</persName> that
                     whenever he's ready for me, I'm ready for him.</said> A gracious message being
                  returned, that <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> will expedite
                  his dressing and join <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> in the
                     <placeName ref="library">library</placeName> within ten minutes, <persName
                     ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> repairs to that apartment; and stands before
                  the fire, with his finger on his chin, looking at the blazing coals.</p>

               <p>Thoughtful <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> is; as a man may be, with
                  weighty work to do; but composed, sure, confident. From the expression of his
                  face, he might be a famous <ref target="#n6">whist</ref>-player for a large stake — say a hundred <ref target="#n7">guineas</ref>
                  certain — with the game in his hand, but with a high reputation involved in his
                  playing his hand out to the last card, in a masterly way. Not in the least anxious
                  or disturbed is <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, when <persName
                     ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> appears; but he eyes the baronet
                  aside as he comes slowly to his easy chair, with that observant gravity of
                  yesterday, in which there might have been yesterday, but for the audacity of the
                  idea, a touch of compassion.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">I am sorry to have kept you
                     waiting, officer, but I am rather later than my usual hour this morning. I am
                     not well. The agitation, and the indignation from which I have recently
                     suffered, have been too much for me. I am subject to — <ref target="#n8">gout</ref>;</said>
                  <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> was going to say
                  indisposition, and would have said it to anybody else, but <persName ref="bucket"
                     >Mr. Bucket</persName> palpably knows all about it; <said aloud="true"
                     who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">and recent circumstances have brought it
                     on.</said></p>

               <p>As he takes his seat with some difficulty, and with an air of pain, <persName
                     ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> draws a little nearer, standing with one of
                  his large hands on the library table.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">I am not aware,
                     officer,</said>
                  <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> observes, raising his eyes to
                  his face, <said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">whether you wish us
                     to be alone; but that is entirely as you please. If you do, well and good. If
                     not, <persName ref="miss-dedlock">Miss Dedlock</persName> would be
                     interested——</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">Why, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>,</said> returns
                     <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, with his head persuasively on one
                  side, and his forefinger pendant at one ear like an ear-ring, <said aloud="true"
                     who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">we can't be too private, just at present. You
                     will presently see that we can't be too private. A lady, under any
                     circumstances, and especially in <persName ref="miss-dedlock">Miss
                        Dedlock</persName>'s elevated station of society, can't but be agreeable to
                     me; but speaking without a view to myself, I will take the liberty of assuring
                     you that I know we can't be too private.</said></p>

               <pb n="514"/>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">That is enough.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">So much so, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>,</said>
                  <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> resumes, <said aloud="true"
                     who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">that I was on the point of asking your
                     permission to turn the key in the door.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">By all means.</said>
                  <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> skilfully and softly takes that
                  precaution; stooping on his knee for a moment, from mere force of habit, so to
                  adjust the key in the lock as that no one shall peep in from the outerside.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="sir-dedlock"
                        >Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, I mentioned yesterday evening,
                     that I wanted but a very little to complete this case. I have now completed it,
                     and collected proof against the person who did this crime.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">Against the
                  soldier?</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">No, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock</persName>; not the
                  soldier.</said></p>
               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> looks astounded, and
                  inquires, <said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">Is the man in
                     custody?</said></p>
               <p><persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> tells him, after a pause, <said
                     aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">It was a woman.</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> leans back in his chair, and
                  breathlessly ejaculates, <said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">Good
                     Heaven!</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">Now, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>,</said>
                  <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> begins, standing over him with one
                  hand spread out on the library table, and the forefinger of the other in
                  impressive use, <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">it's my duty
                     to prepare you for a train of circumstances that may, and I go so far as to say
                     that will, give you a shock. But <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester
                        Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, you are a gentleman; and I know what a
                     gentleman is, and what a gentleman is capable of. A gentleman can bear a shock,
                     when it must come, boldly and steadily. A gentleman can make up his mind to
                     stand up against almost any blow. Why, take yourself, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>. If there's a
                     blow to be inflicted on you, you naturally think of your family. You ask
                     yourself, how would all them ancestors of yours, away to Julius Cæsar—not to go
                     beyond him at present—have borne that blow; you remember scores of them that
                     would have borne it well; and you bear it well on their accounts, and to
                     maintain the family credit. That's the way you argue, and that's the way you
                     act, <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock,
                     Baronet</persName>.</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName>, leaning back in his chair,
                  and grasping the elbows, sits looking at him with a stony face.</p>


               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">Now, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock</persName>,</said> proceeds
                     <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, <said aloud="true" who="bucket"
                     toWhom="sir-dedlock">thus preparing you, let me beg of you not to trouble your
                     mind, for a moment, as to anything having come to <hi rend="it">my</hi>
                     knowledge. I know so much about so many characters, high and low, that a piece
                     of information more or less, don't signify a straw. I don't suppose there's a
                     move on the board that would surprise <hi rend="it">me</hi>; and as to this or
                     that move having taken place, why my knowing it is no odds at all; any possible
                     move whatever (provided it's in a wrong direction) being a probable move
                     according to my experience. Therefore what I say to you, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, is, don't you
                     go and let yourself be put out of the way, because of my knowing anything of
                     your family affairs.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">I thank you for your
                     preparation,</said> returns <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                     Leicester</persName>, after a silence, without moving hand, foot, or feature;
                     <said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">which I hope is not
                     necessary, though I give it credit for being well intended. Be so good as to go
                     on. Also;</said>
                  <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> seems to shrink in the shadow
                  of his figure; <said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">also, to take
                     a seat, if you have no objection.</said></p>

               <p>None at all. <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> brings a chair, and
                  diminishes his shadow.</p>

               <pb n="515"/>
               <note type="original" place="foot">L L 2</note>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">Now, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, with this short
                     preface, I come to the point. <persName ref="lady-dedlock">Lady
                        Dedlock</persName>———</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> raises himself in his seat,
                  and stares at him fiercely. <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> brings
                  the finger into play as an <ref target="#n9">emollient</ref>.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="lady-dedlock"
                        >Lady Dedlock</persName>, you see, she's universally admired. That's what
                        <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName> is; she's universally
                     admired,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">I would greatly prefer,
                        <persName ref="bucket">officer</persName>,</said>
                  <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> returns, stiffly, <said
                     aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket"><persName ref="lady-dedlock">my
                        Lady</persName>'s name being entirely omitted from this
                  discussion.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">So would I, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, but——it's
                     impossible.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">Impossible?</said></p>

               <p>Mr. Bucket shakes his relentless head.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="sir-dedlock"
                        >Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, it's altogether impossible. What
                     I have got to say, is about <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her
                        Ladyship</persName>. She is the pivot it all turns on.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket"><persName ref="bucket"
                        >Officer</persName>,</said> retorts <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                     Leicester</persName>, with a fiery eye, and a guivering lip, <said aloud="true"
                     who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">you know your duty. Do your duty; but be
                     careful not to overstep it. I would not suffer it. I would not endure it. You
                     bring <persName ref="lady-dedlock">my Lady</persName>'s name into this
                     communication, upon your responsibility—upon your responsibility. <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">My Lady</persName>'s name is not a name for common
                     persons to triffe with!</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="sir-dedlock"
                        >Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, I say what I must say; and no
                     more.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">I hope it may prove so. Very
                     well. Go on. Go on, sir!</said></p>

               <p>Glancing at the angry eyes which now avoid him, and at the angry figure trembling
                  from head to foot, yet striving to be still, <persName ref="bucket">Mr.
                     Bucket</persName> feels his way with his forefinger, and in a low voice
                  proceeds.</p>


               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="sir-dedlock"
                        >Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, it becomes my duty to tell you
                     that the deceased <persName ref="tulkinghorn">Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName> long
                     entertained mistrusts and suspicions of <persName ref="lady-dedlock">Lady
                        Dedlock</persName>.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket">If he had dared to breathe
                     them to me, sir—which he never did—I would have killed him myself!</said>
                  exclaims <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName>, striking his hand
                  upon the table. But, in the very heat and fury of the act, he stops, fixed by the
                  knowing eyes of <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, whose forefinger is
                  slowly going, and who, with mingled confidence and patience, shakes his head.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="sir-dedlock"
                        >Sir Leicester Dedlock</persName>, the deceased <persName ref="tulkinghorn"
                        >Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName> was deep and close; and what he fully had in his
                     mind in the very beginning, I can't quite take upon myself to say. But I know
                     from his lips, that he long ago suspected <persName ref="lady-dedlock">Lady
                        Dedlock</persName> of having discovered, through the sight of some
                     handwriting—in this very house, and when you yourself, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock</persName>, were present—the
                     existence, in great poverty, of a certain person, who had been her lover before
                     you courted her, and who ought to have been her husband;</said>
                  <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> stops, and deliberately repeats,
                     <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">ought to have been her
                     husband; not a doubt about it. I know from his lips, that when that person soon
                     afterwards died, he suspected <persName ref="lady-dedlock">Lady
                        Dedlock</persName> of visiting his wretched lodging, and his <ref target="#n10">wretcheder</ref>
                     grave, alone and in secret. I know from my own inquiries, and through my eyes
                     and ears, that <persName ref="lady-dedlock">Lady Dedlock</persName> did make
                     such visit, in the dress of her own maid; for the deceased <persName
                        ref="tulkinghorn">Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName> employed me to <term
                        type="legal" ref="reckon-up">reckon up</term>
                     <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName>—if you'll excuse my making
                     use of the term we commonly employ—and I <term type="legal" ref="reckon-up"
                        >reckoned her up</term>, so far, completely. I confronted the maid, in the
                     chambers in <placeName ref="lincoln-inn-fields">Lincoln's Inn
                        Fields</placeName>, with a witness who had been <persName ref="lady-dedlock"
                        >Lady Dedlock</persName>'s guide; and there couldn't be the shadow of a
                     doubt <pb n="516"/>that she had worn the young woman's dress, unknown to her.
                        <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, I did
                     endeavour to pave the way a little towards these unpleasant disclosures,
                     yesterday, by saying that very strange things happened even in high families
                     sometimes. All this, and more, has happened in your own family, and to and
                     through <persName ref="lady-dedlock">your own Lady</persName>. It's my belief
                     that the deceased <persName ref="tulkinghorn">Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName>
                     followed up these inquiried to the hour of his death; and that he and <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">Lady Dedlock</persName> even had bad blood between them
                     upon the matter, that very night. Now, only you put that to <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">Lady Dedlock</persName>, <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                        Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>; and ask <persName ref="lady-dedlock"
                        >her Ladyship</persName> whether, even after he had left here, she didn't go
                     down to his chambers with the intention of saying something further to him,
                     dressed in a loose black mantle with a deep fringe to it.</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> sits like a statue, gazing at
                  the cruel finger that is probing the life-blood of his heart.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">You put that to <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName>, <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                        Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, from me, <persName ref="bucket"
                        >Inspector Bucket</persName> of the Detective. And if <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName> makes any difficulty about
                     admitting of it, you tell her that it's no use; that <persName ref="bucket"
                        >Inspector Bucket</persName> knows it, and knows that she passed the soldier
                     as you called him (though he's not in the army now), and knows that she knows
                     she passed him, on the staircase. Now, <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                        Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, why do I relate all this?</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName>, who has covered his face
                  with his hands, uttering a single groan, requests him to pause for a moment. By
                  and by, he takes his hands away; and so preserves his dignity and outward
                  calmness, though there is no more color in his face than in his white hair, that
                     <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> is a little awed by him. Something
                  frozen and fixed is upon his manner, over and above its usual shell of
                  haughtiness; and <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> soon detects an
                  unusual slowness in his speech, with now and then a curious trouble in beginning,
                  which occasions him to utter inarticulate sounds. With such sounds, he now breaks
                  silence; soon, however, controlling himself to say, that he does not comprehend
                  why a gentleman so faithful and zealous as the late <persName ref="tulkinghorn"
                     >Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName> should have communicated to him nothing of this
                  painful, this distressing, this unlooked-for, this overwhelming, this incredible
                  intelligence.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock">Again, <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>,</said> returns
                     <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, <said aloud="true" who="bucket"
                     toWhom="sir-dedlock">put it to <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her
                        Ladyship</persName> to clear that up. Put it to her <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">Ladyship</persName>, if you think right, from <persName
                        ref="bucket">Inspector Bucket</persName> of the Detective. You'll find, or
                     I'm much mistaken, that the deceased <persName ref="tulkinghorn">Mr.
                        Tulkinghorn</persName> had the intention of communicating the whole to you,
                     as soon as he considered it ripe; and further, that he had given <persName
                        ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName> so to understand. Why, he might
                     have been going to reveal it on the very morning when I examined the body! You
                     don't know what I'm going to say and do, five minutes from this present time,
                        <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>; and
                     supposing l was to be picked off now, you might wonder why I hadn't done it,
                     don't you see?</said></p>

               <p>True. <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName>, avoiding, with some
                  trouble, those obtrusive sounds, says, <said aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock"
                     toWhom="bucket">True.</said> At this juncture, a considerable noise of voices
                  is heard in the hall. <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, after
                  listening, goes to the library-door, softly unlocks and opens it, and listens
                  again. Then he draws in his head, and whispers, hurriedly, but composedly, <said
                     aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="sir-dedlock"><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                        Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, this unfortunate family affair has
                     taken air, as I expected it <pb n="517"/> might; the deceased Mr. Tulkinghorn
                     being cut down so sudden. The chance to hush it, is to let in these people now
                     in a wrangle with your footmen. Would you mind sitting quiet—on the family
                     account—while I reckon 'em up? And would you just throw in a nod, when I seem
                     to ask you for it?</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> indistinctly answers, <said
                     aloud="true" who="sir-dedlock" toWhom="bucket"><persName ref="bucket"
                        >Officer</persName>. The best you can, the best you can!</said> and
                     <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, with a nod and a sagacious crook
                  of the forefinger, slips down into the hall, where the voices quickly die away. He
                  is not long in returning, a few paces ahead of <persName ref="mercury"
                     >Mercury</persName>, and a brother deity also powdered and in peach-blossom
                  smalls, who bear between them a chair in which is an incapable old man. Another
                  man and two women come behind. Directing the pitching of the chair, in an affable
                  and easy manner, <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> dismisses the
                     <persName ref="mercuries">Mercuries</persName>, and locks the door again.
                     <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester</persName> looks on at this invasion
                  of the sacred <placeName ref="precinct">precincts</placeName> with an icy
                  stare.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket">Now, perhaps you may know me, ladies and
                     gentlemen,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, in a
                  confidential voice. <said aloud="true" who="bucket">I am <persName ref="bucket"
                        >Inspector Bucket</persName> of the Detective, I am; and
                  this,</said>producing the tip of his convenient little staff from his
                  breast-pocket, <said aloud="true" who="bucket">is my authority. Now, you wanted to
                     see <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>.
                     Well! You do see him; and, mind you, it ain't every one as is admitted to that
                     honor. Your name, old gentleman, is <persName ref="smallweed"
                        >Smallweed</persName>; that's what your name is; I know it well.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">Well, and you never heard any
                     harm of it!</said> cries <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> in
                  a shrill loud voice.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">You don't happen to know why
                     they killed the pig, do you?</said> retorts <persName ref="bucket">Mr.
                     Bucket</persName>, with a stedfast look, but without loss of temper.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">No!</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">Why, they killed him,</said>
                  says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, <said aloud="true" who="bucket"
                     toWhom="smallweed">on account of his having so much cheek. Don't <hi rend="it"
                        >you</hi> get into the same position, because it isn't worthy of you. You
                     ain't in the habit of conversing with a deaf person, are you?</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">Yes,</said> snarls <persName
                     ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName>, <said aloud="true" who="smallweed"
                     toWhom="bucket">my wife's deaf.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">That accounts for your pitching
                     your voice so high. But as she ain't here, just pitch it an octave or two
                     lower, will you, and I'll not only be obliged to you, but it'll do you more
                     credit,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>. <said
                     aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">This other gentleman is in the
                     preaching line, I think?</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">Name of <persName
                        ref="mr-chadband">Chadband</persName>,</said>
                  <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> puts in, speaking henceforth in
                  a much lower key.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="mrs-chadband">Once had a friend and
                     brother <term type="legal" ref="serjeant">serjeant</term> of the same
                     name,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, offering his
                  hand, <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="mrs-chadband">and consequently feel
                     a liking for it. <persName ref="mrs-chadband">Mrs. Chadband</persName>, no
                     doubt?</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">And <persName ref="mrs-snagsby"
                        >Mrs. Snagsby</persName>,</said>
                  <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> introduces.</p>

               <!-- This is directed towards a group of people -->
               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket"><persName ref="mr-snagsby">Husband</persName> a
                        <term type="legal" ref="stationer">law stationer</term>, and a friend of my
                     own,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>. <said
                     aloud="true" who="bucket">Love him like a brother!—Now, what's up?</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">Do you mean what business have
                     we come upon?</said>
                  <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> asks, a little dashed by the
                  suddenness of this turn.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket">Ah! You know what I mean. Let us hear what it's
                     all about in presence of <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock,
                        Baronet</persName>. Come. </said></p>

               <p><persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName>, beckoning <persName
                     ref="mr-chadband">Mr. Chadband</persName>, takes a moment's counsel with him in
                  a whisper. <persName ref="mr-chadband">Mr. Chadband</persName>, expressing a
                  considerable <pb n="518"/>amount of oil from the pores of his forchead and the
                  palms of his hands, says aloud, <said aloud="true" who="mr-chadband"
                     toWhom="smallweed">Yes. You first!</said> and retires to his former place.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">I was the client and friend of
                        <persName ref="tulkinghorn">Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName>,</said> pipes
                     <persName ref="smallweed">Grandfather Smallweed</persName>, then; <said
                     aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">I did business with him. I was
                     useful to him, and he was useful to me. <persName ref="krook">Krook</persName>,
                     dead and gone, was my brother in-law. He was own brother to a brimstone
                     magpie—leastways <persName ref="mrs-smallweed">Mrs. Smallweed</persName>. I
                     come in to <persName ref="krook">Krook</persName>'s property. I examined all
                     his papers and all his effects. They was all dug out under my eyes. There was a
                     bundle of letters belonging to a dead and gone lodger, as was hid away at the
                     back of a shelf in the side of <persName ref="krook-cat">Lady Jane</persName>'s
                     bed—his cat's bed. He hid an manner of things away, everywheres. <persName
                        ref="tulkinghorn">Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName> wanted 'em and got'em, but I
                     looked 'em over first. I'm a man of business, and I took a squint at 'em. They
                     was letters from the lodger's sweetheart, and she signed <persName
                        ref="honoria">Honoria</persName>. Dear me, that's not a common name,
                        <persName ref="honoria">Honoria</persName>, is it? There's no lady in this
                     house that signs <persName ref="honoria">Honoria</persName>, is there? O no. I
                     don't think so! O no, I don't think so! And not in the same hand, perhaps? O
                     no, I don't think so!</said></p>

               <p>Here <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName>, seized with a fit of
                  coughing in the midst of his triumph, breaks off to ejaculate <said aloud="true"
                     who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">O dear me! O Lord! I'm shaken all to
                     pieces!</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">Now, when you're ready,</said>
                  says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, after awaiting his recovery,
                     <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">to come to anything that
                     concerns <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>,
                     here the gentleman sits, you know.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">Haven't I come to it, <persName
                        ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>?</said> cries Grandfather Smallweed.
                     <said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">Isn't the gentleman
                     concerned yet? Not with <persName ref="captain-hawdon">Captain
                        Hawdon</persName> and his ever affectionate <persName ref="honoria"
                        >Honoria</persName>, and their child into the bargain? Come, then, I want to
                     know where those letters are. That concerns me, if it don't concern <persName
                        ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock</persName>. I will know where they
                     are. I won't have 'em disappear so quietly. I handed 'em over to my friend and
                     solicitor, <persName ref="tulkinghorn">Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName>; not to
                     anybody else.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">Why he paid you for them, you
                     know, and handsome too,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr.
                     Bucket</persName>.</p>
               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">I don't care for that. I want
                     to know who's got'em. And I tell you what we want—what we all here want, Mr.
                     Bucket. We want more pains-taking and search-making into this murder. We know
                     where the interest and the motive was, and you have not done enough. If
                        <persName ref="george">George</persName> the vagabond dragoon had any hand
                     in it, he was only an accomplice, and was set on. You know what I mean as well
                     as any man.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">Now I tell you what,</said>
                  says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, instantaneously altering his
                  manner, coming close to him, and communicating an extraordinary fascination to the
                  forefinger, <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">I am damned if I am
                     a going to have my case spoilt, or interfered with, or anticipated by so much
                     as half a second of time, by any human being in creation. <hi rend="it"
                        >You</hi> want more pains-taking and search-making? <hi rend="it">You</hi>
                     do? Do you see this hand, and do you think that <hi rend="it">I</hi> don't know
                     the right time to stretch it out, and put it on the arm that fired that
                     shot?</said></p>

               <p>Such is the dread power of the man, and so terribly evident it is that he makes no
                  idle boast, that <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> begins to
                  apologise. <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, dismissing his sudden
                  anger, checks him.</p>

               <p>The advice I give you, is, don't you trouble your head about the murder. That's my
                  affair. You keep half an eye on the newspapers; <pb n="519"/> and I shouldn't
                  wonder if you was to read something about it before long, if you look sharp. I
                  know my business, and that's all I've got to say to you on that subject. Now about
                  those letters. You want to know whos got'em. I don't mind telling you. <hi
                     rend="it">I</hi> have got 'em. Is that the packet?</p>

               <p><persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> looks, with greedy eyes, at the
                  little bundle <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> produces from a
                  mysterious part of his coat, and identifies it as the same.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">What have you got to say
                     next?</said> asks <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>. <said
                     aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">Now, don't open your mouth too
                     wide, because you don't look handsome when you do it.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="smallweed" toWhom="bucket">I want five hundred
                     pound.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">No, you don't; you mean
                     fifty,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, humorously. It
                  appears, however, that <persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> means
                  five hundred.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">That is, I am deputed by
                        <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir Leicester Dedlock, Baronet</persName>, to
                     consider (without admitting or promising anything) this bit of business,</said>
                  says <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>; <persName ref="sir-dedlock">Sir
                     Leicester</persName> mechanically bows his head; <said aloud="true"
                     who="bucket" toWhom="smallweed">and you ask me to consider a proposal of five
                     hundred pound. Why, it's an unreasonable proposal! Two fifty would be bad
                     enough, but better than that. Hadn't you better say two fifty?</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="smallweed">Mr. Smallweed</persName> is quite clear that he had
                  better not.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket">Then,</said> says <persName ref="bucket">Mr.
                     Bucket</persName>, <said aloud="true" who="bucket">let's hear <persName
                        ref="mr-chadband">Mr. Chadband</persName>. Lord! Many a time I've heard my
                     old fellow-<term type="legal" ref="serjeant">serjeant</term> of that name; and
                     a moderate man he was in all respects, as ever I come across!</said></p>

               <p>Thus invited, <persName ref="mr-chadband">Mr. Chadband</persName> steps forth,
                  and, after a little sleek smiling and a little oil-grinding with the palms of his
                  hands, delivers himself as follows:</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="mr-chadband">My friends, we are now—<persName
                        ref="mrs-chadband">Rachael</persName> my wife, and I—in the mansions of the
                     rich and great. Why are we now in the mansions of the rich and great, my
                     friends? Is it because we are invited? Because we are bidden to feast with
                     them, because we are bidden to rejoice with them, because we are bidden to play
                     the lute with them, because we are bidden to dance with them? No. Then why are
                     we here, my friends? Air we in possession of a sinful secret, and doe we
                     require corn, and wine, and oil—or, what is much the same thing, money—for the
                     keeping thereof? Probably so, my friends.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="mr-chadband">You're a man of business, you
                     are,</said> returns <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>, very
                  attentive; <said aloud="true" who="bucket" toWhom="mr-chadband">and consequently
                     you're going on to mention what the nature of your secret is. You are right.
                     You couldn't do better.</said></p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="mr-chadband" toWhom="bucket">Let us then, my brother, in a
                     spirit of love,</said> says Mr. Chadband, with a cunning eye, <said
                     aloud="true" who="mr-chadband">proceed untoe it.</said>
                  <said aloud="true" who="mr-chadband" toWhom="mrs-chadband"><persName
                        ref="mrs-chadband">Rachael</persName> my wife, advance!</said></p>

               <p><persName ref="mrs-chadband">Mrs. Chadband</persName>, more than ready, so
                  advances as to jostle her husband into the back-ground, and confronts <persName
                     ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName> with a hard frowning smile.</p>

               <p><said aloud="true" who="mrs-chadband" toWhom="bucket">Since you want to know what
                     we know,</said> says she, <said aloud="true" who="mrs-chadband" toWhom="bucket"
                     >I'll tell you. I helped to bring up <persName ref="miss-hawdon">Miss
                        Hawdon</persName>, <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName>'s
                     daughter. I was in the service of her <persName ref="lady-dedlock-sister"
                        >Ladyship's sister</persName>, who was very sensitive to the disgrace
                        <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName> brought upon her, and
                     gave out, even to <persName ref="lady-dedlock">her Ladyship</persName>, that
                     the child was dead—she was very nearly so—when she was born. But she's alive,
                     and I know her.</said> With these words, and a laugh, and laying a bitter
                  stress on the word <quote>Ladyship,</quote> Mrs. Chadband folds her arms, and
                  looks implacably at <persName ref="bucket">Mr. Bucket</persName>.</p>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
     <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">The novel features the fictional case, Jarndyce and Jarndyce.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">The Court of Chancery followed rules to avoid a slow pace and inequities of common laws.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Browne was a British artist and illustrator.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Novels in the 1800s were often published in serialized format over a
               number of monthly editions. Individual editions usually ended with a cliffhanger.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">A baronet is a minor member of British nobility, above a knight. They are addressed as "Sir".</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">A 4 player trick-taking card game, popular in 19th century England.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">A historical British coin, worth 21 shillings. It was demonetized in 1816.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">A form of inflammatory arthritis, significantly more common in the 19th century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">A substance that soothes and moisturizes the skin.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">Meaning more wretched.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="biblio">
            <bibl xml:id="lloyd2007"> <author><surname>Lloyd</surname>, <forename>Amy</forename></author>. <title>Advertising in 19th Century British Newspapers (Amy J. Lloyd)</title>. <publisher>Gale</publisher>, <date>2007</date>, <ptr target="www.gale.com/intl/essays/amy-j-lloyd-advertising."/></bibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="poetry2019"><author>Poetry Foundation</author>. <title>Poetry Foundation</title>. <publisher>Poetry Foundation</publisher>, <date>2019</date>, <ptr target="www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/charles-dickens"/></bibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="steinlight2006"><author><surname>Steinlight</surname>, <forename>Emily</forename></author>. <title>“AntiBleak House”: Advertising and the Victorian Novel</title>. <publisher>JSTOR</publisher>, <date>2006</date> <ptr target="www.jstor.org/stable/30219643, https://doi.org/10.2307/30219643."/></bibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="england2014"><author>University of England AU</author>. <title>Introduction: Themes Dickens</title>. <publisher>Une.edu.au</publisher>, <date>2014</date>, <ptr target="esthersnarrative.une.edu.au/themes-1/."/></bibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="wiki2019"><author>Wikipedia Contributors</author>. <title>Bleak House</title>. <publisher>Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation</publisher>, <date>1 Dec. 2019</date>, <ptr target="en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bleak_House."/></bibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
   
   <standOff>
      <!-- characters index -->
      <listPerson>
         <person xml:id="bucket">
            <persName>Inspector Bucket</persName>
            <note>The police detective trying to solve the Tulkinghorn murder mystery.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mr-chadband">
            <persName>Mr. Chadband</persName>
            <note>The Reverend Mr. Chadband is Mrs. Chadband's husband and a clegyman.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mrs-chadband">
            <persName>Mrs. Chadband</persName>
            <note>Also known as Mrs. Rachael, Miss Barbary's servant.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="sir-dedlock">
            <persName>Sir Leicester Dedlock</persName>
            <note>A baronet, proud of his rank, unaware of his wife's (Lady Dedlock's) secret.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="lady-dedlock">
            <persName>Lady Dedlock</persName>
            <note>The wife of Sir Leicester Dedlock. Also referred to as Honoria.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="miss-dedlock">
            <persName>Miss Dedlock</persName>
            <note>Lady Dedlock before her marriage.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="honoria">
            <persName>Honoria</persName>
            <note>A women previously in a relationship with Captain Hawdon. She is revealed to be Lady Dedlock in Chapter 29.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="lady-dedlock-sister">
            <persName>Miss Barbary</persName>
            <note>Lady Dedlock's sister.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="george">
            <persName>George Rouncewell</persName>
            <note>The son of Mrs. Rouncewell who is falsely arrested for Tulkinghorn's murder.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="captain-hawdon">
            <persName>Captain Hawdon</persName>
            <note>A law writer and Lady Dedlock's former lover.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="miss-hawdon">
            <persName>Miss Hawdon</persName>
            <note>The daughter of Lady Dedlock.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="krook-cat">
            <persName>Lady Jane</persName>
            <note>Krook's cat.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="krook">
            <persName>Krook</persName>
            <note>A shop owner and the landlord of Captain Hawdon.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mercury">
            <persName>Mercury</persName>
            <note>A servant at Chesney Wold.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mercuries">
            <persName>Mercuries</persName>
            <note>In general, referring to servants at Chesney Wold.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="smallweed">
            <persName>Mr. Smallweed</persName>
            <note>Mrs. Smallweed's husband.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mrs-smallweed">
            <persName>Mrs. Smallweed</persName>
            <note>Krook's sister.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mr-snagsby">
            <persName>Mr. Snagsby</persName>
            <note>A law-stationer and Mrs. Snagsby's husband.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="mrs-snagsby">
            <persName>Mrs. Snagsby</persName>
            <note>One of Mr. Chadband's parishioners.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="tulkinghorn">
            <persName>Mr. Tulkinghorn</persName>
            <note>A solicitor who threatened to expose a secret in Lady Dedlock's past and is murdered.</note>
         </person>
      </listPerson>
      
      <!-- places index -->
      <listPlace>
         <place xml:id="library">
            <note>The library in Bleak House, the Dedlock estate.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="lincoln-inn-fields">
            <note>Historic public square and garden located in the Holborn area of London, connected to the Court of Chancery (legal institution).</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="precinct">
            <note>A legal precinct, likely near Lincoln’s Inn Fields.
            </note>
         </place>
         
      </listPlace>
      
      <!-- legal annotations -->
      <list>
         <item xml:id="reckon-up">
            <term>To reckon up</term>
            <note>To calculate the total amount owed by a creditor.</note>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="serjeant">
            <term>Serjeant</term>
            <note>Short for serjeant-in-law, a member of an order of barristers at the English and Irish Bar.</note>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="stationer">
            <term>Stationer</term>
            <note>A merchant who sells paper, forms, and stationery items used by lawyers and other legal professionals.</note>
         </item>
      </list>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
