<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles</title>
            <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
            <editor>Em Backstrom</editor>
            <editor>Blue Jordan</editor>
            <editor>Rowan Herron</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>We plan to publish this edition of The Hound of the Baskervilles in June 2025.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <series>
                  <title>The Strand Magazine</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
               </series>
               <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
               <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles></title>
               <publisher>George Newnes LTD.</publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>George Newnes LTD.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>7, 8, 9, 10, 11, &amp; 12, Southampton Street,</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>and Exeter Street, London</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </pubPlace>
               <date when="1901-08">August 1901</date>
               <availability>
                  <p>Held by UW Special Collections under the call number 051 SM v.22.</p>
               </availability>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This edition was created as part of TXTDS 404 at the University of Washington over
               the course of Spring Quarter 2025. Our first goal with this digital edition is to
               reproduce the copytext as close to the original as possible, including text itself as
               well as form, format, and illustrations, using the tools of digital editing such as
               XML, TEI, HTML, and CSS. Our second goal is to include interesting contextual
               information to the story to enrich and contextualize a reader's experience by
               connecting readers with Doyle’s history with The Strand and also to the geographic
               elements in the story and its mediation. We are also interested in how historic
               audiences received and reacted to the story. Our edition, including our HTML and CSS
               formatting of the TEI encoding, was published online using the Vergil web publishing
               system.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Our aim with editiorial decisions is to avoid altering the text and its presentation
               minimally. Original spelling, format, and punctuation is recreated wherever we can. We will
               normalize certain punctuation that resembles em dashes and dashes but are neither.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2025-05-11">Began creating draft TEI Header</change>
            <change when="2025-05-12">Finish draft TEI Header</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
