<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles</title>
            <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
            <editor>Em Backstrom</editor>
            <editor>Blue Jordan</editor>
            <editor>Rowan Herron</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This edition was created as part of TXTDS four oh four at the University of Washington over the course of Spring Quarter 2025. Our first goal with this digital edition is to reproduce the copytext as close to the original as possible, including text itself as well as form, format, and illustrations, using the tools of digital editing such as XML, TEI, HTML, and CSS. Our second goal is to include interesting contextual information to the story to enrich and contextualize a reader's experience by connecting readers with Doyle’s history with The Strand and also to the geographic elements in the story and its mediation. We are also interested in how historic audiences received and reacted to the story. Our edition, including our HTML and CSS formatting of the TEI encoding, was published online using the Vergil web publishing system.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Our source text is “The Hound of the Baskervilles” by Arthur Conan Doyle as it was first published in Strand Magazine, in August 1901. The Magazine was published in London, England. The story text consists of pages 122 through 132 (11 total) of the August issue. It also contains seven illustrations with captions for the actions they depict, most of which are nestled within the text. The first page of text also doubles as the title page for that month’s issue. Our specific copytext is a bound volume of Strand Magazine issues which is held in Special Collections at University of Washington Libraries under the call number 051 SM v.22. This is the 22nd volume of collected magazine issues and was published by the Strand in December of 1901.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
