<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles</title>
            <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
            <editor>Em Backstrom</editor>
            <editor>Blue Jordan</editor>
            <editor>Rowan Herron</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>We plan to publish this edition of The Hound of the Baskervilles in June 2025.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <series>
                  <title>The Strand Magazine</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
               </series>
               <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
               <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles></title>
               <publisher>George Newnes LTD.</publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>George Newnes LTD.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>7, 8, 9, 10, 11, &amp; 12, Southampton Street,</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>and Exeter Street, London</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </pubPlace>
               <date when="1901-08">August 1901</date>
               <availability>
                  <p>Held by UW Special Collections under the call number 051 SM v.22.</p>
               </availability>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This edition was created as part of TXTDS 404 at the University of Washington over
               the course of Spring Quarter 2025. Our first goal with this digital edition is to
               reproduce the copytext as close to the original as possible, including text itself as
               well as form, format, and illustrations, using the tools of digital editing such as
               XML, TEI, HTML, and CSS. Our second goal is to include interesting contextual
               information to the story to enrich and contextualize a reader's experience by
               connecting readers with Doyle’s history with The Strand and also to the geographic
               elements in the story and its mediation. We are also interested in how historic
               audiences received and reacted to the story. Our edition, including our HTML and CSS
               formatting of the TEI encoding, was published online using the Vergil web publishing
               system.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Our aim with editiorial decisions is to avoid altering the text and its presentation
               minimally. Original spelling, format, and punctuation is recreated wherever we can.
               We will normalize certain punctuation that resembles em dashes and dashes but are
               neither.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2025-05-11">Began creating draft TEI Header</change>
            <change when="2025-05-12">Finish draft TEI Header</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front> </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="123"/>
         <head><lb/>The Strand Magazine. <lb/>Vol. xxii. August, 1901. No. 128. <lb/>The Hound of
            the Baskervilles.* <lb/>ANOTHER ADVENTURE OF<lb/>SHERLOCK HOLMES. <lb/>BY CONAN
            DOYLE.</head>
         <cb/>
         <div type="chapter" n="1">
            <ab>CHAPTER I.</ab>
            <ab>MR. SHERLOCK HOLMES.</ab>
            <p>MR. SHERLOCK HOLMES, <lb break="no"/>who was usually very late in <lb break="no"/>the
               mornings, save upon those <lb break="no"/>not infrequent occasions when <lb
                  break="no"/>he was up all night, was seated <lb break="no"/>at the breakfast
               table. I stood <lb break="no"/>upon the hearth-rug and picked up the stick <lb
                  break="no"/>which our visitor had left behind him the night <lb break="no"
               />before. It was a fine, thick piece of wood, <lb break="no"/>bulbous-headed, of the
               sort which is known <lb break="no"/>as a "Penang lawyer." Just under the head <lb
                  break="no"/>was a broad silver band, nearly an inch <lb break="no"/>across. "To
               James Mortimer, M. R. C. S., <lb break="no"/>from his friends of the C. C. H.," was
               engraved <lb break="no"/>upon it, with the date "1884." It was just <lb break="no"
               />such a stick as the old-fashioned family <lb break="no"/>practitioner used to
               carry—dignified, solid, <lb break="no"/>and reassuring.</p>
            <p><s>"Well, Watson, what do you make of it?"</s></p>
            <p>Holmes was sitting with his back to me, <lb break="no"/>and I had given him no sign
               of my occupa-<lb break="yes"/>tion.</p>
            <p><s>"How did you know what I was doing? <lb break="no"/>I believe you have eyes in the
                  back of your <lb break="no"/>head."</s></p>
            <p><s>"I have, at least, a well-polished silver-<lb break="no"/>plated coffee-pot in
                  front of me,"</s> said he. <lb break="no"/><s>"But, tell me, Watson, what do you
                  make of <lb break="no"/>our visitor's stick? Since we have been so <lb break="no"
                  />unfortunate as to miss him and have no <lb break="no"/>notion of his errand,
                  this accidental souvenir <lb break="no"/>becomes of importance. Let me hear you
                     <lb break="no"/>reconstruct the man by an examination of it."</s></p>
            <p><s>"I think," said I, following as far as I could <lb break="no"/>the methods of my
                  companion, "that Dr. <lb break="no"/>Mortimer is a successful elderly medical
                     man,<fw type="-----">
                     <!--what should we call this??????????-->* This story owes its inception to my
                     friend, Mr. Fletcher Robinson, who has helped me both in the general plot and
                     in the local details.—A. C. D.</fw><cb/><lb break="no"/>well-esteemed, since
                  those who know him <lb break="no"/>give him this mark of their
               appreciation."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Good!"</s> said Holmes. <s>"Excellent!"</s></p>
            <p><s>"I think also that the probability is in <lb break="no"/>favour of his being a
                  country practitioner <lb break="no"/>who does a great deal of his visiting on
                  foot."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Why so?"</s></p>
            <p><s>"Because this stick, though originally a <lb break="no"/>very handsome one, has
                  been so knocked <lb break="no"/>about that I can hardly imagine a town <lb
                     break="no"/>practitioner carrying it. The thick iron <lb break="no"/>ferrule is
                  worn down, so it is evident that he <lb break="no"/>has done a great amount of
                  walking with it."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Perfectly sound !"</s> said Holmes.</p>
            <p><s>"And then again, there is the 'friends of<lb break="no"/> the C.C.H.' I should
                  guess that to be the <lb break="no"/>Something Hunt, the local hunt to whose <lb
                     break="no"/>members he has possibly given some surgical <lb break="no"
                  />assistance, and which has made him a small <lb break="no"/>presentation in
                  return."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Really, Watson, you excel yourself,"</s> said <lb break="no"/>Holmes, pushing
               back his chair and lighting <lb break="no"/>a cigarette. <s>"I am bound to say that
                  in all <lb break="no"/>the accounts which you have been so good <lb break="no"/>as
                  to give of my own small achievements you <lb break="no"/>have habitually
                  underrated your own abilities. <lb break="no"/>It may be that you are not yourself
                  luminous, <lb break="no"/>but you are a conductor of light. Some <lb break="no"
                  />people without possessing genius have a <lb break="no"/>remarkable power of
                  stimulating it. I con-<lb break="yes"/>fess, my dear fellow, that I am very much
                  in <lb break="no"/>your debt."</s></p>
            <p>He had never said as much before, and I <lb break="no"/>must admit that his words
               gave me keen <lb break="no"/>pleasure, for I had often been piqued by his <lb
                  break="no"/>indifference to my admiration and to the <lb break="no"/>attempts
               which I had made to give publicity <lb break="no"/>to his methods. I was proud too to
               think <lb break="no"/>that I had so far mastered his system as to <lb break="no"
               />apply it in a way which earned his approval. <lb break="no"/>He now took the stick
               from my hands<fw>Vol. xxii.-16.</fw><pb n="124"/><fw type="RunnningHead" rend="caps"
                  >124 The Strand Magazine.</fw>
            </p>




            <pb n="126"/>
            <fw>126 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>




         </div>
         <div type="chapter" n="2"> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
