<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles</title>
            <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
            <editor>Em Backstrom</editor>
            <editor>Blue Jordan</editor>
            <editor>Rowan Herron</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>We plan to publish this edition of The Hound of the Baskervilles in June 2025.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <series>
                  <title>The Strand Magazine</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
               </series>
               <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
               <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles></title>
               <publisher>George Newnes LTD.</publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>George Newnes LTD.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>7, 8, 9, 10, 11, &amp; 12, Southampton Street,</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>and Exeter Street, London</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </pubPlace>
               <date when="1901-08">August 1901</date>
               <availability>
                  <p>Held by UW Special Collections under the call number 051 SM v.22.</p>
               </availability>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This edition was created as part of TXTDS 404 at the University of Washington over
               the course of Spring Quarter 2025. Our first goal with this digital edition is to
               reproduce the copytext as close to the original as possible, including text itself as
               well as form, format, and illustrations, using the tools of digital editing such as
               XML, TEI, HTML, and CSS. Our second goal is to include interesting contextual
               information to the story to enrich and contextualize a reader's experience by
               connecting readers with Doyle’s history with The Strand and also to the geographic
               elements in the story and its mediation. We are also interested in how historic
               audiences received and reacted to the story. Our edition, including our HTML and CSS
               formatting of the TEI encoding, was published online using the Vergil web publishing
               system.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Our aim with editiorial decisions is to avoid altering the text and its presentation
               minimally. Original spelling, format, and punctuation is recreated wherever we can.
               We will normalize certain punctuation that resembles em dashes and dashes but are
               neither.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2025-05-11">Began creating draft TEI Header</change>
            <change when="2025-05-12">Finish draft TEI Header</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front xml:lang="en"> 
      
      
      
      </front>
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <pb n="123"/>
         <head><title type="magazine"><lb/>The Strand Magazine. <lb/>Vol. xxii. <date when="1901-08"
                  >August, 1901.</date> No. 128.<lb/></title>
            <title type="novel">The Hound of the Baskervilles.* <lb/>ANOTHER ADVENTURE
               OF<lb/>SHERLOCK HOLMES.</title>
            <abbr rend="caps">By Conan Doyle.</abbr><!-- cannot add a rend font in this author section--></head>
         <cb/>
         <div type="chapter" n="1" rend="title">
            <ab rend="caps">Chapter I.</ab>
            <ab rend="caps"><persName ref="#Holmes">Mr. Sherlock Holmes</persName>.</ab>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">MR. SHERLOCK HOLMES</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>who was usually very late in<lb break="yes"
               />the mornings, save upon those<lb break="yes"/>not infrequent occasions when<lb
                  break="yes"/>he was up all night, was seated<lb break="yes"/>at the breakfast
               table. I stood<lb break="yes"/>upon the hearth-rug and picked up the stick<lb
                  break="yes"/>which our visitor had left behind him the night<lb break="yes"
               />before. It was a fine, thick piece of wood,<lb break="yes"/>bulbous-headed, of the
               sort which is known<lb break="yes"/>as a "Penang lawyer." Just under the head<lb
                  break="yes"/>was a broad silver band, nearly an inch<lb break="yes"/>across. "To
               <persName ref="#Mortimer">James Mortimer, <abbr>M. R. C. S</abbr></persName>.,<lb break="yes"/>from his friends of the <placeName ref="#CCHospital"><abbr>C. C. H.</abbr></placeName>," was
               engraved <lb break="yes"/>upon it, with the date "1884." It was just<lb break="yes"
               />such a stick as the old-fashioned family<lb break="yes"/>practitioner used to
               carry—dignified, solid,<lb break="yes"/>and reassuring.</p>
            <p><said>"Well, <persName ref="Watson">Watson</persName>, what do you make of it?"</said></p>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName> was sitting with his back to me,<lb break="yes"/>and I had given him no sign
               of my occupa-<lb break="no"/>tion.</p>
            <p><said>"How did you know what I was doing?<lb break="yes"/>I believe you have eyes in
                  the back of your<lb break="yes"/>head."</said></p>
            <p><said>"I have, at least, a well-polished silver-<lb break="yes"/>plated coffee-pot in
                  front of me,"</said> said he.<lb break="yes"/><s>"But, tell me, <persName ref="Watson">Watson</persName>, what do you
                  make of<lb break="yes"/>our visitor's stick? Since we have been so<lb
                     break="yes"/>unfortunate as to miss him and have no<lb break="yes"/>notion of
                  his errand, this accidental souvenir<lb break="yes"/>becomes of importance. Let
                  me hear you<lb break="yes"/>reconstruct the man by an examination of it."</s></p>
            <p><said>"I think," said I, following as far as I could<lb break="yes"/>the methods of my
                  companion, "that <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr.<lb break="yes"/>Mortimer</persName> is a successful elderly medical
                  man,
                  <fw type="-----">
                     <!--what should we call this??????????-->* This story owes its inception to my
                     friend, Mr. Fletcher<lb break="yes"/>Robinson, who has helped me both in the
                     general plot and in<lb break="yes"/>the local details.—A. C. D.</fw>
                  
                  <cb/><lb break="yes"/>well-esteemed, since those who know him<lb break="yes"
                  />give him this mark of their appreciation."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Good!"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>. <s>"Excellent!"</s></p>
            <p><said>"I think also that the probability is in <lb break="yes"/>favour of his being a
                  country practitioner<lb break="yes"/>who does a great deal of his visiting on
                  foot."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Why so?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Because this stick, though originally a<lb break="yes"/>very handsome one, has
                  been so knocked<lb break="yes"/>about that I can hardly imagine a town<lb
                     break="yes"/>practitioner carrying it. The thick iron<lb break="yes"/>ferrule
                  is worn down, so it is evident that he<lb break="yes"/>has done a great amount of
                  walking with it."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Perfectly sound !"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>.</p>
            <p><said>"And then again, there is the 'friends of<lb break="yes"/>the <abbr>C.C.H.</abbr>' I should
                  guess that to be the<lb break="yes"/>Something Hunt, the local hunt to whose<lb
                     break="yes"/>members he has possibly given some surgical<lb break="yes"
                  />assistance, and which has made him a small<lb break="yes"/>presentation in
                  return."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Really, <persName ref="Watson">Watson</persName>, you excel yourself,"</said> said<lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>, pushing
               back his chair and lighting <lb break="yes"/>a cigarette. <said>"I am bound to say that
                  in all <lb break="yes"/>the accounts which you have been so good <lb break="yes"
                  />as to give of my own small achievements you <lb break="no"/>have habitually
                  underrated your own abilities. <lb break="yes"/>It may be that you are not
                  yourself luminous, <lb break="yes"/>but you are a conductor of light. Some <lb
                     break="yes"/>people without possessing genius have a <lb break="yes"
                  />remarkable power of stimulating it. I con-<lb break="no"/>fess, my dear fellow,
                  that I am very much in <lb break="yes"/>your debt."</said></p>
            <p>He had never said as much before, and I <lb break="yes"/>must admit that his words
               gave me keen <lb break="yes"/>pleasure, for I had often been piqued by his <lb
                  break="yes"/>indifference to my admiration and to the <lb break="yes"/>attempts
               which I had made to give publicity <lb break="yes"/>to his methods. I was proud too
               to think <lb break="yes"/>that I had so far mastered his system as to <lb break="yes"
               />apply it in a way which earned his approval. <lb break="yes"/>He now took the stick
               from my hands<fw type="--------------------">Vol. xxii.-16.</fw>
               <!-- what type would this fw be??????-->
               
               <pb n="124"/><fw type="RunnningHead" rend="caps"> 124 The Strand
               Magazine.</fw>
               <cb/>and examined it for a few minutes with his<lb break="yes"/>naked
               eyes. Then with an expression of<lb break="yes"/>interest he laid down his cigarette
               and, carry-<lb break="no"/>ing the cane to the window, he looked over<lb break="yes"
               />it again with a convex lens.</p>
            <p><said>"Interesting, though elementary,"</said> said he,<lb break="yes"/>as he returned to his
               favourite corner of the<lb break="yes"/>settee. <said>"There are certainly one or two<lb
                  break="yes"/>indications upon the stick.<lb break="yes"/>It gives us the basis
               for<lb break="yes"/>several deductions."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Has anything escaped<lb break="yes"/>me?"</said> I asked, with some<lb break="yes"
            />self-importance. <said>"I trust<lb break="yes"/>that there is nothing of<lb break="yes"
               />consequence which I have<lb break="yes"/>overlooked?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"I am afraid, my dear<lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, that most of your<lb break="yes"
               />conclusions were erro-<lb break="no"/>neous. When I said that<lb break="yes"/>you
               stimulated me I meant,<lb break="yes"/>to be frank, that in noting<lb break="yes"
               />your fallacies I was occa-<lb break="no"/>sionally guided towards the<lb
                  break="yes"/>truth. Not that you are<lb break="yes"/>entirely wrong in this
                  in-<lb break="no"/>stance. The man is cer-<lb break="no"/>tainly a country
                  practi-<lb break="yes"/>tioner. And he walks a<lb break="yes"/>good deal."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Then I was right."</said></p>
            <p><said>"To that extent."</said></p>
            <p><said>"But that was all."</said></p>
            <p><said>"No, no, my dear Wat-<lb break="no"/>son, not all—by no means<lb break="yes"/>all. I
               would suggest, for<lb break="yes"/>example, that a presenta-<lb break="no"/>tion to
               a doctor is more<lb break="yes"/>likely to come from an<lb break="yes"/>hospital
               than from a<lb break="yes"/>hunt, and that when<lb break="yes"/>the initials '<abbr>C.C.</abbr>'
               are<lb break="yes"/>placed before that hospital<lb break="yes"/>the words 'Charing
               <lb break="yes"/>Cross' very naturally suggest themselves."</said></p>
            <p><said>"You may be right."</said></p>
            <p><said>"The probability lies in that direction.<lb break="yes"/>And if we take this as a
               working hypothesis<lb break="yes"/>we have a fresh basis from which to start our<lb
                  break="yes"/>construction of this unknown visitor."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Well, then, supposing that '<abbr>C.C.H</abbr>.' does<lb break="yes"/>stand for '<placeName ref="#CCHospital">Charing Cross
               Hospital</placeName>,' what<lb break="yes"/>further inferences may we draw?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Do none suggest themselves? You<lb break="yes"/>know my methods. Apply them!"</said></p>
            <p><said>"I can only think of the obvious conclu-<lb break="no"/>sion that the man has
               practiced in town<lb break="yes"/>before going to the country."</said></p>

            <cb/>
            <p><said>"I think that we might venture a little<lb break="yes"/>farther than this. Look at
               it in this<lb break="yes"/>light. On what occasion would it be<lb break="yes"/>most
               probable that such a presentation<lb break="yes"/>would be made? When would his
               friends<lb break="yes"/>unite to give him a pledge of their good will?<lb
                  break="yes"/>Obviously at the moment when <persName ref="Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName><lb break="yes"/>withdrew
               from the service of the hospital in<lb break="yes"/>order to start in practice<lb
                  break="yes"/>for himself. We know<lb break="yes"/>there has been a presenta-<lb
                  break="no"/>tion. We believe there has<lb break="yes"/>been a change from a town
                  <lb break="yes"/>hospital to a country prac-<lb break="no"/>tice. Is it, then,
               stretching<lb break="yes"/>our inference too far to say<lb break="yes"/>that the
               presentation was<lb break="yes"/>on the occasion of the<lb break="yes"
               />change?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"It certainly seems<lb break="yes"/>probable."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Now, you will observe<lb break="yes"/>that he could not have been<lb break="yes"
               />on the <emph rend="italics">staff</emph> of the hospital,<lb break="yes"/>since
               only a man well-<lb break="maybe"/>established in a London<lb break="yes"/>practice
               could hold such a<lb break="yes"/>position, and such a one<lb break="yes"/>would
               not drift into the<lb break="yes"/>country. What was he then?<lb break="yes"/>If he
               was in the hos-<lb break="no"/>pital and yet not on the<lb break="yes"/>staff he
               could only have<lb break="yes"/>been a house-surgeon or a<lb break="yes"
               />house-physician — little<lb break="yes"/>more than a senior student.<lb
                  break="yes"/>And he left five years ago<lb break="yes"/>—the date is on the stick.
               <lb break="yes"/>So on your grave, middle-aged<lb break="yes"/>family
               practitioner vanishes<lb break="yes"/>into thin air,<lb break="yes"/>my dear
                  <persName ref="Watson">Wat-<lb break="no"/>son</persName>, and there emerges a<lb break="yes"/>young fellow under
               thirty,<lb break="yes"/>amiable, unambitious,<lb break="yes"/>absent-minded, and
               the<lb break="yes"/>possessor of a favourite dog, which I should<lb break="yes"
               />describe roughly as being larger than a terrier<lb break="yes"/>and smaller than a
               mastiff."</said></p>
            <p>I laughed incredulously as <persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock<lb break="yes"/>Holmes</persName> leaned back in his settee
               and blew<lb break="yes"/>little wavering rings of smoke up to the<lb break="yes"
               />ceiling.</p>
            <p><said>"As to the latter part, I have no means<lb break="yes"/>of checking you,"</said> said I,
               <said>"but at least<lb break="yes"/>it is not difficult to find out a few par-<lb
                  break="no"/>ticulars about the man's age and profes-<lb break="no"/>sional
               career."</said> From my small medical<lb break="yes"/>shelf I took down the Medical
               Directory and<lb break="yes"/>turned up the name. There were several
               
               <pb n="125"
                  /><fw type="RunningHead" rend="caps">The Hound of the Baskervilles 125</fw>
               Mortimers, but only one who could be our<lb break="yes"/>visitor. I read his record
               aloud.</p>
            <p><said>"<persName ref="#Mortimer">Mortimer, James, <abbr>M.R.C.S.</abbr></persName>, 1882,<lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#Grimpen">Grimpen</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Dartmoor">Dartmoor</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Devon">Devon</placeName>. House
               surgeon,<lb break="yes"/>from 1882 to 1884, at <placeName ref="#CCHospital">Charing Cross<lb break="yes"
               />Hospital</placeName>. Winner of the Jackson prize for<lb break="yes"/>Comparative Pathology,
               with essay entitled<lb break="yes"/>'Is Disease a Reversion?' Corresponding<lb
                  break="yes"/>member of the Swedish Pathological Society.<lb break="yes"/>Author
               of 'Some Freaks of Atavism'<lb break="yes"/><q rend="italics">(Lancet, 1882)</q>. 'Do We Progress?'
               <q rend="italics">(Journal<lb break="yes"/>of Psychology, March, 1883)</q>. <!-- unsure whether we will be creating some sort of citation format--> Medical<lb break="yes"
               />Officer for the parishes of <placeName ref="Grimpen">Grimpen</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#Thorsley">Thorsley</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#HighBarrow">High
               Barrow</placeName>."</said></p>
            <p><said>"No mention of that local hunt, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>,"</said><lb break="yes"/>said <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>, with a
               mischievous smile, <said>"but<lb break="yes"/>a country doctor, as you very astutely
               observed.<lb break="yes"/>I think that I am fairly justified in my infer-<lb
                  break="no"/>ences. As to the adjectives, I said, if I<lb break="yes"/>remember
               right, amiable, unambitious, and<lb break="yes"/>absent-minded. It is my experience
               that it is<lb break="yes"/>only an amiable man in this world who<lb break="yes"
               />receives testimonials, only<lb break="yes"/>an unambitious one who<lb break="yes"
               />abandons a London career<lb break="yes"/>for the country, and only<lb break="yes"
               />an absent-minded one who<lb break="yes"/>leaves his stick and not his<lb
                  break="yes"/>visiting-card after waiting<lb break="yes"/>an hour in your
               room."</said></p>
            <p><said>"And the dog?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Has been in the habit<lb break="yes"/>of carrying this stick behind<lb break="yes"
               />his master. Being a heavy<lb break="yes"/>stick the dog has held it<lb
                  break="yes"/>tightly by the middle, and<lb break="yes"/>the marks of his teeth
               are<lb break="yes"/>very plainly visible. The<lb break="yes"/>dog's jaw, as shown
               in the<lb break="yes"/>space between these marks,<lb break="yes"/>is too broad in
               my opinion<lb break="yes"/>for a terrier and not broad<lb break="yes"/>enough for a
               mastiff. It may<lb break="yes"/>have been—yes, by Jove, it<lb break="yes"/>is a
               curly-haired spaniel."</said></p>
            <p>He had risen and paced<lb break="yes"/>the room as he spoke. Now<lb break="yes"/>he
               halted in the recess of<lb break="yes"/>the window. There was<lb break="yes"/>such
               a ring of conviction in<lb break="yes"/>his voice that I glanced up<lb break="yes"
               />in surprise.</p>
            <p><said>"My dear fellow, how<lb break="yes"/>can you possibly be so<lb break="yes"/>sure of
               that?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"For the very simple<lb break="yes"/>reason that I see the dog<lb break="yes"
               />himself on our very door-<lb break="maybe"/>step, and there is the ring 
               
               <cb/>of its
               owner. Don't move, I beg you, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>.<lb break="yes"/>He is a professional brother
               of yours, and your<lb break="yes"/>presence may be of assistance to me. Now is<lb
                  break="yes"/>the dramatic moment of fate, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, when<lb break="yes"/>you hear a
               step upon the stair which is walking<lb break="yes"/>into your life, and you know
               not whether for<lb break="yes"/>good or ill. What does <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. James Mortimer</persName>, <lb
                  break="yes"/>the man of science, ask of <persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock Holmes</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>the
               specialist in crime? Come in!"</said></p>
            <p>The appearance of our visitor was a surprise<lb break="yes"/>to me, since I had
               expected a typical country<lb break="yes"/>practitioner. He was a very tall, thin
               man,<lb break="yes"/>with a long nose like a beak, which jutted out<lb break="yes"
               />between two keen, grey eyes, set closely<lb break="yes"/>together and sparkling
               brightly from behind a<lb break="yes"/>pair of gold-rimmed glasses. He was clad in
               <lb break="yes"/>a professional but rather slovenly fashion, for<lb break="yes"
               />his frock-coat dingy and his trousers<lb break="yes"/>frayed. Though young, his
               long back was<lb break="yes"/>already bowed, and he walked with a forward<lb
                  break="yes"/>thrust of his head and a general air of peering<lb break="yes"
               />benevolence. As he entered his eyes fell upon
               
               <pb n="126"/>
               <fw>126 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>
            </p>


         </div>
         <div type="chapter" n="2"> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      
      
      
   </standOff>
</TEI>
