<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles</title>
            <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
            <editor>Em Backstrom</editor>
            <editor>Blue Jordan</editor>
            <editor>Rowan Herron</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>We plan to publish this edition of The Hound of the Baskervilles in June 2025.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <series>
                  <title>The Strand Magazine</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
               </series>
               <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
               <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles></title>
               <publisher>George Newnes LTD.</publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>George Newnes LTD.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>7, 8, 9, 10, 11, &amp; 12, Southampton Street,</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>and Exeter Street, London</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </pubPlace>
               <date when="1901-08">August 1901</date>
               <availability>
                  <p>Held by UW Special Collections under the call number 051 SM v.22.</p>
               </availability>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This edition was created as part of TXTDS 404 at the University of Washington over
               the course of Spring Quarter 2025. Our first goal with this digital edition is to
               reproduce the copytext as close to the original as possible, including text itself as
               well as form, format, and illustrations, using the tools of digital editing such as
               XML, TEI, HTML, and CSS. Our second goal is to include interesting contextual
               information to the story to enrich and contextualize a reader's experience by
               connecting readers with Doyle’s history with The Strand and also to the geographic
               elements in the story and its mediation. We are also interested in how historic
               audiences received and reacted to the story. Our edition, including our HTML and CSS
               formatting of the TEI encoding, was published online using the Vergil web publishing
               system.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Our aim with editiorial decisions is to avoid altering the text and its presentation
               minimally. Original spelling, format, and punctuation is recreated wherever we can.
               We will normalize certain punctuation that resembles em dashes and dashes but are
               neither.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2025-05-11">Began creating draft TEI Header</change>
            <change when="2025-05-12">Finish draft TEI Header</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front> </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="123"/>
         <head>The Strand Magazine.</head>
         <head>Vol. xxii. August, 1901. No. 128.</head>
         <head>The Hound of the Baskervilles.*</head>
         <head><lb/>ANOTHER ADVENTURE OF<lb/>SHERLOCK HOLMES.</head>
         <head>BY CONAN DOYLE.</head>
         <cb/>
         <div type="chapter" n="1">
            <ab>CHAPTER I.</ab>
            <ab>MR. SHERLOCK HOLMES.</ab>
            <p>MR. SHERLOCK HOLMES, who was usually very late in the mornings, save upon those not
               infrequent occasions when he was up all night, was seated at the breakfast table. I
               stood upon the hearth-rug and picked up the stick which our visitor had left behind
               him the night before. It was a fine, thick piece of wood, bulbous-headed, of the sort
               which is known as a "Penang lawyer." Just under the head was a broad silver band,
               nearly an inch across. "To James Mortimer, M. R. C. S., from his friends of the C. C.
               H.," was engraved upon it, with the date "1884." It was just such a stick as the
               old-fashioned family practitioner used to carry—dignified, solid, and reassuring.</p>
            <p><s>"Well, Watson, what do you make of it?"</s></p>
            <p>Holmes was sitting with his back to me, and I had given him no sign of my
               occupa-tion.</p>
            <p><s>"How did you know what I was doing? I believe you have eyes in the back of your
                  head."</s></p>
            <p><s>"I have, at least, a well-polished silver-plated coffee-pot in front of me,"</s>
               said he.</p>
            <p><s>"But, tell me, Watson, what do you make of our visitor's stick? Since we have been
                  so unfortunate as to miss him and have no notion of his errand, this accidental
                  souvenir becomes of importance. Let me hear you reconstruct the man by an
                  examination of it."</s></p>
            <p><s>"I think," said I, following as far as I could the methods of my companion, "that
                  Dr. Mortimer is a successful elderly medical man,<fw type="-----">* This story
                     owes its inception to my friend, Mr. Fletcher Robinson, who has helped me both
                     in the general plot and in the local details.—A. C. D.</fw><cb/>well-esteemed,
                  since those who know him give him this mark of their appreciation."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Good!"</s> said Holmes. <s>"Excellent!"</s></p>
            <p><s>"I think also that the probability is in favour of his being a country practitioner
               who does a great deal of his visiting on foot."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Why so?"</s></p>
            <p><s>"Because this stick, though originally a very handsome one, has been so knocked about
               that I can hardly imagine a town practitioner carrying it. The thick iron ferrule is
               worn down, so it is evident that he has done a great amount of walking with it."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Perfectly sound !"</s> said Holmes.</p>
            <p><s>"And then again, there is the 'friends of the C.C.H.' I should guess that to be the
               Something Hunt, the local hunt to whose members he has possibly given some surgical
               assistance, and which has made him a small presentation in return."</s></p>
            <p><s>"Really, Watson, you excel yourself,"</s> said Holmes, pushing back his chair and
               lighting a cigarette. <s>"I am bound to say that in all the accounts which you have been
               so good as to give of my own small achievements you have habitually underrated your
               own abilities. It may be that you are not yourself luminous, but you are a conductor
               of light. Some people without possessing genius have a remarkable power of
               stimulating it. I con-fess, my dear fellow, that I am very much in your debt."</s></p>
            <p>He had never said as much before, and I must admit that his words gave me keen
               pleasure, for I had often been piqued by his indifference to my admiration and to the
               attempts which I had made to give publicity to his methods. I was proud too to think
               that I had so far mastered his system as to apply it in a way which earned his
               approval. He now took the stick from my hands<fw>Vol. xxii.-16.</fw><pb n="124"/><fw
                  type="RunnningHead" rend="caps">124 The Strand Magazine.</fw>
            </p>


            <pb n="126"/>
            <fw>126 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter" n="2"> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
