<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Reindeer Recipes</title>
                <author>The Great Northern Dining Car Department</author>
                <editor>Priyanka Kannan, Preyal Garg, Ryan Gottlieb, Zooey Whang</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This edition was prepared for educational purposes as part of TXTDTS 404 A:
                    Digital Textual Editing, at the University of Washington. It is a final class
                    project and is not intended for commercial publication.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Reindeer Recipes</title>
                    <author>Great Northern Dining Car Department</author>
                    <publisher>Unknown</publisher>
                    <date notBefore="1889" notAfter="1970">[between 1889 and 1970]</date>
                    <idno type="callNumber">SCPNW TX749.5.R45 1910z</idno>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>University of Washington Special Collections</repository>
                        <idno>SCPNW TX749.5.R45 1910z</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>Printed booklet on paper, approximately 6 pages. The paper
                                    is cream-colored with green border around it. Cover art is of a
                                    reindeer with its herd in the background of a snowy hill at
                                    sunset, with an orange sun and a few barren trees.</support>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>Produced by the Great Northern Railway Dining Car Department
                            sometime between 1889 and 1970.</origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This text is a Reindeer Recipe cookbook that was created by the Great Northern
                    Dining Car Department in the early 20th century. The Great Northern Dining Car
                    Department is a part of the Great Northern Railway company, which was an
                    American Class I railroad that was created in the 19th century by James J. Hill,
                    a Canadian-American rail entrepreneur. This rail ran from Saint Paul, Minnesota
                    to Seattle, Washington, and was wildly successful for a majority of its
                    existence. But since 1970, it has undergone mergers and acquisitions and has
                    essentially been erased, or it’s at least not as visible as it once was.</p>
                <p>That’s why we think this text is so important. It’s so far from common thought,
                    why would you ever be thinking about the Great Northern Railroad’s Reindeer
                    Recipe from a century ago? Even though it’s in our archives, even though we can
                    access it with an appointment and a librarian, we still thought there was value
                    in republishing it, in breathing some new life into it. We just made it go that
                    much farther from being forgotten. Now we talk about it with our friends at
                    dinner, how we’re working on a reindeer recipe cookbook, now we research the
                    Great Northern Railroad, we read about the origins and progression of the entire
                    company. It’s these little, personal things that keep texts alive, it doesn’t
                    have to be on a widespread level.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Notes</head>
                <list>
                    <item><label>James J. Hill:</label> He was born in Canada on September 16, 1838
                        and died in Minnesota on May 29, 1916. He was a rail entrepreneur
                        responsible for the entirety of the Great Northern Railroad and he amassed a
                        wealth of $63 million by the time he died.</item>
                    <item><label>Reindeer:</label> Reindeer are endogenous to subarctic regions,
                        much like some parts of North America. With this being said, the nearby
                        areas of the rail itself would’ve been close to reindeer populations, making
                        reindeer an extremely viable source of food, hence the entire cookbook.
                        Reindeer meat is high in protein, healthy fats, and vitamins.</item>
                    <item><label>Great Northern Railroad:</label> Now known as the Burlington
                        Northern and Santa Fe Railway</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>“Great Northern Empire - Then and Now.” Greatnorthernempire.net, 2025,
                        www.greatnorthernempire.net/index2.htm?GNEPreservedGNPassengerCars_Diners.htm.
                        Accessed 19 May 2025.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Recipes.” Gngoat.org, 2025, www.gngoat.org/recipes.htm. Accessed 19 May
                        2025.</bibl>
                    <bibl>University of Washington. “Reindeer Recipes.” Exlibrisgroup.com, 2025,
                        orbiscascade-washington.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/discovery/fulldisplay?docid=alma99162019554401452&amp;context=L&amp;vid=01ALLIANCE_UW:UW&amp;lang=en&amp;search_scope=UW_EVERYTHING&amp;adaptor=Local%20Search%20Engine&amp;tab=UW_default&amp;query=any.
                        Accessed 19 May 2025.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wikipedia Contributors. “Great Northern Railway (U.S.).” Wikipedia,
                        Wikimedia Foundation, 11 Nov. 2019,
                        en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Northern_Railway_(U.S.).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            
            
            <div>
                <head>Recipes</head>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="hunter-soup">
                    <head>Reindeer Hunter Soup</head>
                    <p>Cut two pounds of Reindeer meat in small pieces and put it into the soup pot
                        (casserole), add two quarts of water. Chop one onion, pinch of mace and one
                        bay leaf, add to the meat, let it simmer until the meat is tender, add one
                        cup of rice, salt and pepper and let it cook until the rice is done. Pour
                        into the tureen over French croutons and serve.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="stew-creole">
                    <head>Reindeer Stew Creole Style</head>
                    <p>Cut the meat into two-inch square pieces, salt and pepper well. Chop a couple
                        onions very fine, brown them in a pan in a little butter, then add the meat,
                        let it brown slightly and add a little flour. Let this brown a little. Chop
                        a piece of cold ham very fine, then add a few cloves and garlic, a sprig of
                        thyme, a sprig of parsley and a bay leaf, all minced fine. Pour soup stock
                        or water over it, let it cook for thirty minutes, add fresh mushrooms and
                        cook for another twenty minutes. Serve very hot.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="ragout">
                    <head>Ragout of Reindeer</head>
                    <p>Take the breast and the neck, cut it up into neat pieces, put it into a jar,
                        cut up some carrots, onions and celery, a few bay leaves, whole cloves,
                        whole allspice, whole pepper, put all together in vinegar, let it stand for
                        two or three days, then take it out and braise it to a light brown color,
                        sprinkle it with flour and some stock, some tomato juice. Let it simmer
                        until done, season it with salt, paprika, pepper, thyme, a little chopped
                        garlic, chopped parsley, a little sugar, tomato catsup, Worcestershire
                        sauce, finish it with a little sour cream.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="roast-leg">
                    <head>Roast Leg of Reindeer Meat</head>
                    <p>Wipe meat, sprinkle with salt and pepper, place on rack in dripping pan and
                        dredge meat and bottom of pan with flour. Place in not too hot oven and
                        baste as soon as flour in pan is brown, and every fifteen minutes
                        thereafter, until meat is done, which should be cooked rare. It may be
                        necessary to put a small quantity of water in pan while meat is cooking.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="reindeer-stew">
                    <head>Reindeer Stew</head>
                    <p>Take a piece of the preserved venison, place in kettle, add some of the
                        spices in which the meat has been lying, also a piece of butter, cover well
                        and stew until tender. When ready to serve add a generous portion of sweet
                        cream thickened with browned flour and a little sugar.</p>
                    <p>Cuts from the flank, breast, neck or ribs are best suited for this dish. Cut
                        meat in pieces desired, fry in butter and bacon fat to a rich golden-brown,
                        add boiling water and cover. After a few minutes remove scum and add
                        following: grated bread or flour browned in butter, grated rind of a lemon,
                        pepper, cloves, few bay leaves, liberal quantity of cubed onions, several
                        cucumbers cut lengthwise and vinegar. When nearly done add a very little
                        apple jam or sugar to lessen sharpness of vinegar.</p>
                    <p>The sauce in which meat is served must be of creamy consistency and generous
                        in quantity.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="chops-steaks">
                    <head>Reindeer Chops or Steaks</head>
                    <p>Chops or steaks should be broiled, or fried, on a quick fire, well seasoned
                        and served with jelly.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="mulligan">
                    <head>Reindeer Mulligan—Hunter Style</head>
                    <p>This recipe was furnished by an old hunter.</p>
                    <p>Take neck and shanks and parts of shoulder, cut in uniform pieces about two
                        inches square, place in large wide kettle, cover with water and let simmer
                        about half hour, add rutabagas, cut in uniform pieces about two inches
                        square, fifteen minutes later add carrots and potatoes cut the same way.
                        Vegetables should be equal parts, and the three together the same quantity
                        as meat, also add several large onions, cut in quarters, then season with
                        salt and whole black peppers; place peppers in small cheese-cloth bag and a
                        few bay leaves, let simmer until done. Serve with dill pickles or sour
                        pickles, according to taste.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="broiled-steak">
                    <head>Broiled Reindeer Meat Steak</head>
                    <p>Wipe steak, sprinkle with salt and pepper, place on greased boiler and broil
                        five minutes. Remove to hot platter and pour over Chestnut sauce or Maitre
                        d' Hotel butter.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="roast-loin">
                    <head>Roast Loin of Reindeer Meat</head>
                    <p>Meat should be well skinned, neatly larded and pan closely covered during
                        first part of roasting, as this will help retain juices and also insure a
                        milder flavor. Heat liberal quantity of cubed bacon in roasting pan, add
                        piece of butter, place loin roast in pan, larded side up and cook, well
                        covered, for one hour. During this time and afterwards, baste frequently and
                        as often as necessary add half cup boiling water. But during last half hour
                        of cooking use thick sour cream in place of water. Roast, according to size
                        of meat, from 2–2:30 hours, without turning. Must be cooked rare. Stir up
                        gravy with cold water and if not sufficiently creamy stiffen with some
                        flour.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="recipe" xml:id="saddle">
                    <head>Saddle of Reindeer—Larded</head>
                    <p>Take the saddle and lard it, season it with salt and pepper, thyme, fry it on
                        a quick fire in a saute pan, a few spices, add some Espagnole, a little
                        jelly, lemon juice. Do not cook it too much—it should be medium cooked. When
                        done finish the sauce with a little chopped garlic, chopped parsley and a
                        little cream and nutmeg.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
