<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reindeer Recipes</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p> A NEW discovery from Alaska — nourishment—not gold—something to add to the enjoyment of
            life—something that with a final analysis is found more precious than gold—something to
            delight the inner man—Reindeer meat. </p>
         <p> The Great Northern Dining Car Department, ever on the alert to discover new and better
            foods to offer its patrons, believes that Reindeer meat will be approved by all who
            crave something different. </p>
         <p>The Reindeer, as now raised in Alaska, is a domesticated animal; has nothing of the wild
            animal taste—the meat is finer in texture than beef and decidedly more tender—this
            explained by the fact that the Reindeer is a docile animal, seldom exerting itself to
            the extent of providing ordinary exercise—therefore he grows fat and soft. Reindeer meat
            has juiciness of beef with delicacy of flavor unequalled by beef or venison. Reindeer
            meat is a happy medium between wild game and domestic meats. </p>
         <p> Reindeer meat is Alaska's latest and most promising contribution to its mother country,
            and Great Northern Dining cars are happy in their role of introducing it. We confidently
            predict a hearty reception. </p>
         <p> Reindeer Recipes larger text, bold, centred</p>
         <p> Reindeer Hunter Soup </p>
         <p> Cut two pounds of Reindeer meat in small pieces and put it into the soup pot
            (casserole), add two quarts of water. Chop one onion, pinch of mace and one bay leaf,
            add to the meat, let it simmer until the meat is tender, add one cup of rice, salt and
            pepper and let it cook until the rice is done. Pour into the tureen over French croutons
            and serve. </p>
         <p> Reindeer Stew Creole Style </p>
         <p> Cut the meat into two-inch square pieces, salt and pepper well. Chop a couple onions
            very fine, brown them in a pan in a little butter, then add the meat, let it brown
            slightly and add a little flour. Let this brown a little. Chop a piece of cold ham very
            fine, then add a few cloves and garlic, a sprig of thyme, a sprig of parsley and a bay
            leaf, all minced fine. Pour soup stock or water over it, let it cook for thirty minutes,
            add fresh mushrooms and cook for another twenty minutes. Serve very hot. </p>
         <p>Ragout of Reindeer</p>
         <p> Take the breast and the neck, cut it up into neat pieces, put it into a jar, cut up
            some carrots, onions and celery, a few bay leaves, whole cloves, whole allspice, whole
            pepper, put all together in vinegar, let it stand for two or three days, then take it
            out and braise it to a light brown color, sprinkle it with flour and some stock, some
            tomato juice. Let it simmer until done, season it with salt, paprika, pepper, thyme, a
            little chopped garlic, chopped parsley, a little sugar, tomato catsup, Worcestershire
            sauce, finish it with a little sour cream. </p>
         <p> Roast Leg of Reindeer Meat </p>
         <p> Wipe meat, sprinkle with salt and pepper, place on rack in dripping pan and dredge meat
            and bottom of pan with flour. Place in not too hot oven and baste as soon as flour in
            pan is brown, and every fifteen minutes thereafter, until meat is done, which should be
            cooked rare. It may be necessary to put a small quantity of water in pan while meat is
            cooking. </p>
         <p>Reindeer Stew</p>
         <p>Take a piece of the preserved venison, place in kettle, add some of the spices in which
            the meat has been lying, also a piece of butter, cover well and stew until tender. When
            ready to serve add a generous portion of sweet cream thickened with browned flour and a
            little sugar.</p>
         <p>Cuts from the flank, breast, neck or ribs are best suited for this dish</p>
         <p> Cut meat in pieces desired, fry in butter and bacon fat to a rich golden-brown, add
            boiling water and cover. After a few minutes remove scum and add following: grated bread
            or flour browned in butter, grated rind of a lemon, pepper, cloves, few bay leaves,
            liberal quantity of cubed onions, several cucumbers cut lengthwise and vinegar. When
            nearly done add a very little apple jam or sugar to lessen sharpness of vinegar. </p>
         <p>The sauce in which meat is served must be of creamy consistency and generous in
            quantity.</p>
         <p>Reindeer Chops or Steaks</p>
         <p>Chops or streaks should be broiled, or fried, on a quick fire, well seasoned and served
            with jelly. </p>
         <p>Reindeer Mulligan—Hunter Style</p>
         <p> This recipe was furnished by an old hunter </p>
         <p> Take neck and shanks and parts of shoulder, cut in uniform pieces about two inches
            square, place in large wide kettle, cover with water and let simmer about half hour, add
            rutabagas, cut in uniform pieces about two inches square, fifteen minutes later add
            carrots and potatoes cut the same way. Vegetables should be equal parts, and the three
            together the same quantity as meat, also add several large onions, cut in quarters, then
            season with salt and whole black peppers; place peppers in small cheese-cloth bag and a
            few bay leaves, let simmer until done. Serve with dill pickles or sour pickles,
            according to taste. </p>
         <p>Broiled Reindeer Meat Steak</p>
         <p>Wipe steak, sprinkle with salt and pepper, place on greased boiler and broil five
            minutes. Remove to hot platter and pour over Chestnut sauce or Maitre d' Hotel butter. </p>
         <p>Roast Loin of Reindeer Meat</p>
         <p> Meat should be well skinned, neatly larded and pan closely covered during first part of
            roasting, as this will help retain juices and also insure a milder flavor. Heat liberal
            quantity of cubed bacon in roasting pan, add piece of butter, place loin roast in pan,
            larded side up and cook, well covered, for one hour. During this time and afterwards,
            baste frequently and as often as necessary add half cup boiling water. But during last
            half hour of cooking use thick sour cream in place of water. Roast, according to size of
            meat, from 2—2:30 hours, without turning. Must be cooked rare. Stir up gravy with cold
            water and if not sufficiently creamy stiffen with some flour. </p>
         <p>Saddle of Reindeer—Larded</p>
         <p>Take the saddle and lard it, season it with salt and pepper, thyme, fry it on a quick
            fire in a saute pan, a few spices, add some Espagnole, a little jelly, lemon juice. Do
            not cook it too much—it should be medium cooked. When done finish the sauce with a
            little chopped garlic, chopped parsley and a little cream and nutmeg.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
