<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Selections from the Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
                <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
                <editor xml:id="MO">Marisa Oishi</editor>
                <editor xml:id="CL">Christine Leak</editor>
                <editor xml:id="HS">Hannah Swoffer</editor>
                <sponsor>University of Washington Libraries, Special Collections</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p>This edition focuses on a selection of pages from Clarence T. Arai’s scrapbook
                    held in the University of Washington Special Collections.</p>
                <p>We chose to work with a scrapbook because of the vulnerability conveyed through
                    its visual and textual features. This edition, only a small selection of pieces
                    from the full work, explores the choices Arai made in assembling his scrapbook,
                    considering how these preserved materials capture a personal experience during
                    World War II and contribute to a more holistic, human understanding of the
                    period.</p>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Washington Student Project for TXTDS 404/FREN 420: Texts,
                    Publics, and Publication</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2025-06-06">June 6th, 2025</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available for use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
                    <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
                    <pubPlace>University of Washington, Special Collections Manuscripts and
                        Archives</pubPlace>
                    <date from="1919" to="1993">1919-1993</date>
                    <idno type="oclcNo">945773039</idno>
                    <idno type="accessionNo">acc5542-001</idno>
                    <note>Box 2</note>
                    <note>This scrapbook, assembled by Clarence T. Arai, provides a perspective on
                        his life as a Japanese American in Seattle before and during World War II.
                        It includes correspondences, newspaper clippings, certificates, and other
                        artifacts Arai selected to preserve.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>We did not correct any errors as they did not detract from one's understanding of the
                text.</p>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="border" scheme="css"> border: 4px solid black; padding: 30px; </rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="date" scheme="css">font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align:
                    right; font-style: italic; font-size: 20px;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="title" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
                    35px; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="subTitle" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
                    35px; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="paper" scheme="css"> font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align:
                    right; font-style: italic; font-size: 20px;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="author" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
                    20px; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="description" scheme="css"> font-family: "Lucida Console Regular",
                    monospace; font-size: 20px; text-indent: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titleIndent" scheme="css">padding-left: 1em;</rendition>

            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="editorial_intro">
                <p>The phrase "on paper" is an interesting one. On paper, Clarence Takeya Arai was
                    an accomplished and influential member of the Seattle community. He was the
                    first Japanese American to earn a law degree from the University of Washington
                    and the first nisei commissioned officer in the US Army Reserve. He was a
                    founder and the first president of the Japanese American Citizens League, the
                    oldest Asian American civil rights organization, as well as a Republican
                    precinct committee member and delegate to the Washington State Republican
                    Convention. On paper, Arai and his family were sent to the Puyallup Fairgrounds,
                    and then to a concentration camp in Minidoka, Idaho, when over a hundred
                    thousand innocent Japanese Americans were incarcerated during World War II. His
                    health deteriorated there, but he continued to advocate for Japanese Americans'
                    legal rights within the camp. Three months after the war ended, his son Ken died
                    of a brain tumor. Arai gave up practicing law full time and took up photography.
                    He died less than twenty years later. </p>
                <p>When we discovered the Clarence T. Arai papers in the University of Washington
                    Special Collections, we didn't just discover certificates and newspaper
                    clippings taped to yellowing pages that crumbled as we turned them. This was a
                    life, a collection of moments of pride and tragedy, lived in service to his
                    community and yet persecuted by his country. This was an autobiography, a
                    telling of Arai's story through the papers he decided to preserve. He had a
                    Cocker Spaniel named Duke of Main Street. His son Ken liked "hot dog sandwiches"
                    and bus rides to Portland. On paper, Arai was a lawyer, civil rights advocate,
                    and photographer. But on paper, he was also a gardener, a father, a man with
                    dreams and indignation with the injustice he knew he was living: a human.</p>
                <p>Regrettably, we could not include every insightful artifact in Arai’s scrapbook.
                    We each chose a genre (personal correspondences, state issues, and newspaper
                    articles) and selected a few pages from that genre, maintaining original
                    spellings and punctuation to preserve authenticity. Our goal was to provide a
                    glimpse into the first-hand experiences of Japanese Americans in Washington
                    before and during World War II. Arai’s scrapbook offers a perspective unlike
                    textbooks or documentaries, providing insight on lived experiences through his
                    personal memorabilia and artifacts. By publishing this work, we hope that
                    readers will gain a more well-rounded, holistic perspective on this time period,
                    and an awareness of Arai’s life and enduring legacy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations"> </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="certificate" style="gothic">
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center">In Appreciation</head>
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center">Presented to</head>
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center"><name>Mr. Clarence T. Arai
                    </name></head>
                <p>On behalf of <ref target="#fujiyama">Aiichiro Fujiyama</ref>, Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs of Japan, I convey to you the commendations of the Japanese
                    Government for your exemplary citizenship and leadership in the affairs of your
                    community</p>
                <p>Your unremitting and dedicated endeavors have contributed greatly to the
                    development and strengthening of admirable relations between the United States
                    and Japan, as well as between Americans and Japanese within your own
                    community.</p>
                <p>On this auspicious occasion commemorating the 100th Anniversary of the Treaty of
                    Friendship and Trade between the United States and Japan, I am privileged to
                    present to you this mokuahi from the Japanese Government as a token of heartfelt
                    appreciation for your unswerving devotion to the cause of peace and
                    understanding between our two countries.</p>
                <p>Presented at Seattle, Washington this <date when="1960-05-22">22nd day of May,
                        1960</date>.</p>
                <l>Consul-General of Japan</l>
                <l>_______(signature)______ <name>Yoshiharu Takeno</name></l>
                <!-- maybe we should add image of signature here?-->
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="certificate" rend="caps">
                <head>Smithsonian Institution</head>
                <head>Washington, D.C.</head>
                <head>This·is·to·certify·that</head>
                <head><name>Clarence T. Arai</name></head>
                <head>is·registered· in·the·archives·of·the·institution·as·a</head>
                <head>patron</head>
                <p>of·the·Smithsonian·Scientific·Series·in·recognition·of·his·aid·to·the·
                    Institution’s·program·for·the·diffusion·of·knowledge·among·men·
                    And·the·increase·of·its·financial·endowment·for·scientific·research</p>
                <p>in·witness·whereof·the·seal·of·the·institution·and·the·signatures·of
                    ·the·secretary·and·the·administration·assistant·are·affixed·hereto</p>
                <signed>
                    <l>___________(signature)_________ Secretary</l>
                    <!-- maybe we should add images of signatures here?-->
                    <l> __________(signature)_________ General</l>
                </signed>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="correspondence" xml:id="buttsLetter">
                <opener>
                    <seg type="letterhead">
                        <address>
                            <addrLine rend="caps">The Butts' Parole League</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Box 70, Nippon Station</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Seattle, Washington</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <date when="1937-04-02">April 2, 1937</date>
                    </seg>
                
                    <address>
                        <addrLine><name>Clarence T. Arai</name>, Esq.,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Seattle, Wn.</addrLine>
                    </address>

                    <salute>Sir;-</salute>
                </opener>

                <p>Permit us to offer our congratulations and best wishes toward your future as a
                    trustee of the <name ref="#spl">Seattle Public Library</name>.</p> 
                    
                <p>Mayor <name ref="#dore">John F. Dore</name>, in choosing you, thus for the first time in
                the history of Seattle according recognition to the people you so ably
                represent, we know made a selection which will undoubtedly redound to his and
                your credit.</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed rend="caps">The Butts' Parole League</signed>
                    <signed>
                        <figure xml:id="FrankOMurphySignature">
                            <graphic url="../images/Frank's_signature.jpeg"/>
                            <figDesc>by <name>Frank O. Murphy</name></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="certificate" xml:id="akcCertificate">
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center;">Registration Certificate</head>
                <figure xml:id="akcLogo">
                    <graphic url="../images/akcLogo.jpeg"/>
                    <figDesc rend="caps">American Kennel Club</figDesc>
                    <figDesc rend="caps">AKC</figDesc>
                    <figDesc rend="caps">Incorporated</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center;">American Kennel Club Stud Book</head> 
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center;">American Kennel Club</head> 
                <head rend="caps" style="text-align: center;">New York, N.Y.</head>

                <ab><hi rend="caps">Name of Dog</hi> Duke of Main Street</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Breed</hi> Cocker Spaniel <hi rend="caps">Sex</hi> Male</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Sire</hi> Slicker Boy of Kitsop (934421)</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Dam</hi> Paul’s Queenie (898745)</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Whelped</hi> March 14, 1934</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Color</hi> Red</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Breeder</hi> M. Ellen Paul</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Owner</hi> Clarence T. Arai</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Registered</hi>
                    <date when="1934-06-15">June 15, 1934</date></ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Assigned No</hi> 941308</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="caps">Volume</hi> 51</ab>
                <ab>August <hi rend="caps">Issue</hi></ab>

                <signed>
                    <figure xml:id="PercyBRiceSignature">
                        <graphic url="../images/percySignature.jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc><name>Perry B Rice</name></figDesc>
                        <figDesc rend="caps">Secretary</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    gm 
                </signed>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="statement">
                <head><hi rend="bold" style="text-align:center">Headquarters</hi></head>
                <head rend="bold">Western Defense Command</head>
                <head><hi rend="bold">And Fourth Army</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="bold">Presidio of San Francisco, California</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="bold">- - - Public Proclamation No. 3 - - - </hi></head>
                <head><date when="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date></head>
                <p>TO: The people within the States of Washington, Oregon, California, Montana,
                    Idaho, Nevada, Utah and Arizona, and the Public Generally:</p>
                <p><hi rend="sc">WHEREAS</hi>, By Public Proclamation No.1, dated <date
                        when="1942-03-02">March 2, 1942</date>, this headquarters, there were
                    designated and established Military Areas Nos. 1 and 2 and Zones thereof,
                    and</p>
                <p><hi rend="sc">WHEREAS</hi>, By Public Proclamation No. 2, dated <date
                        when="1942-03-02">March 2, 1942</date>, this headquarters, there were
                    designated and established Military Areas Nos. 3,4,5 and 6 and Zones thereof,
                    and</p>
                <p><hi rend="sc">WHEREAS</hi>, The present situation within these Military Areas and
                    Zones requires as a matter of military necessity the establishment of certain
                    regulations pertaining to all enemy aliens and all persons of Japanese ancestry
                    within said Military Areas and Zones thereof:</p>
                <p>Now, <hi rend="sc">THEREFORE</hi>, I, J.L. DEWITT, Lieutenant General, U.S. Army,
                    by virtue of the authority vested in me by the President of the United States
                    and by the Secretary of War and my powers and prerogatives as Commanding
                    General, Western Defense Command, do hereby declare and establish the following
                    regulations covering the conduct to be observed by all alien Japanese, all alien
                    Germans, all alien Italians, and all persons of Japanese ancestry residing or
                    being within the Military Areas above described, or such portions thereof as are
                    hereinafter mentioned: </p>
                <p>From and after 6:00 A.M., <date when="1942-03-27">March 27, 1942</date>, all
                    alien Japanese, all alien Germans, all alien Italians, and all persons of
                    Japanese ancestry residing or being within the geographical limits of Military
                    Area No.1, or within any of the Zones</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="statement">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Headquarters</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="bold">Western Defense Command</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="bold">And Fourth Army Presidio of San Francisco,
                    California</hi></head>
                <head><date when="1942-04-24">April 24th, 1942</date></head>
                <head><hi rend="bold">Civilian Exclusion Order No.17</hi></head>
                <p> 1. Pursuant to the provisions of Public Proclamations Nos. 1 and 2, this
                    Headquarters, dated <date when="1942-03-02">March 2, 1942</date>, and <date
                        when="1942-03-16">March 16, 1942</date>, respectively, it is hereby ordered
                    that from and after 12 o’clock noon, P.W.T., of Friday, <date when="1942-05-01"
                        >May 1, 1942</date>, all persons of Japanese ancestry, both alien and
                    non-aline, be excluded from that portion of Military Area No. 1 described as
                    follows:</p>
                <p style="text-align:indent">All that portion of the City of Seattle, State of
                    Washington, within that boundary beginning at the point at which the northerly
                    limits of said city meet Shilshole Bay ; thence easterly and following the
                    northerly limits of said city to Roosevelt Way ; thence southerly and following
                    Roosevelt Way, Eastlake Avenue, fairview Avenue, Virginia Street, and Westlake
                    Avenue to Fifth Avenue ; thence southeasterly on Fifth Avenue to Yesler Way ;
                    thence easterly on Yesler Way to Maynard Avenue ; thence southerly on Maynard
                    Avenue to Jackson Street ; thence westerly on jackson Street to Elliott Bay ;
                    thence north-westerly and northerly, and following the westerly limits of the
                    City of Seattle, to the point of beginning.</p>
                <p> 2. A responsible member of each family, and each individual living alone, in the
                    above described area will report between the hours of 8:00 A.M. and 5:00 P.M.,
                    Saturday, <date when="1942-04-25">April 25, 1942</date>, or during the same
                    hours on Sunday, <date when="1942-04-26">April 26, 1942</date>, to the Civil
                    Control Station located at :</p>
                <l>2100 Second Avenue,</l>
                <l> Seattle, Washington</l>
                <p> 3. Any person subject to this order who fails to comply with any of its
                    provisions or with the provisions of published instructions pertaining herto or
                    who is found in the above area after 12 o’clock noon, P.W.T., of Friday, May 1,
                    1942, will be liable to the criminal penalties provided by Public Law No.503,
                    77th Congress, approved March 21, 1942, entitled “An Act to Provide a Penalty
                    for Violation of Restrictions or Orders with Respect to Persons Entering,
                    Remaining in, Leaving, or Committing any Act in Military Areas or Zones,” and
                    alien Japanese will be subject to immediate apprehension and internment.</p>
                <l><ref type="#Dewitt">James L. DeWitt</ref> Lieutenant General, U.S. Army
                    Commanding</l>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div xml:id="emptyStallsClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                <head rendition="#date"><date when="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date>MAY 1,
                    1942</head>
                <head rendition="#title">EMPTY STALLS--EVACUATIONS</head>
                <head rendition="#paper">SEATTLE TIMES</head>
                <figure xml:id="emptyStallsImage">
                    <graphic url="../images/pikeplacenewTEIBP.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc>black and white vacant stalls at Pike Place Public Market</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p rendition="#description">Vacant stalls like these at <placeName ref="#pike_place"
                        >Pike Place Public Markets</placeName>, Inc., confronted shoppers at
                    numerous Seattle markets today. The Japanese operators of many of the stalls
                    have been evacuated. Japanese farmers who formerly took their produce to the
                    markets to sell it also were absent. Even though they live outside the
                    evacuation area, they are barred from the central business district by wartime
                    restrictions on movements of Japanese.</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div xml:id="halfOfCityClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                <head rendition="#title">HALF OF CITY'S</head>
                <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">JAPS HAVE GONE</head>
                <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
                <p rendition="#description">Seattle's central business district gave the appearance
                    of a city without Japanese today as the last of them from Zones No. 1 and 2, or
                    population, departed for the assembly center in Puyallup.</p>
                <p rendition="#description"> And the <placeName ref="#pike_place">Pike Place
                        Markets</placeName> for the first time in their years of operation, did
                    business without their myriad of Japanese-operated stalls. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"> It is estimated that only about half the Japanese of
                    the city have been removed but those who have gone were from areas in which many
                    were engaged in business and where they most often met public. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"> Those Japanese remaining in the city are restricted to
                    movement within the area in which they live. Beginning at noon, they and all
                    others of the Japanese race were banned from going to the central business
                    district, the waterfront or any place in the area to the north of the city that
                    lies west of Eastlake Avenue and Roosevelt Way, any place west of Fifth Avenue
                    in the central area, or any place south of Jackson Street in the southern area,
                    except for one small locality between Jackson and Dearborn Streets. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">This ban prevents any Japanese in the farming community
                    surrounding the city from delivering produce to Seattle firms personally, as
                    Produce Row and the markets cannot be reached without passing through a
                    restricted area.</p>
                <p rendition="#description"> The market master of the municipal market said that not
                    a single Japanese merchant appeared this morning, although the ban did not go
                    into effect until noon. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"> Operators of private markets said several Japanese
                    renters of stalls came early this morning with produce but brought Filipinos
                    with them to tend the stalls and left before noon. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">No date has been set for removal of the Japanese from
                    there</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="correspondence" xml:id="jenningsLetter">
                <opener>
                    <seg type="letterhead">
                        <name ref="#spl" rend="caps">Seattle Public Library</name><l/>
                        <name rend="caps">Seattle, Washington</name><l/>
                        <name ref="#jennings">Judson T. Jennings</name>, Librarian<l/>
                        <date when="1942-04-29">29 April 1942</date>
                    </seg>

                    <address>
                         <addrLine>Mr Clarence T. Arai</addrLine>
                         <addrLine>452-12th Avenue</addrLine>
                         <addrLine>Seattle, Washington</addrLine>
                    </address>
     
                    <salute>Dear Mr Arai:</salute>
                </opener>

                <p>Thank you kindly for the copies of “Our Times” by Mark Sullivan, and “The March
                    of Democracy by Adams, which you sent to the library yesterday.</p>

                <p> Both sets are being added to the Reference department.</p>

                <closer>
                    <salute>Cordially yours</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <figure xml:id="JTJenningsSignature">
                            <graphic url="../images/jenningsSignature.jpeg"/>
                            <figDesc><name ref="#jennings">J T Jennings</name></figDesc>
                            <figDesc>Librarian</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        JTJ/FRP
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="statement" xml:id="travelPermit">
                <opener>
                    <seg type="letterhead" rend="caps"> 
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Headquarters</addrLine> 
                            <addrLine>NWS &amp; 44th Infantry Division</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Office of Acting Provost Marshal</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>State of Washington</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Seattle, Washington</addrLine>
                        </address>
                    </seg>

                    <dateline style="text-align: right;"><date when="1942-05-02">May 2, 1942</date></dateline>

                    <salute rend="caps">To whom it may concern:</salute>
                </opener>
                
                <p>The applicant named, <name rend="caps">Clarence Arai</name>, an American citizen
                    of Japanese blood is hereby granted permission and authorized to travel without
                    molestation or hindrance by the most direct route from 452 12th Avenue, Seattle,
                    Washington to the <name ref="#spl">Seattle Public Library</name>, 4th and
                    Madison Street and the Federal Reserve National Bank of Commerce Building,
                    Seattle, Washington. Travel authorized will be effective <date when="1942-05-05"
                        >Tuesday, May 5, 1942</date> between the hours of 11:00 A.M. and 2:00 P.M.
                        <hi rend="caps">Nothing follows.</hi></p>

                <signed>
                    <figure xml:id="MichaelARivistoSignature">
                        <graphic url="../images/rivistoSignature.jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc>Illegible signature</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <hi rend="caps">Michael A. Rivisto</hi><lb/>
                    Captain Infantry<lb/>
                    Acting Provost Marshal<lb/>
                    State of Washington<lb/>
                    <seg type="stamped" style="color: blue;">
                        <hi rend="caps">Michael A. Rivisto</hi><lb/>
                        Captain, Infantry<lb/>
                        NWS. PCF
                    </seg>
                    <seg rend="caps" style="text-align: left;">
                        MM<lb/>
                        Temporary Permit #18
                    </seg>
                </signed>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div xml:id="moreJapaneseGetOrdersClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                <head rendition="#title">More Japanese Get</head>
                <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">Evacuation Orders</head>
                <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
                <head rendition="#author #center">By R. B. Bermann</head>

                <p rendition="#description">Evacuation of all Japanese from Kitsap County, western
                    Pierce County and the southwestern tip of King County was decreed yesterday in
                    orders by <name ref="#DeWitt">Lieut. Gen. John L. DeWitt</name> commanding the
                    Western Defense Command and Fourth Army.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">One order, No. 67, takes in Tacoma, Fort Lewis, McChord
                    Field, Steilacoom and that portion of King County west of Highway 99 and south
                    of Des Moines. The 1,100 Japanese living in this area are to be evacuated by
                    noon Monday.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">OTHER AREAS</p>
                <p rendition="#description">The other order, No. 68, takes in the Puget Sound Navy
                    Yard at Bremerton and all the rest of Kitsap County, except Bainbridge Island
                    which was evacuated earlier; Vashon Island in King County and the island and
                    Olympic Peninsula sections of Pierce County. The 200 Japanese living in this
                    area are to be evacuated by noon Saturday.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">The destination of the Japanese affected by these orders
                    was not announced, but the fact that they were advised they would not be
                    permitted to use private automobiles was constructed as an indication that they
                    will not be sent to the assembly center in Puyallup.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">It was considered probable that they would be sent to
                    the assembly center at Pinedale, Calif., to join evacuees from the rural
                    districts of King and Pierce counties who have already been moved there.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Prospective evacuees in the area covered by Order No. 67
                    will register between 8 a.m. and 5 p. m. today and tomorrow at a civil control
                    station at 1715 S. Tacoma Ave., Tacoma.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">There will be two registration points, open during the
                    same hours on the same days, for the other area—one in the Bowers Building on
                    MainSt., Poulsbo, and the other</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div xml:id="exclusionAreasClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                <head rendition="#paper">SEATTLE POST-INTELLIGENCER, WEDNESDAY, MAY 18, 1942</head>
                <head rendition="#title">NEW EXCLUSION AREAS</head>
                <head rendition="#date">P.1 5/13/42</head>
                <figure xml:id="firstExclusionAreaImage">
                    <graphic url="../images/firstExclusionAreaTEIPB.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc>Camp Harmony Bedroom</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p rendition="#description">PROHIBITED ZONE—Map of the area covered by Exclusion
                    Order No. 67, from which Japanese will be cleared by Monday. </p>
                <figure xml:id="secondExclusionAreaImage">
                    <graphic url="../images/secondExclusionAreaTEIBP.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc>Camp Harmony Bedroom</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p rendition="#description"> UNDER BAN, TOO—The territory inside the heavy line is
                    covered by Exclusion Order No. 68, effective on Saturday.</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div xml:id="registrationClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                <head rendition="#date">TUESDAY</head>
                <head rendition="#date"><date when="1942-05-12"/>P.1 5/12/42</head>
                <head rendition="#title">REGISTRATION</head>
                <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">OF REMAINING</head>
                <head rendition="#title #titleIndent #titleIndent">JAPS STARTS</head>
                <head rendition="#subTitle #center">All Left in Seattle to Get</head>
                <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Assignments by Tonight;</head>
                <head rendition="#subTitle #center">New County Orders Seen</head>
                <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
                <p rendition="#description">Registration of all Japanese remaining in Seattle
                    started yesterday and will continue today at the newest civil control station,
                    2203 E. Madison St.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Like the registrations which preceded it, everything was
                    varied out in an orderly manner with a minimum of confusion. It is expected that
                    1,098 Japanese remain in the last Seattle district to be evacuated, and all will
                    be registered and get their Puyallup center assignments by 5 o’clock this
                    evening.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">PUYALLUP, TOO</p>
                <p rendition="#description">At the same time, registration was proceeding in
                    Puyallup of some 1,000 Japanese living in Eastern Pierce County. They are to be
                    sent to an evacuation center at Pinedale, Calif., where Japanese from rural King
                    County south of Seattle are also going.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Among those who registered yesterday were a number of
                    Japanese who are married to men or women of other races.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Orders are expected this week to evacuate all of the
                    remaining Japanese in King County. They still remain in rural areas north and
                    east of Seattle, and a smaller portion of Southern King County.</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div xml:id="campHarmonyJapsClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                <head rendition="#title #center">Camp Harmony Japs</head>
                <head rendition="#title #center">Living Up to Name</head>
                <head rendition="#center">___________</head>
                <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Seattle Evacuees Making Best of</head>
                <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Site, Despite New Conditions</head>
                <head rendition="#date">SEATTLE, <date when="1942-05-25">MAY 25, 1942</date></head>
                <head rendition="#center">___________</head>
                <head rendition="#author #center">By R. B. Bermann</head>
                <head rendition="#author #center">Post-Intelligencer Staff Correspondent</head>

                <p rendition="#description">CAMP HARMONY, Puyallup, May 24—Although some of them
                    have been here scarcely a week, Seattle Japanese are adjusting themselves
                    rapidly to conditions at this assembly center, and the camp is really living up
                    to its name.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Life is very different from anything to which they had
                    been accustomed, but they are making the best of things as they found them, and
                    remarkably few complaints are heard.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Maybe the secret lies in the fact that they have so
                    little idle time on their hands. If they are not just before the travel of all
                    Japanese was restricted. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">Her husband build a wardrobe, a linen closet, a vanity
                    and bench and other bedroom furniture out of scrap lumber and she supplied the
                    feminine touch with draperies that give the room a really homelike
                    appearance.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">A completely democratic spirit prevails in the camp,
                    because practically everyone is on the same economic status.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">This is because there is so little difference in scales
                    of pay. A common laborer receives $8 a month,</p>
                <p rendition="#description #center">__________________________________</p>
                <figure xml:id="campHarmonyImage">
                    <graphic url="../images/campHarmonyBedroomTEIBP.jpg"/>
                    <figDesc>Camp Harmony Bedroom</figDesc>
                </figure>

                <p rendition="#description">COMFORT OF HOME—Mrs. Robert Hosokawa, recent Willamette
                    coed, laying out a new apron in the cozy apartment which she and her husband
                    have contrived to make out of their bare barracks. Her husband constructed the
                    furniture out of scrap lumber and his drive of two months achieved the rest with
                    a few draperies.</p>
                <p rendition="#description #center">__________________________________</p>

                <p rendition="#description">busy on work details or administrative duties, there is
                    always something to do around their temporary homes — because the army didn’t
                    have time to indulge in any of the niceties of interior decoration in
                    constructing their barracks. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">And, as if that weren’t enough, many of them have put in
                    tiny Victory Gardens. For instance, Clarence Arai, for years a prominent Seattle
                    attorney, has put in radishes, beets, Chinese lettuce and onions — and his
                    little plot is as meticulously neat as if he were a professional gardener. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">They take pride in the amount of ingenuity they can show
                    in making their primitive quarters look more like the homes they left behind
                    them.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">An outstanding example in this respect is furnished by
                    the apartment where <name>Robert Hosokawa</name>, formerly a furniture salesman
                    in Seattle, is spending his honeymoon. His brider, the former <name>Yoshi
                        Yoshizawa</name>, twenty, was a junior in Willamette University when the
                    first evacuation orders were issued. She hurried to Seattle to be married [...]
                    a skilled laborer $12 and a professional man or woman $16. This pay, of course,
                    is in addition to their board and lodging and medical and dental attention.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">The dental clinic is one of the busiest centers in the
                    camp, with as many as eighteen or twenty patients in a single morning — which
                    isn’t excessive in view of the fact that the center has an estimated population
                    of 7,500.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Six former Seattle dentists are on duty there —
                        <name>Dr. S. Higashida</name> and his son, Robert; <name>Dr. H.
                        Mitsumori</name>, <name>Dr. F. Kinemori</name>, <name>Dr. G. Y.
                        Nomura</name> and <name>Dr. S. Ishihashi</name>.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">A paper has been started, with <name>Dick
                        Takeuchi</name>, former editor of the Great Northern Daily News, in charge.
                    Takeuchi, who was a journalism senior at the University of Washington, has
                    tentatively called the paper the Camp Harmony News Letter, but he isn’t
                    satisfied and has asked his readers to suggest other names. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"><name>Dyke Miyagawa</name>, another University of
                    Washington senior, is his managing editor, and Taka Oka, a sophomore, is
                    assistant managing editor. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"><name>Keith Oka</name>, formerly employed at the
                    Craftsmen’s Press, is art editor, and <name>Tad Kuniyuki</name>, formerly sports
                    editor for the Japanese American Courier, has a similar job there. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"><name>James Y. Sakamoto</name>, former publisher of the
                    Japanese American Courier and now chief Japanese supervisor of the camp, has set
                    up his headquarters underneath the grandstand on the fairgrounds and keeps busy
                    from morning to night consulting with members of his staff. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"><name>Bill Hosokawa</name>, University of Washington
                    graduate and former editor of a newspaper in Singapore, is his chief adjutant.
                    The headquarters staff is divided into five general sections, with <name>George
                        Ishihara</name>, produce shipper, in charge of personnel; <name>Jack
                        Maki</name>, associate in the Far Eastern department at the University of
                    Washington, in charge of information; <name>Dick Setsuda</name>, beer
                    distributor, in charge of operations; <name>Thomas Iseri</name>, Auburn produce
                    shipper, in charge of supply, and <name>Julius Fujihara</name>, in charge of
                    police, fire, postal and other services.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">Leaders of the four areas into which the center is
                    divided are <name>William Mimbu</name>, attorney; <name>Yakeo Nogaki</name> and
                        <name>Teruji Umino</name>, both bank clerks, and <name>Hiroyuki (“Lefty”)
                        Ichihara</name>, who had a fishing tackle store in Seattle.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">All of these executives, incidentally, are American-born
                    Japanese. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">Life in the camp is by no means all work and no play. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">Churches have supplied a piano for each of the four
                    areas and there is plenty of community singing and choir practice.</p>
                <p rendition="#description">There are athletic facilities for all ages, and a number
                    of soft ball and ping pong tournaments are already in progress. </p>
                <p rendition="#description">There are recreational rooms in each area. </p>
                <p rendition="#description"><name>Jack Maki</name>, the former University faculty
                    member, summed up the attitude of the evacuees when he said: </p>
                <p rendition="#description">“We aren’t being mistreated, but, on the other hand, we
                    aren’t being pampered — I think everybody’s doing a swell job.</p>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="correspondence" xml:id="quigleyLetter">
                <opener>
                    <dateline><date when="1942-06-02" style="text-align: right;">June 2, 1942</date></dateline>

                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Mr. Clarence T. Arai</addrLine> 
                        <addrLine>Puyallup</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Washington</addrLine>
                    </address>

                    <salute>Dear Mr. Arai:</salute>
                </opener>

                <p>The members of the Board of the <name ref="#spl">Seattle Public Library</name>
                    wish to express to you our regret that you are unable to serve longer with them
                    in the labor of sreving the citizens of Seattle in their library needs.</p>
                <p> We do wish, however, to let you know how much we have enjoyed your disinterested
                    advice - your willingness to serve faithfully and your just approach to all
                    problems that have come before the Board.</p>
                <p>Your viewpoint has always been wholesome, un- prejudiced and eminently fair and
                    we shall all miss your congenial companionship at our Board meetings, as well as
                    the presence of Mrs. Arai and yourself at the annual banquet of the <name
                        ref="#staff_association">Staff Association.</name></p>
                <p>While we recognize that under present conditions many things arise that give much
                    distress, we know that your sound philosophy and unfailing good humour will ever
                    attend you.</p>

                <closer> 
                    <salute>Sincerely yours</salute>
                    <name ref="#spl" rend="caps">Seattle Public Library Board</name>
                    <signed>
                        <figure xml:id="splSignatures">
                            <graphic url="../images/4signatures.jpeg"/>
                            <figDesc><name>Josephine M. Quigley</name></figDesc>
                            <figDesc>President</figDesc>
                            <figDesc><name>Christine A. Neergaard</name></figDesc>
                            <figDesc>Two more illegible signatures</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>

            <pb/>

            <div type="correspondence" xml:id="frostLetter">
                <opener>
                    <seg type="letterhead">
                        <address rend="caps">
                            <addrLine><name ref="#staff_association">Seattle Public Library Staff
                                    Association</name></addrLine>
                            <addrLine>4th Ave. <hi rend="lowercase">and</hi> Madison St.</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Seattle, Washington</addrLine>
                        </address>
                    </seg>

                     <dateline style="text-align: center;"><date when="1942-05-25">25 May 1942</date></dateline>
     
                     <address>
                         <addrLine>Mr Clarence T. Arai</addrLine>
                         <addrLine>(H/S)taff Headquarters, Camp Harmony</addrLine>
                         <!--note to self: fix corrections like above-->
                         <addrLine>Section 2, no. 79</addrLine>
                         <addrLine>Puyallup, Washington</addrLine>
                     </address>
     
                     <salute>Dear Mr Arai:</salute>
                 </opener>
                
                <p>Greetings from the Seventh Annual Banquet of the S(E/e)attle Public Library Staff
                    Association to both you and Mrs Arai.</p>

                <p>We were so sorry not to have you with us Friday night. We tried to make it an
                    especially nice affair since it was to be the last one before <name ref="#jennings">Mr Jennings</name> retired. As toastmistress, I read your
                    letter and when the suggestion was made that greetings be sent to you, you
                    should have heard the applause, so you can see what a place you hold in our
                    minds and hearts.</p>

                <p>The dining room at the Ranier Club looked very beautiful with the tables
                    decorated with rhododendrons and iris and colorful programs, serving also as
                    place cards. There were one hundred and forty-one present.</p>

                <p>Between courses we sang the songs printed in the program and then we had a series
                    of humorous book reviews supposedly suggestions for the book case in the new
                    house <name ref="#jennings">Mr Jennings</name> is building across Lake
                    Washington. After the last of these the group burst into the song “For He’s a
                    Jolly Good Fellow.” Then we said we had a real book for him and Miss Andrus
                    presented him with the portfolio of letters, one of which you wrote, - there
                    were over a hundred altogether, and was he pleased!</p>

                <p>He made a little speech of appreciation and then it was Mrs. Quigley’s turn to
                    add to the book-shelf. She presented him with a book containing a diploma saying <!--note to self: address weird thingy here?-->
                    that he had completed thirty-five years of successful service “summa cum laude”,
                    and then she presented Mr Richards, the new librarian, with a schedule book such
                    as they give Freshmen at the University, listing the courses he’d have to take
                    such as Handling the Board, Pleasing the Staff, Balancing the Budget, etc. Mr
                    Richards then said briefly how pleased he and Mrs Richards were to be included
                    and how much he was looking forward to his work.</p>

                <p>Last of all we said we thought the best books to have on our shelves were the
                    master works that were standbys through thick and thin to guide and comfort us
                    and then Miss Eberlin presented <name ref="#jennings">Mr Jennings</name> with a
                    Columbia Master Works Album of Beethoven’s “Tempest” Sonata, first speaking of
                    records and how librarians have always”kept</p>

                <pb/>

                <ab type="letterhead">
                    <address rend="caps">
                        <addrLine><name ref="#staff_association">Seattle Public Library Staff
                                Association</name></addrLine>
                        <addrLine>4th Ave. <hi rend="lowercase">and</hi> Madison St.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Seattle, Washington</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </ab>

                <ab type="pgNum" style="text-align: center;">-2-</ab>

                <p>records” religiously. But she said that after we had gotten this record it
                    occurred to us he would need something to play it on it on and so there was a
                    companion volume to this. Covered with a cloth in the alcover back of the
                    speakers table was an R.C.A. Radio-Victrola which Miss Eberlin then uncovered.
                        <name ref="#jennings">Mr Jennings</name> was quite overcome. “I can’t say
                    anything” was all he could say, so we joined hands around the table and sang
                    Auld Lang Syne, and that was the end.</p>

                <p>We surely wished many times during the evening that you and Mrs Arai might be
                    with us and I know I am expressing the feeling of the whole group when I say
                    that you have our very best wishes and that we hope this trying period through
                    which you are passing may seem more bearable as time goes on. This morning’s P-I
                    <!--maybe make a note saying this is probably the post intelligencer?--> carries
                    your picture and tells of your new work. “You can’t keep a good man down”, you
                    know.</p>

                <closer> 
                    <salute>Sincerely your friend</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <figure xml:id="frostSignature">
                            <graphic url="../images/frostSignature.jpeg"/>
                            <figDesc><name>Alice A. Frost</name></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        (E/A)AF/FRP       President, <name ref="#staff_association">Seattle Public Library<lb/>
                        Staff Association</name>
                    </signed>
                </closer>

                <postscript>
                    <label>P.S.</label>
                    <p>Miss Calkins, head of our Reference department, is coming with a friend to
                        Puyallup tomorrow and will be at the gate of the Camp at 5:30 and will be
                        very happy to see you if you can be there.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>

        </body>

        <back>
            <div type="annotations">
                <note xml:id="spl"> During World War II, the Seattle Public Library continued to
                    serve incarcerated Japanese American patrons, sending almost 7,000 books to Camp
                        Minidoka.<ref target="#spl_historylink_bib"/>
                </note>
                <!--minidoka-->
                <!--maybe we should make ones for exclusion orders 67 and/or 68 too?-->
                <note xml:id="akc"> The American Kennel Club is a nonprofit registry of purebred dog
                    pedigrees. <ref target="#akc_bib"/>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="jennings"> Librarian Judson T. Jennings (1873-1948) was the director
                    of the <name ref="#spl">Seattle Public Library</name> from 1907 to 1942. Upon
                    reaching the mandatory retirement age, he became the first chair of the King
                    County Rural Library District (now the King County Library System).<ref
                        target="#spl_historylink_bib"/>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="staff_association"> The <name ref="#spl">Seattle Public Library</name>
                    Staff Association was established in 1935 to address staff problems including
                    lack of pension, cuts to hours and vacation, and staff reductions.<ref
                        target="#spl_historylink_bib"/>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="pike_place"> Pike Place Market is a public market in Seattle that
                    opened in 1907. This is one of the oldest continuously operated public markets
                    in the United States.<ref target="#pike_place_market_bib"/>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="dore"> John F. Dore (1881-1938) served as the Mayor of Seattle from
                    1932 to 1934 and from 1936 to 1938.</note>
                <note xml:id="fujiyama"> Aiichiro Fujiyama was the Japanese Foreign Minister from
                        1957-1960.<ref target="#fujiyama_bib"/>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="DeWitt"> J.L. DeWitt was a United States general officer known for
                    overseeing the incarceration of over 110,000 Japanese Americans.<ref
                        target="#dewitt_bib"/>
                </note>
                <!--spl staff association 7th banquet program (is referenced in a letter i transcribed and is included in the scrapbook but i didn't transcribe it)-->
                <!--seattle post intelligencer?-->
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="arai_bib" type="webpage"> "<title>Clarence Takeya Arai</title>."
                            <author>Mary Schons</author>
                        <publisher>EBSCO</publisher>
                        <date>2023</date>
                        <ref
                            target="https://www.ebsco.com/research-starters/history/clarence-takeya-arai"
                            >Clarence Takeya Arai</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="akc_bib" type="webpage"> “<title level="a">American Kennel
                            Club</title>. <title level="m">Wikipedia</title>
                        <publisher>Wikipedia.org</publisher>
                        <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Kennel_Club">American
                            Kennel Club</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="pike_place_market_bib" type="webpage"> “<title level="a">Pike
                            Place Market</title>. <title level="m">Wikipedia</title>
                        <publisher>Wikipedia.org</publisher>
                        <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/
                            wiki/Pike_Place_Market">Pike Place Market</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="spl_historylink_bib" type="webpage"> “<title>Central Library,
                            1906-1957, The Seattle Public Library</title>.” <author>Paula
                            Becker</author>
                        <publisher>HistoryLink.org</publisher>
                        <date>7/01/2011</date>
                        <ref target="https://www.historylink.org/File/9869">Central Library,
                            1906-1957, The Seattle Public Library</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="fujiyama_bib" type="webpage"> "<title level="a">Aiichiro Fujiyama,
                            87; Ex-Japanese Politician</title>." <publisher>New York
                            Times</publisher>
                        <ref
                            target="https://www.nytimes.com/1985/02/23/world/aiichiro-fujiyama-87-ex-japanese-politician.html"
                            >Aiichiro Fujiyama, 87; Ex-Japanese Politician</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="dewitt_bib" type="webpage">
                        <title level="a">John Lesene DeWitt</title>
                        <publisher>National Park Service</publisher>
                        <date>04/03/2024</date>
                        <ref target="https://www.nps.gov/people/john-lesesne-dewitt.htm">John
                            Lesesne DeWitt</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
