<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Selections from the Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
                <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
                <editor xml:id="MO">Marisa Oishi</editor>
                <editor xml:id="CL">Christine Leak</editor>
                <editor xml:id="HS">Hannah Swoffer</editor>
                <sponsor>University of Washington Libraries, Special Collections</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p>This edition focuses on a selection of pages from Clarence T. Arai’s scrapbook
                    held in the University of Washington Special Collections.</p>
                <p>We chose to work with a scrapbook because of the vulnerability conveyed through
                    its visual and textual features. This edition, only a small selection of pieces
                    from the full work, explores the choices Arai made in assembling his scrapbook,
                    considering how these preserved materials capture a personal experience during
                    World War II and contribute to a more holistic, human understanding of the
                    period.</p>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Washington Student Project for TXTDS 404: Texts, Publics,
                    and Publication</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2025-06-06">June 6th, 2025</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available for use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
                    <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
                    <pubPlace>University of Washington, Special Collections Manuscripts and
                        Archives</pubPlace>
                    <date from="1919" to="1993">1919-1993</date>
                    <idno type="oclcNo">945773039</idno>
                    <idno type="accessionNo">acc5542-001</idno>
                    <note>Box 2</note>
                    <note>This scrapbook, assembled by Clarence T. Arai, provides a perspective on
                        his life as a Japanese American in Seattle before and during World War II.
                        It includes correspondences, newspaper clippings, certificates, and other
                        artifacts Arai selected to preserve.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
          <div type="editorial_intro">
              <p>The phrase "on paper" is an interesting one. On paper, Clarence Takeya Arai was an accomplished and influential member of the Seattle community. He was the first Japanese American to earn a law degree from the University of Washington and the first nisei commissioned officer in the US Army Reserve. He was a founder and the first president of the Japanese American Citizens League, the oldest Asian American civil rights organization, as well as a Republican precinct committee member and delegate to the Washington State Republican Convention. On paper, Arai and his family were sent to the Puyallup Fairgrounds, and then to a concentration camp in Minidoka, Idaho, when over a hundred thousand innocent Japanese Americans were incarcerated during World War II. His health deteriorated there, but he continued to advocate for Japanese Americans' legal rights within the camp. Three months after the war ended, his son Ken died of a brain tumor. Arai gave up practicing law full time and took up photography. He died less than twenty years later. </p>
                  <p>When we discovered the Clarence T. Arai papers in the University of Washington Special Collections, we didn't just discover certificates and newspaper clippings taped to yellowing pages that crumbled as we turned them. This was a life, a collection of moments of pride and tragedy, lived in service to his community and yet persecuted by his country. This was an autobiography, a telling of Arai's story through the papers he decided to preserve. He had a Cocker Spaniel named Duke of Main Street. His son Ken liked "hot dog sandwiches" and bus rides to Portland. On paper, Arai was a lawyer, civil rights advocate, and photographer. But on paper, he was also a gardener, a father, a man with dreams and indignation with the injustice he knew he was living: a human.</p>
                 <p> Regrettably, we could not include every insightful artifact in Arai’s scrapbook. We each chose a genre (personal correspondences, state issues, and newspaper articles) and selected a few pages from that genre, maintaining original spellings and punctuation to preserve authenticity. Our goal was to provide a glimpse into the first-hand experiences of Japanese Americans in Washington before and during World War II. Arai’s scrapbook offers a perspective unlike textbooks or documentaries, providing insight on lived experiences through his personal memorabilia and artifacts. By publishing this work, we hope that readers will gain a more well-rounded, holistic perspective on this time period, and an awareness of Arai’s life and enduring legacy. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="annotations">
              
          </div>
      </front>
      <body>
            <div><ab>In Appreciation

Presented to 

Mr. Clarence T. Arai 

	On behalf of Aiichiro Fujiyama, Minister for Foreign Affairs of Japan, I convey to you the commendations of the Japanese Government for your exemplary citizenship and leadership in the affairs of your community 

	Your unremitting and dedicated endeavors have contributed greatly to the development and strengthening of admirable relations between the United States and Japan, as well as between Americans and Japanese within your own community. 

	On this auspicious occasion commemorating the 100th Anniversary of the Treaty of Friendship and Trade between the United States and Japan, I am privileged to present to you this mokuahi from the Japanese Government as a token of heartfelt appreciation for your unswerving devotion to the cause of peace and understanding between our two countries. 

	Presented at Seattle, Washington this 22nd day of May, 1960. 

Consul-General of Japan 
_______(signature)______
Yoshiharu Takeno</ab>
</div>

<div><ab>SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION 
WASHINGTON, D.C.

THIS·IS·TO·CERTIFY·THAT 
Clarence T. Arai
IS·REGISTERED· IN·THE·ARCHIVES·OF·THE·INSTITUTION·AS·A 
PATRON 
OF·THE·SMITHSONIAN·SCIENTIFIC·SERIES·IN·RECOGNITION·OF·HIS·AID·TO·THE· INSTITUTION’S·PROGRAM·FOR·THE·DIFFUSION·OF·KNOWLEDGE·AMONG·MEN· AND·THE·INCREASE·OF·ITS·FINANCIAL·ENDOWMENT·FOR·SCIENTIFIC·RESEARCH

IN·WITNESS·WHEREOF·THE·SEAL· OF ·THE· INSTITUTION·AND ·THE ·SIGNATURES·OF ·THE·SECRETARY ·AND·THE·ADMINISTRATION·ASSISTANT·ARE ·AFFIXED·HERETO

___________(signature)_________
            SECRETARY 


____(signature)_______________
                           ADMINISTRATIVE ASSISTANT </ab></div>
                                             
<div><ab>THE BUTTS’ PAROLE LEAGUE
Box 70, Nippon Station
Seattle, Washington
April 2, 1937

Clarence T. Arai, Esq.,
Seattle, Wn.

Sir;-

Permit us to offer our congratulations and best wishes toward your future as a trustee of the Seattle Public Library.

Mayor John F. Dore, in choosing you, thus for the first time in the history of Seattle according recognition to the people you so ably represent, we know made a selection which will undoubtedly redound to his and your credit.

THE BUTTS’ PAROLE LEAGUE.
by Frank O. Murphy</ab></div>

<div><ab>REGISTRATION CERTIFICATE
AMERICAN KENNEL CLUB
AKC
INCORPORATED

AMERICAN KENNEL CLUB STUD BOOK
AMERICAN KENNEL CLUB
NEW YORK, N.Y.

NAME OF DOG   Duke of Main Street
BREED    Cocker Spaniel    Sex  Male
SIRE    Slicker Boy of Kitsop (934421)
DAM   Paul’s Queenie (898745)
WHELPED   March 14, 1934
COLOR   Red
BREEDER   M. Ellen Paul
OWNER  Clarence T. Arai

REGISTERED   June 15, 1934
ASSIGNED NO   941308
VOLUME   51
August     ISSUE

Perry B Rice
SECRETARY
gm</ab></div>

<div><ab>Headquarters
Western Defense Command 
And Fourth Army 
Presidio of San Francisco, California 
- - -
Public Proclamation No. 3 
- - -
March 24, 1942

TO: 	The people within the States of Washington, Oregon, California, Montana, Idaho,                                             Nevada, Utah and Arizona, and the Public Generally: 

	WHEREAS, By Public Proclamation No.1, dated March 2, 1942, this headquarters, there were designated and established Military Areas Nos. 1 and 2 and Zones thereof, and 

	WHEREAS, By Public Proclamation No. 2, dated March 2, 1942, this headquarters, there were designated and established Military Areas Nos. 3,4,5 and 6 and Zones thereof, and 

	WHEREAS, The present situation within these Military Areas and Zones requires as a matter of military necessity the establishment of certain regulations pertaining to all enemy aliens and all persons of Japanese ancestry within said Military Areas and Zones thereof: 
	
Now, THEREFORE, I, J.L. DEWITT, Lieutenant General, U.S. Army, by virtue of the authority vested in me by the President of the United States and by the Secretary of War and my powers and prerogatives as Commanding General, Western Defense Command, do hereby declare and establish the following regulations covering the conduct to be observed by all alien Japanese, all alien Germans, all alien Italians, and all persons of Japanese ancestry residing or being within the Military Areas above described, or such portions thereof as are hereinafter mentioned :

From and after 6:00 A.M., March 27, 1942, all alien Japanese, all alien Germans, all alien Italians, and all persons of Japanese ancestry residing or being within the geographical limits of Military Area No.1, or within any of the Zones 
</ab></div>
          
<div><ab>Headquarters 
Western Defense Command 
And Fourth Army 
Presidio of San Francisco, California
April 24th, 1942 

Civilian Exclusion Order No.17

Pursuant to the provisions of Public Proclamations Nos. 1 and 2, this Headquarters, dated March 2, 1942, and March 16, 1942, respectively, it is hereby ordered that from and after 12 o’clock noon, P.W.T., of Friday, May 1, 1942, all persons of Japanese ancestry, both alien and non-aline, be excluded from that portion of Military Area No. 1 described as follows: 

All that portion of the City of Seattle, State of Washington, within that boundary beginning at the point at which the northerly limits of said city meet Shilshole Bay ; thence easterly and following the northerly limits of said city to Roosevelt Way ; thence southerly and following Roosevelt Way, Eastlake Avenue, fairview Avenue, Virginia Street, and Westlake Avenue to Fifth Avenue ; thence southeasterly on Fifth Avenue to Yesler Way ; thence easterly on Yesler Way to Maynard Avenue ; thence southerly on Maynard Avenue to Jackson Street ; thence westerly on jackson Street to Elliott Bay ; thence north-westerly and northerly, and following the westerly limits of the CIty of Seattle, to the point of beginning. 

 A responsible member of each family, and each individual living alone, in the above described area will report between the hours of 8:00 A.M. and 5:00 P.M., Saturday, April 25, 1942, or during the same hours on Sunday, April 26, 1942, to the Civil Control Station located at : 

2100 Second Avenue, 
Seattle, Washington. 

Any person subject to this order who fails to comply with any of its provisions or with the provisions of published instructions pertaining herto or who is found in the above area after 12 o’clock noon, P.W.T., of Friday, May 1, 1942, will be liable to the criminal penalties provided by Public Law No.503, 77th Congress, approved March 21, 1942, entitled “An Act to Provide a Penalty for Violation of Restrictions or Orders with Respect to Persons Entering, Remaining in, Leaving, or Committing any Act in Military Areas or Zones,” and alien Japanese will be subject to immediate apprehension and internment. 

J. L. DEWITT 
Lieutenant General, U.S. Army 
Commanding </ab></div>

<div><ab>MAY 1, 1942
EMPTY STALLS—EVACUATIONS
SEATTLE TMES

HALF OF THE CITY’S 
JAPS HAVE GONE
          
    Seattle’s central business district gave the appearance of a city without Japanese today as the last of them from Zones No. 1 and 2, or population, departed for the assembly center in Puyallup.
    And the Pike Place Markets for the first time in their years of operation, did business without their myriad of Japanese-operated stalls. 
    It is estimated that only about half the Japanese of the city have been removed but those who have gone were from areas in which many were engaged in business and where they most often met public.
    Those Japanese remaining in the city are restricted to movement within the area in which they live. Beginning at noon, they and all others of the Japanese race were banned from going to the central business district, the waterfront or any place in the area to the north of the city that lies west of Eastlake Avenue and Roosevelt Way, any place west of Fifth Avenue in the central area, or any place south of Jackson Street in the southern area, except for one small locality between Jackson and Dearborn Streets.
    This ban prevents any Japanese in the farming community sur- rounding the city from delivering produce to Seattle firms personally, as Produce Row and the markets cannot be reached without passing through a restricted area.
    The market master of the municipal market said that not a single Japanese merchant appeared this morning, although the ban did not go into effect until noon.
    Operators of private markets said several Japanese renters of stalls came early this morning with produce but brought Filipinos with them to tend the stalls and left before noon.
The contingent of Japanese which left Seattle for Puyallup today swelled the population of Camp Harmony, the assembly on the Western Washington Fairgrounds, to more than 2,000. About 200 Japanese are there from Alaska. 
    No date has been set for removal of the Japanese from there
    
Vacant stalls like these at Pike Place Public Markets, Inc. confronted shoppers at numerous Seattle markets today. These Japanese operators of many of the stalls have been evacuated. Japanese farmers who formerly took their produce to the markets to sell it also were absent. Even though they live outside the evacuation area, they are barred from the central business district by wartime restrictions on movements of Japanese. </ab></div>

<div><ab>SEATTLE PUBLIC LIBRARY
SEATTLE, WASHINGTON
Judson T. Jennings, Librarian
29 April 1942

Mr Clarence T. Arai
452-12th Avenue
Seattle, Washington

Dear Mr Arai:

Thank you kindly for the copies of “Our Times” by Mark Sullivan, and “The March of Democracy by Adams, which you sent to the library yesterday.

Both sets are being added to the Reference department.

Cordially yours

J T Jennings
JTJ/FRP   Librarian
</ab></div>

<div><ab>HEADQUARTERS
NWS &amp; 44TH INFANTRY DIVISION
OFFICE OF ACTING PROVOST MARSHAL
STATE OF WASHINGTON
SEATTLE, WASHINGTON

May 2, 1942

TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN:
The applicant named, CLARENCE ARAI, an American citizen of   Japa- nese blood is hereby granted permission and authorized to travel without molestation or hindrance by the most direct route from 452 12th Avenue, Seattle, Washington to the Seattle Public Library, 4th and Madison Street and the Federal Reserve National Bank of Commerce Building, Seattle, Washington.   Travel authorized will be effective Tuesday, May 5, 1942 between the hours of 11:00 A.M. and 2:00 P.M.    NOTHING FOLLOWS.

(signature)
MICHAEL A. RIVISTO
Captain Infantry
Acting Provost Marshal
State of Washington
MICHAEL A. RIVISTO
Captain, Infantry
NWS. PCF

MM
TEMPORARY PERMIT #18</ab></div>

<div><ab>SEATTLE POST-INTELLIGENCER, WEDNESDAY, MAY 18, 1942
NEW EXCLUSION AREAS
P.1  5/13/42

PROHIBITED ZONE—Map of the area covered by Exclusion Order No. 67, from which Japanese will be cleared by Monday. 
UNDER BAN, TOO—The territory inside the heavy line is covered by Exclusion Order No. 68, effective on Saturday.</ab></div>

<div><ab>More Japanese Get
Evacuation Orders
________________
By R. B. Bermann 
    Evacuation of all Japanese from Kitsap County, western Pierce County and the southwestern tip of King County was decreed yesterday in orders by Lieut. Gen. John L. DeWitt, commanding the Western Defense Command and Fourth Army.
    One order, No. 67, takes in Tacoma, Fort Lewis, McChord Field, Steilacoom and that portion of King County west of Highway 99 and south of Des Moines. The 1,100 Japanese living in this area are to be evacuated by noon Monday.
OTHER AREAS	
    The other order, No. 68, takes in the Puget Sound Navy Yard at Bremerton and all the rest of Kitsap County, except Bainbridge Island which was evacuated earlier; Vashon Island in King County and the island and Olympic Peninsula sections of Pierce County. The 200 Japanese living in this area are to be evacuated by noon Saturday. 
    The destination of the Japanese affected by these orders was not announced, but the fact that they were advised they would not be permitted to use private automobiles was constructed as an indication that they will not be sent to the assembly center in Puyallup. 
    It was considered probable that they would be sent to the assembly center at Pinedale, Calif., to join evacuees from the rural districts of King and Pierce counties who have already been moved there. 
    Prospective evacuees in the area covered by Order No. 67 will register between 8 a.m. and 5 p. m. today and tomorrow at a civil control station at 1715 S. Tacoma Ave., Tacoma. 
    There will be two registration points, open during the same hours on the same days, for the other area—one in the Bowers Building on MainSt., Poulsbo, and the other</ab></div>

<div><ab>TUESDAY
P.1  5/12/42
REGISTRATION
OF REMAININ
JAPS STARTS


All Left in Seattle to Get Assignments by Tonight; New County Orders Seen
_______________
    Registration of all Japanese remaining in Seattle started yesterday and will continue today at the newest civil control station, 2203 E. Madison St.
    Like the registrations which preceded it, everything was varied out in an orderly manner with a minimum of confusion. It is expected that 1,098 Japanese remain in the last Seattle district to be evacuated, and all will be registered and get their Puyallup center assignments by 5 o’clock this evening.
PUYALLUP, TOO
    At the same time, registration was proceeding in Puyallup of some 1,000 Japanese living in Eastern Pierce County. They are to be sent to an evacuation center at Pinedale, Calif., where Japanese from rural King County south of Seattle are also going.
    Among those who registered yesterday were a number of Japanese who are married to men or women of other races.
    Orders are expected this week to evacuate all of the remaining Japanese in King County. They still remain in rural areas north and east of Seattle, and a smaller portion of Southern King County.</ab></div>
    
<div><ab>Camp Harmony Japs
Living Up to Name
Seattle Evacuees Making Best of                      
Site, Despite New Conditions
______________________
By R. B. Bermann 
Post-Intelligencer Staff Correspondent
  
    CAMP HARMONY, Puyallup, May 24—Although some of them have been here scarcely a week, Seattle Japanese are adjusting themselves rapidly to conditions at this assembly center, and the camp is really living up to its name.
    Life is very different from anything to which they had been accustomed, but they are making the best of things as they found them, and remarkably few complaints are heard.
    Maybe the secret lies in the fact that they have so little idle time on their hands. If they are not just before the travel of all Japanese was restricted. Her husband build a wardrobe, a linen closet, a vanity and bench and other bedroom furniture out of scrap lumber and she supplied the feminine touch with draperies that give the room a really homelike appearance.
    A completely democratic spirit prevails in the camp, because practically everyone is on the same economic status.
    This is because there is so little difference in scales of pay. A common laborer receives $8 a month,
____________________________________________________________________________

COMFORT OF HOME—Mrs. Robert Hosokawa, recent Willamette coed, laying out a new apron in the cozy apartment which she and her husband have contrived to make out of their bare barracks. Her husband constructed the furniture out of scrap lumber and his drive of two months achieved the rest with a few draperies.
____________________________________________________________________________

Busy on work details or administrative duties, there is always something to do around their temporary homes — because the army didn’t have time to indulge in any of the niceties of interior decoration in constructing their barracks. 
    And, as if that weren’t enough, many of them have put in tiny Victory Gardens. For instance, Clarence Arai, for years a prominent Seattle attorney, has put in radishes, beets, Chinese lettuce and onions — and his little plot is as meticulously neat as if he were a professional gardener. 
    They take pride in the amount of ingenuity they can show in making their primitive quarters look more like the homes they left behind them.
    An outstanding example in this respect is furnished by the apartment where Robert Hosokawa, formerly a furniture salesman in Seattle, is spending his honeymoon. His brider, the former Yoshi Yoshizawa, twenty, was a junior in Willamette University when the first evacuation orders were issued. She hurried to Seattle to be married [...] a skilled laborer $12 and a professional man or woman $16. This pay, of course, is in addition to their board and lodging and medical and dental attention. The dental clinic is one of the busiest centers in the camp, with as many as eighteen or twenty patients in a single morning — which isn’t excessive in view of the fact that the center has an estimated population of 7,500.
    Six former Seattle dentists are on duty there — Dr. S. Higashida and his son, Robert; Dr. H. Higashida and his son, Robert; Dr. H. Mitsumori, Dr. F. Kinemori, Dr. G. Y. Nomura and Dr. S. Ishihashi.
    A paper has been started, with Dick Takeuchi, former editor of the Great Northern Daily News, in charge. Takeuchi, who was a journalism senior at the University of Washington, has tentatively called the paper the Camp Harmony News Letter, but he isn’t satisfied and has asked his readers to suggest other names. 
    Dyke Miyagawa, another University of Washington senior, is his managing editor, and Taka Oka, a sophomore, is assistant managing editor. 
    Keith Oka, formerly employed at the Craftsmen’s Press, is art editor, and Tad Kuniyuki, formerly sports editor for the Japanese American Courier, has a similar job there. 
    James Y. Sakamoto, former publisher of the Japanese American Courier and now chief Japanese supervisor of the camp, has set up his headquarters underneath the grandstand on the fairgrounds and keeps busy from morning to night consulting with members of his staff. 
     Bill Hosokawa, University of Washington graduate and former editor of a newspaper in Singapore, is his chief adjutant. The headquarters staff is divided into five general sections, with George Ishihara, produce shipper, in charge of personnel; Jack Maki, associate in the Far Eastern department at the University of Washington, in charge of information; Dick Setsuda, beer distributor, in charge of operations; Thomas Iseri, Auburn produce shipper, in charge of supply, and Julius Fujihara, in charge of police, fire, postal and other services.
    Leaders of the four areas into which the center is divided are William Mimbu, attorney; Yakeo Nogaki and Teruji Umino, both bank clerks, and Hiroyuki (“Lefty”) Ichihara, who had a fishing tackle store in Seattle.
    All of these executives, incidentally, are American-born Japanese. 
    Life in the camp is by no means all work and no play. 
    Churches have supplied a piano for each of the four areas and there is plenty of community singing and choir practice.
    There are athletic facilities for all ages, and a number of soft ball and ping pong tournaments are already in progress. 
    There are recreational rooms in each area. 
    Jack Maki, the former University faculty member, summed up the attitude of the evacuees when he said: 
    “We aren’t being mistreated, but, on the other hand, we aren’t being pampered — I think everybody’s doing a swell job.”</ab></div>

<div><ab>June 2, 1942

Mr. Clarence T. Arai
Puyallup
Washington

Dear Mr. Arai:

The members of the Board of the Seattle Public Library wish to express to you our regret that you are unable to serve longer with them in the labor of sreving the citizens of Seattle in their library needs.

We do wish, however, to let you know how much we have enjoyed your disinterested advice - your will- ingness to serve faithfully and your just approach to all problems that have come before the Board.

Your viewpoint has always been wholesome, un- prejudiced and eminently fair and we shall all miss your congenial companionship at our Board meetings, as well as the presence of Mrs. Arai and yourself at the annual banquet of the Staff Association.

While we recognize that under present conditions many things arise that give much distress, we know that your sound philosophy and unfailing good humour will ever attend you.

Sincerely yours
SEATTLE PUBLIC LIBRARY BOARD
Josephine M. Quigley
President
Christine A. Neergaard
(signature)
(signature)</ab></div>

<div><ab>SEATTLE PUBLIC LIBRARY STAFF ASSOCIATION
4th AVE. and MADISON ST.
SEATTLE, WASHINGTON

25 May 1942

Mr Clarence T. Arai
(H/S)taff Headquarters, Camp Harmony
Section 2, no. 79
Puyallup, Washington

Dear Mr Arai:

Greetings from the Seventh Annual Banquet of the S(E/e)attle Public Library Staff Association to both you and Mrs Arai.

We were so sorry not to have you with us Friday night.  We tried to make it an especially nice affair since it was to be the last one before Mr Jennings retired.  As toastmistress, I read your letter and when the suggestion was made that greetings be sent to you, you should have heard the applause, so you can see what a place you hold in our minds and hearts.

The dining room at the Ranier Club looked very beautiful with the tables decorated with rhododendrons and iris and colorful programs, serving also as place cards. There were one hundred and forty-one present.

Between courses we sang the songs printed in the program and then we had a series of humorous book reviews supposedly suggestions for the book case in the new house Mr Jennings is building across Lake Washington.  After the last of these the group burst into the song “For He’s a Jolly Good Fellow.”  Then we said we had a real book for him and Miss Andrus presented him with the portfolio of letters, one of which you wrote, - there were over a hundred altogether, and was he pleased!

He made a little speech of appreciation and then it was Mrs. Quigley’s turn to add to the book-shelf.  She presented him with a book containing a diploma saying that he had completed thirty-five years of successful service “summa cum laude”, and then she presented Mr Richards, the new librarian, with a schedule book such as they give Freshmen at the University, listing the courses he’d have to take such as Handling the Board, Pleasing the Staff, Balancing the Budget, etc.  Mr Richards then said briefly how pleased he and Mrs Richards were to be included and how much he was looking forward to his work.

Last of all we said we thought the best books to have on our shelves were the master works that were standbys through thick and thin to guide and comfort us and then Miss Eberlin presented Mr Jennings with a Columbia Master Works Album of Beethoven’s “Tempest” Sonata, first speaking of records and how librarians have always”kept 

SEATTLE PUBLIC LIBRARY STAFF ASSOCIATION
4th AVE. and MADISON ST.
SEATTLE, WASHINGTON

-2-

records” religiously. But she said that after we had gotten this record it occurred to us he would need something to play it on it on and so there was a companion volume to this.  Covered with a cloth in the alcover back of the speakers table was an R.C.A. Radio-Victrola which Miss Eberlin then uncovered.  Mr Jennings was quite overcome.  “I can’t say anything” was all he could say, so we joined hands around the table and sang Auld Lang Syne, and that was the end.

We surely wished many times during the evening that you and Mrs Arai might be with us and I know I am expressing the feeling of the whole group when I say that you have our very best wishes and that we hope this trying period through which you are passing may seem more bearable as time goes on.  This morning’s P-I carries your picture and tells of your new work.  “You can’t keep a good man down”, you know. 

Sincerely your friend
Alice A. Frost
(E/A)AF/FRP                 President, Seattle Public Library
Staff Association

P.S. Miss Calkins, head of our Reference department, is coming with a friend to Puyallup tomorrow and will be at the gate of the Camp at 5:30 and will be very happy to see you if you can be there.</ab></div>
      </body>
      <back>
          <div type="bibliography">
              <listBibl>
                  <bibl xml:id="TODO" type="webpage">
                      "<title level="a">TODO</title>."
                      <title level="m">TODO</title>
                      <publisher>TODO</publisher>
                      <date>TODO</date>
                      <ref target="INSERT_LINK">INSERT_NAME_OF_LINK</ref>
                  </bibl>
              </listBibl>
          </div>
      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
