<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Selections from the Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
                <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
                <editor xml:id="MO">Marisa Oishi</editor>
                <editor xml:id="CL">Christine Leak</editor>
                <editor xml:id="HS">Hannah Swoffer</editor>
                <sponsor>University of Washington Libraries, Special Collections</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p>This edition focuses on a selection of pages from Clarence T. Arai’s scrapbook
                    held in the University of Washington Special Collections.</p>
                <p>We chose to work with a scrapbook because of the vulnerability conveyed through
                    its visual and textual features. This edition, only a small selection of pieces
                    from the full work, explores the choices Arai made in assembling his scrapbook,
                    considering how these preserved materials capture a personal experience during
                    World War II and contribute to a more holistic, human understanding of the
                    period.</p>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Washington Student Project for TXTDS 404/FREN 420: Texts,
                    Publics, and Publication</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2025-06-06">June 6th, 2025</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available for use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
                    <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
                    <pubPlace>University of Washington, Special Collections Manuscripts and
                        Archives</pubPlace>
                    <date from="1919" to="1993">1919-1993</date>
                    <idno type="oclcNo">945773039</idno>
                    <idno type="accessionNo">acc5542-001</idno>
                    <note>Box 2</note>
                    <note>This scrapbook, assembled by Clarence T. Arai, provides a perspective on
                        his life as a Japanese American in Seattle before and during World War II.
                        It includes correspondences, newspaper clippings, certificates, and other
                        artifacts Arai selected to preserve.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>We did not correct any errors as they did not detract from one's understanding of the
                text.</p>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="border" scheme="css"> border: 4px solid black; padding: 30px; </rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="date" scheme="css">font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align:
                    right; font-style: italic; font-size: 20px;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="title" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
                    35px; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="subTitle" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
                    35px; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="paper" scheme="css"> font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align:
                    right; font-style: italic; font-size: 20px;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="author" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
                    20px; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="description" scheme="css"> font-family: "Lucida Console Regular",
                    monospace; font-size: 20px; text-indent: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titleIndent" scheme="css">padding-left: 1em;</rendition>

            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="editorial_intro">
                <p>The phrase "on paper" is an interesting one. On paper, Clarence Takeya Arai was
                    an accomplished and influential member of the Seattle community. He was the
                    first Japanese American to earn a law degree from the University of Washington
                    and the first nisei commissioned officer in the US Army Reserve. He was a
                    founder and the first president of the Japanese American Citizens League, the
                    oldest Asian American civil rights organization, as well as a Republican
                    precinct committee member and delegate to the Washington State Republican
                    Convention. On paper, Arai and his family were sent to the Puyallup Fairgrounds,
                    and then to a concentration camp in Minidoka, Idaho, when over a hundred
                    thousand innocent Japanese Americans were incarcerated during World War II. His
                    health deteriorated there, but he continued to advocate for Japanese Americans'
                    legal rights within the camp. Three months after the war ended, his son Ken died
                    of a brain tumor. Arai gave up practicing law full time and took up photography.
                    He died less than twenty years later. </p>
                <p>When we discovered the Clarence T. Arai papers in the University of Washington
                    Special Collections, we didn't just discover certificates and newspaper
                    clippings taped to yellowing pages that crumbled as we turned them. This was a
                    life, a collection of moments of pride and tragedy, lived in service to his
                    community and yet persecuted by his country. This was an autobiography, a
                    telling of Arai's story through the papers he decided to preserve. He had a
                    Cocker Spaniel named Duke of Main Street. His son Ken liked "hot dog sandwiches"
                    and bus rides to Portland. On paper, Arai was a lawyer, civil rights advocate,
                    and photographer. But on paper, he was also a gardener, a father, a man with
                    dreams and indignation with the injustice he knew he was living: a human.</p>
                <p>Regrettably, we could not include every insightful artifact in Arai’s scrapbook.
                    We each chose a genre (personal correspondences, state issues, and newspaper
                    articles) and selected a few pages from that genre, maintaining original
                    spellings and punctuation to preserve authenticity. Our goal was to provide a
                    glimpse into the first-hand experiences of Japanese Americans in Washington
                    before and during World War II. Arai’s scrapbook offers a perspective unlike
                    textbooks or documentaries, providing insight on lived experiences through his
                    personal memorabilia and artifacts. By publishing this work, we hope that
                    readers will gain a more well-rounded, holistic perspective on this time period,
                    and an awareness of Arai’s life and enduring legacy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations"> </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="clippings">

                <div xml:id="emptyStallsClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                    <head rendition="#date"><date when="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date>MAY 1,
                        1942</head>
                    <head rendition="#title">EMPTY STALLS--EVACUATIONS</head>
                    <head rendition="#paper">SEATTLE TIMES</head>
                    <figure xml:id="emptyStallsImage">
                        <graphic url="../images/pikeplacenewTEIBP.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc>black and white vacant stalls at Pike Place Public Market</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p rendition="#description">Vacant stalls like these at <placeName
                            ref="#pike_place">Pike Place Public Markets</placeName>, Inc.,
                        confronted shoppers at numerous Seattle markets today. The Japanese
                        operators of many of the stalls have been evacuated. Japanese farmers who
                        formerly took their produce to the markets to sell it also were absent. Even
                        though they live outside the evacuation area, they are barred from the
                        central business district by wartime restrictions on movements of
                        Japanese.</p>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="halfOfCityClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                    <head rendition="#title">HALF OF CITY'S</head>
                    <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">JAPS HAVE GONE</head>
                    <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
                    <p rendition="#description">Seattle's central business district gave the
                        appearance of a city without Japanese today as the last of them from Zones
                        No. 1 and 2, or population, departed for the assembly center in
                        Puyallup.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description"> And the <placeName ref="#pike_place">Pike Place
                            Markets</placeName> for the first time in their years of operation, did
                        business without their myriad of Japanese-operated stalls. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"> It is estimated that only about half the Japanese
                        of the city have been removed but those who have gone were from areas in
                        which many were engaged in business and where they most often met public. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"> Those Japanese remaining in the city are restricted
                        to movement within the area in which they live. Beginning at noon, they and
                        all others of the Japanese race were banned from going to the central
                        business district, the waterfront or any place in the area to the north of
                        the city that lies west of Eastlake Avenue and Roosevelt Way, any place west
                        of Fifth Avenue in the central area, or any place south of Jackson Street in
                        the southern area, except for one small locality between Jackson and
                        Dearborn Streets. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">This ban prevents any Japanese in the farming
                        community surrounding the city from delivering produce to Seattle firms
                        personally, as Produce Row and the markets cannot be reached without passing
                        through a restricted area.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description"> The market master of the municipal market said that
                        not a single Japanese merchant appeared this morning, although the ban did
                        not go into effect until noon. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"> Operators of private markets said several Japanese
                        renters of stalls came early this morning with produce but brought Filipinos
                        with them to tend the stalls and left before noon. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">No date has been set for removal of the Japanese
                        from there</p>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="moreJapaneseGetOrdersClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                    <head rendition="#title">More Japanese Get</head>
                    <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">Evacuation Orders</head>
                    <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
                    <head rendition="#author #center">By R. B. Bermann</head>

                    <p rendition="#description">Evacuation of all Japanese from Kitsap County,
                        western Pierce County and the southwestern tip of King County was decreed
                        yesterday in orders by <name ref="#DeWitt">Lieut. Gen. John L. DeWitt</name>
                        commanding the Western Defense Command and Fourth Army.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">One order, No. 67, takes in Tacoma, Fort Lewis,
                        McChord Field, Steilacoom and that portion of King County west of Highway 99
                        and south of Des Moines. The 1,100 Japanese living in this area are to be
                        evacuated by noon Monday.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">OTHER AREAS</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">The other order, No. 68, takes in the Puget Sound
                        Navy Yard at Bremerton and all the rest of Kitsap County, except Bainbridge
                        Island which was evacuated earlier; Vashon Island in King County and the
                        island and Olympic Peninsula sections of Pierce County. The 200 Japanese
                        living in this area are to be evacuated by noon Saturday.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">The destination of the Japanese affected by these
                        orders was not announced, but the fact that they were advised they would not
                        be permitted to use private automobiles was constructed as an indication
                        that they will not be sent to the assembly center in Puyallup.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">It was considered probable that they would be sent
                        to the assembly center at Pinedale, Calif., to join evacuees from the rural
                        districts of King and Pierce counties who have already been moved there.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Prospective evacuees in the area covered by Order
                        No. 67 will register between 8 a.m. and 5 p. m. today and tomorrow at a
                        civil control station at 1715 S. Tacoma Ave., Tacoma.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">There will be two registration points, open during
                        the same hours on the same days, for the other area—one in the Bowers
                        Building on MainSt., Poulsbo, and the other</p>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="exclusionAreasClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                    <head rendition="#paper">SEATTLE POST-INTELLIGENCER, WEDNESDAY, MAY 18,
                        1942</head>
                    <head rendition="#title">NEW EXCLUSION AREAS</head>
                    <head rendition="#date">P.1 5/13/42</head>
                    <figure xml:id="firstExclusionAreaImage">
                        <graphic url="../images/firstExclusionAreaTEIPB.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc>Camp Harmony Bedroom</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p rendition="#description">PROHIBITED ZONE—Map of the area covered by Exclusion
                        Order No. 67, from which Japanese will be cleared by Monday. </p>
                    <figure xml:id="secondExclusionAreaImage">
                        <graphic url="../images/secondExclusionAreaTEIBP.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc>Camp Harmony Bedroom</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p rendition="#description"> UNDER BAN, TOO—The territory inside the heavy line
                        is covered by Exclusion Order No. 68, effective on Saturday.</p>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="registrationClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                    <head rendition="#date">TUESDAY</head>
                    <head rendition="#date"><date when="1942-05-12"/>P.1 5/12/42</head>
                    <head rendition="#title">REGISTRATION</head>
                    <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">OF REMAINING</head>
                    <head rendition="#title #titleIndent #titleIndent">JAPS STARTS</head>
                    <head rendition="#subTitle #center">All Left in Seattle to Get</head>
                    <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Assignments by Tonight;</head>
                    <head rendition="#subTitle #center">New County Orders Seen</head>
                    <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
                    <p rendition="#description">Registration of all Japanese remaining in Seattle
                        started yesterday and will continue today at the newest civil control
                        station, 2203 E. Madison St.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Like the registrations which preceded it, everything
                        was varied out in an orderly manner with a minimum of confusion. It is
                        expected that 1,098 Japanese remain in the last Seattle district to be
                        evacuated, and all will be registered and get their Puyallup center
                        assignments by 5 o’clock this evening.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">PUYALLUP, TOO</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">At the same time, registration was proceeding in
                        Puyallup of some 1,000 Japanese living in Eastern Pierce County. They are to
                        be sent to an evacuation center at Pinedale, Calif., where Japanese from
                        rural King County south of Seattle are also going.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Among those who registered yesterday were a number
                        of Japanese who are married to men or women of other races.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Orders are expected this week to evacuate all of the
                        remaining Japanese in King County. They still remain in rural areas north
                        and east of Seattle, and a smaller portion of Southern King County.</p>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="campHarmonyJapsClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
                    <head rendition="#title #center">Camp Harmony Japs</head>
                    <head rendition="#title #center">Living Up to Name</head>
                    <head rendition="#center">___________</head>
                    <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Seattle Evacuees Making Best of</head>
                    <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Site, Despite New Conditions</head>
                    <head rendition="#date">SEATTLE, <date when="1942-05-25">MAY 25,
                        1942</date></head>
                    <head rendition="#center">___________</head>
                    <head rendition="#author #center">By R. B. Bermann</head>
                    <head rendition="#author #center">Post-Intelligencer Staff Correspondent</head>

                    <p rendition="#description">CAMP HARMONY, Puyallup, May 24—Although some of them
                        have been here scarcely a week, Seattle Japanese are adjusting themselves
                        rapidly to conditions at this assembly center, and the camp is really living
                        up to its name.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Life is very different from anything to which they
                        had been accustomed, but they are making the best of things as they found
                        them, and remarkably few complaints are heard.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Maybe the secret lies in the fact that they have so
                        little idle time on their hands. If they are not just before the travel of
                        all Japanese was restricted. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Her husband build a wardrobe, a linen closet, a
                        vanity and bench and other bedroom furniture out of scrap lumber and she
                        supplied the feminine touch with draperies that give the room a really
                        homelike appearance.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">A completely democratic spirit prevails in the camp,
                        because practically everyone is on the same economic status.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">This is because there is so little difference in
                        scales of pay. A common laborer receives $8 a month,</p>
                    <p rendition="#description #center">__________________________________</p>
                    <figure xml:id="campHarmonyImage">
                        <graphic url="../images/campHarmonyBedroomTEIBP.jpg"/>
                        <figDesc>Camp Harmony Bedroom</figDesc>
                    </figure>

                    <p rendition="#description">COMFORT OF HOME—Mrs. Robert Hosokawa, recent
                        Willamette coed, laying out a new apron in the cozy apartment which she and
                        her husband have contrived to make out of their bare barracks. Her husband
                        constructed the furniture out of scrap lumber and his drive of two months
                        achieved the rest with a few draperies.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description #center">__________________________________</p>

                    <p rendition="#description">busy on work details or administrative duties, there
                        is always something to do around their temporary homes — because the army
                        didn’t have time to indulge in any of the niceties of interior decoration in
                        constructing their barracks. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">And, as if that weren’t enough, many of them have
                        put in tiny Victory Gardens. For instance, Clarence Arai, for years a
                        prominent Seattle attorney, has put in radishes, beets, Chinese lettuce and
                        onions — and his little plot is as meticulously neat as if he were a
                        professional gardener. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">They take pride in the amount of ingenuity they can
                        show in making their primitive quarters look more like the homes they left
                        behind them.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">An outstanding example in this respect is furnished
                        by the apartment where <name>Robert Hosokawa</name>, formerly a furniture
                        salesman in Seattle, is spending his honeymoon. His brider, the former
                            <name>Yoshi Yoshizawa</name>, twenty, was a junior in Willamette
                        University when the first evacuation orders were issued. She hurried to
                        Seattle to be married [...] a skilled laborer $12 and a professional man or
                        woman $16. This pay, of course, is in addition to their board and lodging
                        and medical and dental attention.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">The dental clinic is one of the busiest centers in
                        the camp, with as many as eighteen or twenty patients in a single morning —
                        which isn’t excessive in view of the fact that the center has an estimated
                        population of 7,500.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Six former Seattle dentists are on duty there —
                            <name>Dr. S. Higashida</name> and his son, Robert; <name>Dr. H.
                            Mitsumori</name>, <name>Dr. F. Kinemori</name>, <name>Dr. G. Y.
                            Nomura</name> and <name>Dr. S. Ishihashi</name>.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">A paper has been started, with <name>Dick
                            Takeuchi</name>, former editor of the Great Northern Daily News, in
                        charge. Takeuchi, who was a journalism senior at the University of
                        Washington, has tentatively called the paper the Camp Harmony News Letter,
                        but he isn’t satisfied and has asked his readers to suggest other names. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"><name>Dyke Miyagawa</name>, another University of
                        Washington senior, is his managing editor, and Taka Oka, a sophomore, is
                        assistant managing editor. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"><name>Keith Oka</name>, formerly employed at the
                        Craftsmen’s Press, is art editor, and <name>Tad Kuniyuki</name>, formerly
                        sports editor for the Japanese American Courier, has a similar job there. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"><name>James Y. Sakamoto</name>, former publisher of
                        the Japanese American Courier and now chief Japanese supervisor of the camp,
                        has set up his headquarters underneath the grandstand on the fairgrounds and
                        keeps busy from morning to night consulting with members of his staff. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"><name>Bill Hosokawa</name>, University of Washington
                        graduate and former editor of a newspaper in Singapore, is his chief
                        adjutant. The headquarters staff is divided into five general sections, with
                            <name>George Ishihara</name>, produce shipper, in charge of personnel;
                            <name>Jack Maki</name>, associate in the Far Eastern department at the
                        University of Washington, in charge of information; <name>Dick
                            Setsuda</name>, beer distributor, in charge of operations; <name>Thomas
                            Iseri</name>, Auburn produce shipper, in charge of supply, and
                            <name>Julius Fujihara</name>, in charge of police, fire, postal and
                        other services.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Leaders of the four areas into which the center is
                        divided are <name>William Mimbu</name>, attorney; <name>Yakeo Nogaki</name>
                        and <name>Teruji Umino</name>, both bank clerks, and <name>Hiroyuki
                            (“Lefty”) Ichihara</name>, who had a fishing tackle store in
                        Seattle.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">All of these executives, incidentally, are
                        American-born Japanese. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Life in the camp is by no means all work and no
                        play. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">Churches have supplied a piano for each of the four
                        areas and there is plenty of community singing and choir practice.</p>
                    <p rendition="#description">There are athletic facilities for all ages, and a
                        number of soft ball and ping pong tournaments are already in progress. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">There are recreational rooms in each area. </p>
                    <p rendition="#description"><name>Jack Maki</name>, the former University
                        faculty member, summed up the attitude of the evacuees when he said: </p>
                    <p rendition="#description">“We aren’t being mistreated, but, on the other hand,
                        we aren’t being pampered — I think everybody’s doing a swell job.</p>
                </div>

            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
