<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Selections from the Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
            <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
            <editor xml:id="MO">Marisa Oishi</editor>
            <editor xml:id="CL">Christine Leak</editor>
            <editor xml:id="HS">Hannah Swoffer</editor>
            <sponsor>University of Washington Libraries, Special Collections</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This edition focuses on a selection of pages from Clarence T. Arai’s scrapbook held
               in the University of Washington Special Collections.</p>
            <p>We chose to work with a scrapbook because of the vulnerability conveyed through its
               visual and textual features. This edition, only a small selection of pieces from the
               full work, explores the choices Arai made in assembling his scrapbook, considering
               how these preserved materials capture a personal experience during World War II and
               contribute to a more holistic, human understanding of the period.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Washington Student Project for TXTDS 404: Texts, Publics, and
               Publication</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
            <date when="2025-06-06">June 6th, 2025</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Freely available for use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
               <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
               <pubPlace>University of Washington, Special Collections Manuscripts and
                  Archives</pubPlace>
               <date from="1919" to="1993">1919-1993</date>
               <idno type="oclcNo">945773039</idno>
               <idno type="accessionNo">acc5542-001</idno>
               <note>Box 2</note>
               <note>This scrapbook, assembled by Clarence T. Arai, provides a perspective on his
                  life as a Japanese American in Seattle before and during World War II. It includes
                  correspondences, newspaper clippings, certificates, and other artifacts Arai
                  selected to preserve.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="border" scheme="css"> border: 4px solid black; padding: 30px; </rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="date" scheme="css">font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align: right;
               font-style: italic; font-size: 20px;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="title" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 35px;
               font-weight: bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="subTitle" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size:
               35px; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="paper" scheme="css"> font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align:
               right; font-style: italic; font-size: 20px;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="author" scheme="css">font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 20px;
               font-weight: bold;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="description" scheme="css"> font-family: "Lucida Console Regular",
               monospace; font-size: 20px; text-indent: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>

            <rendition xml:id="paragraphIndent" scheme="css">text-align: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titleIndent" scheme="css">padding-left: 1em; </rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>The phrase "on paper" is an interesting one. On paper, Clarence Takeya Arai was an
               accomplished and influential member of the Seattle community. He was the first
               Japanese American to earn a law degree from the University of Washington and the
               first nisei commissioned officer in the US Army Reserve. He was a founder and the
               first president of the Japanese American Citizens League, the oldest Asian American
               civil rights organization, as well as a Republican precinct committee member and
               delegate to the Washington State Republican Convention. On paper, Arai and his family
               were sent to the Puyallup Fairgrounds, and then to a concentration camp in Minidoka,
               Idaho, when over a hundred thousand innocent Japanese Americans were incarcerated
               during World War II. His health deteriorated there, but he continued to advocate for
               Japanese Americans' legal rights within the camp. Three months after the war ended,
               his son Ken died of a brain tumor. Arai gave up practicing law full time and took up
               photography. He died less than twenty years later. </p>
            <p>When we discovered the Clarence T. Arai papers in the University of Washington
               Special Collections, we didn't just discover certificates and newspaper clippings
               taped to yellowing pages that crumbled as we turned them. This was a life, a
               collection of moments of pride and tragedy, lived in service to his community and yet
               persecuted by his country. This was an autobiography, a telling of Arai's story
               through the papers he decided to preserve. He had a Cocker Spaniel named Duke of Main
               Street. His son Ken liked "hot dog sandwiches" and bus rides to Portland. On paper,
               Arai was a lawyer, civil rights advocate, and photographer. But on paper, he was also
               a gardener, a father, a man with dreams and indignation with the injustice he knew he
               was living: a human.</p>
            <p> Regrettably, we could not include every insightful artifact in Arai’s scrapbook. We
               each chose a genre (personal correspondences, state issues, and newspaper articles)
               and selected a few pages from that genre, maintaining original spellings and
               punctuation to preserve authenticity. Our goal was to provide a glimpse into the
               first-hand experiences of Japanese Americans in Washington before and during World
               War II. Arai’s scrapbook offers a perspective unlike textbooks or documentaries,
               providing insight on lived experiences through his personal memorabilia and
               artifacts. By publishing this work, we hope that readers will gain a more
               well-rounded, holistic perspective on this time period, and an awareness of Arai’s
               life and enduring legacy. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations"> </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="newspaperClippings">
            <div xml:id="emptyStallsClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
               <head rendition="#date">MAY 1, 1942</head>
               <head rendition="#title">EMPTY STALLS--EVACUATIONS</head>
               <head rendition="#paper">SEATTLE TIMES</head>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="../images/pikeplacenewTEIBP.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>black and white vacant stalls at Pike Place Public Market</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p rendition="#description">Vacant stalls like these at Pike Place Public Markets,
                  Inc., confronted shoppers at numerous Seattle markets today. The Japanese
                  operators of many of the stalls have been evacuated. Japanese farmers who formerly
                  took their produce to the markets to sell it also were absent. Even though they
                  live outside the evacuation area, they are barred from the central business
                  district by wartime restrictions on movements of Japanese.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="halfOfCityClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
               <head rendition="#title">HALF OF CITY'S</head>
               <head rendition="#title #titleIndent">JAPS HAVE GONE</head>
               <head rendition="#center">____________</head>
               <p rendition="#description">Seattle's central business district gave the appearance
                  of a city without Japanese today as the last of them from Zones No. 1 and 2, or
                  population, departed for the assembly center in Puyallup.</p>
               <p rendition="#description"> And the Pike Place Markets for the first time in their
                  years of operation, did business without their myriad of Japanese-operated stalls. </p>
               <p rendition="#description"> It is estimated that only about half the Japanese of the
                  city have been removed but those who have gone were from areas in which many were
                  engaged in business and where they most often met public. </p>
               <p rendition="#description"> Those Japanese remaining in the city are restricted to
                  movement within the area in which they live. Beginning at noon, they and all
                  others of the Japanese race were banned from going to the central business
                  district, the waterfront or any place in the area to the north of the city that
                  lies west of Eastlake Avenue and Roosevelt Way, any place west of Fifth Avenue in
                  the central area, or any place south of Jackson Street in the southern area,
                  except for one small locality between Jackson and Dearborn Streets. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">This ban prevents any Japanese in the farming community
                  sur- rounding the city from delivering produce to Seattle firms personally, as
                  Produce Row and the markets cannot be reached without passing through a restricted
                  area.</p>
               <p rendition="#description"> The market master of the municipal market said that not
                  a single Japanese merchant appeared this morning, although the ban did not go into
                  effect until noon. </p>
               <p rendition="#description"> Operators of private markets said several Japanese
                  renters of stalls came early this morning with produce but brought Filipinos with
                  them to tend the stalls and left before noon. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">No date has been set for removal of the Japanese from
                  there</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="campHarmonyJapsClipping" type="clipping" rendition="#border">
               <head rendition="#title #center">Camp Harmony Japs</head>
               <head rendition="#title #center">Living Up to Name</head>
               <head rendition="#center">___________</head>
               <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Seattle Evacuees Making Best of</head>
               <head rendition="#subTitle #center">Site, Despite New Conditions</head>
               <head rendition="#center">___________</head>
               <head rendition="#author">By R. B. Bermann</head>
               <head rendition="#author">Post-Intelligencer Staff Correspondent</head>

               <p rendition="#description">CAMP HARMONY, Puyallup, May 24—Although some of them have
                  been here scarcely a week, Seattle Japanese are adjusting themselves rapidly to
                  conditions at this assembly center, and the camp is really living up to its
                  name.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">Life is very different from anything to which they had
                  been accustomed, but they are making the best of things as they found them, and
                  remarkably few complaints are heard.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">Maybe the secret lies in the fact that they have so
                  little idle time on their hands. If they are not just before the travel of all
                  Japanese was restricted. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Her husband build a wardrobe, a linen closet, a vanity
                  and bench and other bedroom furniture out of scrap lumber and she supplied the
                  feminine touch with draperies that give the room a really homelike appearance.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">A completely democratic spirit prevails in the camp,
                  because practically everyone is on the same economic status.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">This is because there is so little difference in scales
                  of pay. A common laborer receives $8 a month,</p>
               <p rendition="#description"
                  >____________________________________________________________________________</p>
               <p>INSERT_IMAGE</p>

               <p rendition="#description">COMFORT OF HOME—Mrs. Robert Hosokawa, recent Willamette
                  coed, laying out a new apron in the cozy apartment which she and her husband have
                  contrived to make out of their bare barracks. Her husband constructed the
                  furniture out of scrap lumber and his drive of two months achieved the rest with a
                  few draperies.</p>
               <p rendition="description"
                  >____________________________________________________________________________</p>

               <p rendition="#description">busy on work details or administrative duties, there is
                  always something to do around their temporary homes — because the army didn’t have
                  time to indulge in any of the niceties of interior decoration in constructing
                  their barracks. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">And, as if that weren’t enough, many of them have put in
                  tiny Victory Gardens. For instance, Clarence Arai, for years a prominent Seattle
                  attorney, has put in radishes, beets, Chinese lettuce and onions — and his little
                  plot is as meticulously neat as if he were a professional gardener. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">They take pride in the amount of ingenuity they can show
                  in making their primitive quarters look more like the homes they left behind
                  them.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">An outstanding example in this respect is furnished by
                  the apartment where Robert Hosokawa, formerly a furniture salesman in Seattle, is
                  spending his honeymoon. His brider, the former Yoshi Yoshizawa, twenty, was a
                  junior in Willamette University when the first evacuation orders were issued. She
                  hurried to Seattle to be married [...] a skilled laborer $12 and a professional
                  man or woman $16. This pay, of course, is in addition to their board and lodging
                  and medical and dental attention.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">The dental clinic is one of the busiest centers in the
                  camp, with as many as eighteen or twenty patients in a single morning — which
                  isn’t excessive in view of the fact that the center has an estimated population of
                  7,500.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">Six former Seattle dentists are on duty there — Dr. S.
                  Higashida and his son, Robert; Dr. H. Higashida and his son, Robert; Dr. H.
                  Mitsumori, Dr. F. Kinemori, Dr. G. Y. Nomura and Dr. S. Ishihashi.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">A paper has been started, with Dick Takeuchi, former
                  editor of the Great Northern Daily News, in charge. Takeuchi, who was a journalism
                  senior at the University of Washington, has tentatively called the paper the Camp
                  Harmony News Letter, but he isn’t satisfied and has asked his readers to suggest
                  other names. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Dyke Miyagawa, another University of Washington senior,
                  is his managing editor, and Taka Oka, a sophomore, is assistant managing editor. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Keith Oka, formerly employed at the Craftsmen’s Press, is
                  art editor, and Tad Kuniyuki, formerly sports editor for the Japanese American
                  Courier, has a similar job there. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">James Y. Sakamoto, former publisher of the Japanese
                  American Courier and now chief Japanese supervisor of the camp, has set up his
                  headquarters underneath the grandstand on the fairgrounds and keeps busy from
                  morning to night consulting with members of his staff. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Bill Hosokawa, University of Washington graduate and
                  former editor of a newspaper in Singapore, is his chief adjutant. The headquarters
                  staff is divided into five general sections, with George Ishihara, produce
                  shipper, in charge of personnel; Jack Maki, associate in the Far Eastern
                  department at the University of Washington, in charge of information; Dick
                  Setsuda, beer distributor, in charge of operations; Thomas Iseri, Auburn produce
                  shipper, in charge of supply, and Julius Fujihara, in charge of police, fire,
                  postal and other services.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">Leaders of the four areas into which the center is
                  divided are William Mimbu, attorney; Yakeo Nogaki and Teruji Umino, both bank
                  clerks, and Hiroyuki (“Lefty”) Ichihara, who had a fishing tackle store in
                  Seattle.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">All of these executives, incidentally, are American-born
                  Japanese. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Life in the camp is by no means all work and no play. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Churches have supplied a piano for each of the four areas
                  and there is plenty of community singing and choir practice.</p>
               <p rendition="#description">There are athletic facilities for all ages, and a number
                  of soft ball and ping pong tournaments are already in progress. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">There are recreational rooms in each area. </p>
               <p rendition="#description">Jack Maki, the former University faculty member, summed
                  up the attitude of the evacuees when he said: </p>
               <p rendition="#description">“We aren’t being mistreated, but, on the other hand, we
                  aren’t being pampered — I think everybody’s doing a swell job.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
