<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Selections from the Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
            <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
            <editor xml:id="MO">Marisa Oishi</editor>
            <editor xml:id="CL">Christine Leak</editor>
            <editor xml:id="HS">Hannah Swoffer</editor>
            <sponsor>University of Washington Libraries, Special Collections</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This edition focuses on a selection of pages from Clarence T. Arai’s scrapbook held
               in the University of Washington Special Collections.</p>
            <p>We chose to work with a scrapbook because of the vulnerability conveyed through its
               visual and textual features. This edition, only a small selection of pieces from the
               full work, explores the choices Arai made in assembling his scrapbook, considering
               how these preserved materials capture a personal experience during World War II and
               contribute to a more holistic, human understanding of the period.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Washington Student Project for TXTDS 404: Texts, Publics, and
               Publication</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
            <date when="2025-06-06">June 6th, 2025</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Freely available for use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Clarence T. Arai Papers</title>
               <author>Clarence T. Arai</author>
               <pubPlace>University of Washington, Special Collections Manuscripts and
                  Archives</pubPlace>
               <date from="1919" to="1993">1919-1993</date>
               <idno type="oclcNo">945773039</idno>
               <idno type="accessionNo">acc5542-001</idno>
               <note>Box 2</note>
               <note>This scrapbook, assembled by Clarence T. Arai, provides a perspective on his
                  life as a Japanese American in Seattle before and during World War II. It includes
                  correspondences, newspaper clippings, certificates, and other artifacts Arai
                  selected to preserve.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="rend-date" scheme="css">font-family: Papyrus, fantasy; text-align:
               right; font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="paragraphIndent" scheme="css">text-align: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titleIndent" scheme="css">padding-left: 1em; font-weight:
               bold</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="clippingBox" scheme="css">border: 2px solid black; width: 260px;
               padding: 10px; font-family: Geogria, "Times New Roman", serif; font-size: 12px;
               line-height: 12px; line-height: 1.2; margin: auto</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>The phrase "on paper" is an interesting one. On paper, Clarence Takeya Arai was an
               accomplished and influential member of the Seattle community. He was the first
               Japanese American to earn a law degree from the University of Washington and the
               first nisei commissioned officer in the US Army Reserve. He was a founder and the
               first president of the Japanese American Citizens League, the oldest Asian American
               civil rights organization, as well as a Republican precinct committee member and
               delegate to the Washington State Republican Convention. On paper, Arai and his family
               were sent to the Puyallup Fairgrounds, and then to a concentration camp in Minidoka,
               Idaho, when over a hundred thousand innocent Japanese Americans were incarcerated
               during World War II. His health deteriorated there, but he continued to advocate for
               Japanese Americans' legal rights within the camp. Three months after the war ended,
               his son Ken died of a brain tumor. Arai gave up practicing law full time and took up
               photography. He died less than twenty years later. </p>
            <p>When we discovered the Clarence T. Arai papers in the University of Washington
               Special Collections, we didn't just discover certificates and newspaper clippings
               taped to yellowing pages that crumbled as we turned them. This was a life, a
               collection of moments of pride and tragedy, lived in service to his community and yet
               persecuted by his country. This was an autobiography, a telling of Arai's story
               through the papers he decided to preserve. He had a Cocker Spaniel named Duke of Main
               Street. His son Ken liked "hot dog sandwiches" and bus rides to Portland. On paper,
               Arai was a lawyer, civil rights advocate, and photographer. But on paper, he was also
               a gardener, a father, a man with dreams and indignation with the injustice he knew he
               was living: a human.</p>
            <p> Regrettably, we could not include every insightful artifact in Arai’s scrapbook. We
               each chose a genre (personal correspondences, state issues, and newspaper articles)
               and selected a few pages from that genre, maintaining original spellings and
               punctuation to preserve authenticity. Our goal was to provide a glimpse into the
               first-hand experiences of Japanese Americans in Washington before and during World
               War II. Arai’s scrapbook offers a perspective unlike textbooks or documentaries,
               providing insight on lived experiences through his personal memorabilia and
               artifacts. By publishing this work, we hope that readers will gain a more
               well-rounded, holistic perspective on this time period, and an awareness of Arai’s
               life and enduring legacy. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations"> </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="halfOfCityClipping" type="clippingPage" rendition="halfOfCityClipping">
            <div type="clippingArticle">
               <head rendition="halfCityTitle lineSpacing">HALF OF CITY'S</head>
               <head rendition="halfCityTitle lineSpacing titleIndent">JAPS HAVE GONE</head>
               <head rendition="center lineSpacing">____________</head>
               <p rendition="description">Seattle's central business district gave the appearance
                  of a city without Japanese today as the last of them from Zones No. 1 and 2, or
                  population, departed for the assembly center in Puyallup.</p>
               <p rendition="description"> And the Pike Place Markets for the first time in their
                  years of operation, did business without their myriad of Japanese-operated stalls. </p>
               <p rendition="description"> It is estimated that only about half the Japanese of the
                  city have been removed but those who have gone were from areas in which many were
                  engaged in business and where they most often met public. </p>
               <p rendition="description"> Those Japanese remaining in the city are restricted to
                  movement within the area in which they live. Beginning at noon, they and all
                  others of the Japanese race were banned from going to the central business
                  district, the waterfront or any place in the area to the north of the city that
                  lies west of Eastlake Avenue and Roosevelt Way, any place west of Fifth Avenue in
                  the central area, or any place south of Jackson Street in the southern area,
                  except for one small locality between Jackson and Dearborn Streets. </p>
               <p rendition="description">This ban prevents any Japanese in the farming community
                  sur- rounding the city from delivering produce to Seattle firms personally, as
                  Produce Row and the markets cannot be reached without passing through a restricted
                  area.</p>
               <p rendition="description"> The market master of the municipal market said that not
                  a single Japanese merchant appeared this morning, although the ban did not go into
                  effect until noon. </p>
               <p rendition="description"> Operators of private markets said several Japanese
                  renters of stalls came early this morning with produce but brought Filipinos with
                  them to tend the stalls and left before noon. </p>
               <p rendition="description">No date has been set for removal of the Japanese from
                  there</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
