<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Various Ways of Cooking Appless</title>
            <author>Georgiana Hill</author>
            <editor>Ainsley Lin, Isabelle Bowman</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Our goal for our text edition is that it will be an edition incredibly similar to the
               original visually and textually. By keeping almost all of the text the same as the
               original, we are hoping to preserve recipes from this 1869 cookbook, in hopes that
               readers will reflect on the way recipes can mirror the time they were written in</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>"How To Cook Potatoes, Apples, Eggs, Fish, Four Hundred Different Ways" is a cookbook
               by Georgiana Hill, a 19th century cookery book writer and journalist. This cookbook
               is not only a collection of recipes, but a reflection of Georgiana Hill’s character.
               Her often humorous section introductions, the almost casual nature of the recipes,
               and the deviation of the cookbook from just British recipes paints Georgiana Hill as
               a well-traveled and educated woman with the intention of reaching other women with
               her cooking knowledge.</p>
            <p><bibl>
                  <title>How to Cook Potatoes, Apples, Eggs, Fish, Four Hundred Different
                     Ways</title>
                  <author>Georgiana Hill</author>
                  <publisher>Dick &amp; Fitzgerald Publishers</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date>1869</date>
            </bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction>
               <p>The main corrections we chose to make were spelling errors, such as editing
                  “powered sugar” to “powdered sugar”, but not correcting for historical differences
                  in spelling.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <!-- title page, preface -->
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chaptertitle">
            <head rend = "caps">Various Ways of Cooking Apples</head>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="115">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">115. Pommes Au Naturel.</head>
            <p>The Evil One, who first offered apples to our universal mother, exemplified his
               serpent-like sapience by tempting her to try them off the tree: this, notwithstanding
               the enthusiasm we entertain for the culinary art, is unquestionably the ne plus ultra
               of epicurism in apple-eating. </p>
            <p>The learned tell us that apples, by keeping, become mellow; that time turns their
               natural acids into sugar; but there is a season for the perfection of apples, as for
               every other fruit; and when the period of their ripeness is past, a slow process of
               decay takes place - their rinds become cork, and their pulp becomes sponge. Oh! let
               me not eat of these tough, shrivelled, high-temperatured apples!- but let me taste
               them when all their summer lusciousness is fresh upon them; when their sparkling
               juice almost appears to effervesce as it comes in contact with the surrounding air;
               when, in short, they have attained maturity, and are, properly speaking, "in season."
               There are different kinds of apples ripe and in their prime from August to November,
               when in the estimation of gourmets, they are considered to be the most correct fruit
               for taking with wine; their agreeable, but not strongly pronounced, acid augmenting
               the sensitiveness of the palate to the flavors which peculiarly characterize the
               several varieties of wine. I must observe that inelegantly large apples are
               frequently introduced upon the dessert table; small or medium-sized fruit have a much
               more dainty appearance, and are invariably to be preferred, either for their greater
               sweetness, or on account of the coquettish grace with which a tasty table-dresser can
               arrange them, peeping from among green leaves, or nestling in tufts of moss.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="116">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">116. Pudding À La Zouave.</head>
            <p>Blanch half a pound of sweet almonds, pound them in a mortar, adding gradually half a
               pound of butter, four eggs well-beaten, half a pint of cream, half a pound of sugar
               and a glasss of raisin or Madeira wine. When this forms is a smooth paste, stir in a
               pound of pulped apples, which should have been previously boiled and allowed to grow
               cold. All the ingredients being properly mingled, put them into a well-buttered
               mould, and either boil or bake it for half an hour. In Marseilles, where we partook
               of this elegant compound, it was served with a sauce prepared with sugar and rum, in
               which a clove or two of garlic had been steeped. National prejudices did not prevent
               our pronouncing it delicious.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="117">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">117. Apple Ginger.</head>
            <p>Take three pounds of Spitzenbergen apples, cut them into small pieces, put them into
               a dish, and pour boiling water upon them, then cover them up; clarify weight for
               weight of white sugar, and boil it to almost a candy height, throw in the apples,
               draining them from the water, and, without boiling, put them aside for half an hour,
               keeping them closely covered; then pour in a bottle and a half of Brown's tincture of
               ginger; boil it all unitl clear and of a proper consistency. When sufficiently cool,
               put it into bottles or jars. This economical preparation is very little inferior to
               foreign preserved ginger; it keeps well, and is exceedingly beneficial as a
               restorative for weak nerves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="118">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">118. Pommes À La Vésuve.</head>
            <p>Pile some apple marmalade high in a dish; get ready some macaroni boiled in water,
               but well drained, and afterwards sweetened with white sugar, and flavored with
               brandy; cut it into short lengths, but do not mince it; lay it as a bordering round
               the mountain of marmalade, plentifully dust the whole over with powdered white sugar,
               and on the apex form a crater with about half a dozen good-sized nubs of sugar; pour
               a good gill of brandy over the top, and immediately before serving set fire to it,
               and introduce it at table flaming.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="119">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">119. Apple Bread.</head>
            <p>Weigh seven pounds of fresh juicy apples, peel, core, and boil them to a pulp, being
               careful to use an enamelled saucepan, or a stone jar placed inside an ordinary
               saucepan of boiling water, otherwise the fruit becomes discolored; mix the pulp with
               fourteen pounds of the best flour, put in the same quantity of yeast you would use in
               common bread, and as much water as will make it into a fine smooth dough; put it into
               a pan, and stand it in a warm place to rise; let it remain for twelve hours at least;
               form it into rather longshaped loaves, and bake it in a lively oven. This bread is
               very much eaten in the south of Europe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="120">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">120. Pommes Farcies.</head>
            <p>Take some large apples, pare them, and from the stalk end cut out a good deal of the
               insides without cutting the fruit through; fill the orifice of each apple with a
               mincemeat of cold roast goose, duck, or even pork, well seasoned with the best white
               pepper and a little sage; put the stuffed apples into a baking dish, with a bit of
               butter under each, and bake for half an hour in a gay oven, basting them as they
               require it. Grate a little toasted bread over them before serving.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="121">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">121. Pippin Tarts.</head>
            <p>Take three large oranges, peel them very thin, boil the peel until it becomes soft,
               then take it up and chop it small; pare and core four dozen golden pippins, boil them
               with only enough water to cover them; when nearly done, add a pound and a half of
               brown sugar, the shred orange peel, and the juice of the oranges; boil it all
               together until smooth, and let it get cold; line your patty-pans with thin paste, and
               fill up each with the fruit. These tarts can be eaten warm or cold.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="122">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">122. Gâteau De Pommes.</head>
            <p>Peel about two pounds of apples, bake or steam them until they are perfectly soft;
               add two pounds of white sugar in powder, with the juice and rinds of two lemons, and
               if requisite, a little water. Boil all this together for forty minutes, pour it into
               a mould; when cold, turn it out, cover it with a thick custard, and serve.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="123">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">123. Pommes Sautées.</head>
            <p>Peel some very small and prettily-shaped apples, but do not take off their stalks;
               put them into a stew-pan of boiling butter, and shake them over a brisk fire until
               they are of a nice brown color; drain them, and arrange them neatly, with their
               stalks upwards, upon a thick layer of white sugar in a dish. Serve them either warm
               or cold.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="124">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">124. Simple Apple Pie.</head>
            <p>Pare, core, and cut up the fruit into thin slices, lay it in your dish, and sprinkle
               some sugar amongst it; when full, put in the juice of two lemons, with a little of
               the rind finely shred, and some cloves or cinnamon in powder; line the dish and cover
               it with a good crust, and bake it for about an hour. Before serving, sift a little
               sugar over it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="125">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">125. Beignets De Pommes.</head>
            <p>Take some Greening apples, scoop out the cores with a vide-pomme, and cut the apples
               into thin slice; put them into some brandy, with the grated rind of a lemon, and
               place them over the fire for a few moments. Take out the slices of apple when they
               are pretty warm, and dip them into batter; then fry them in boiling lard. Free them
               as much as possible from all fat, and serve them thickly powedered over with sifted
               white sugar. Send them to table as warm as possible.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="126">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">126. Pommes En Compote.</head>
            <p>Parboil some apples, then peel, core, and cut them into quarters, put them into a
               preserving pan with an equal weight of white sugar, adding a litte water; let it
               simmer slowly, and keep skimming it until the apples are quite done, then allow them
               to grow cold; arrange them in a jar; again boil the syrup until it is greatly reduced
               in quantity, and pour it boiling hot over the apples. When cold cover them up
               closely.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="127">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">127. Croutes De Pommes.</head>
            <p>Cut some thin slices of bread into lozenge-shaped pieces, butter them on both sides,
               and lay them to fit in a well-buttered baking dish. Cut some middling-sized pippins
               into halves, hollow out the cores, and upon each piece of bread place half an apple,
               with the inside of the apple upwards. Put into each orifice a spoonful of good thick
               cream, and strew some pounded loaf sugar over the bread and fruit. Place it in a slow
               oven, and renew the cream and sugar as they dissolve. When done, arrange the lozenges
               of bread, with the apples upon them, in a clean dish, pouring over them any juice
               that may remain unabsorbed by the crusts. Serve them warm.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="128">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">128. Apple Fritters.</head>
            <p>Make a thick batter with six well-beaten eggs, a pint of milk, a little powdered
               nutmeg, a glass of brandy, and fine flour enough to make it of the requisite
               consistency. Slice some good dressing apples into rounds, and dip each piece into the
               batter; then fry, in very hot lard, over a quick fire. The lard should smoke before
               the fritters are put in, otherwise they will not be of a good color.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="129">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">129. Gélatine De Pommes.</head>
            <p>In a pint of water boil one pound and a half of white sugar until it is reduced to a
               very thick syrup; then add two pounds of Newtown pippins, pared, cored, and cut into
               slices; squeeze in the juice of three lemons, and simmer gently until it is almost a
               paste; then pour it into a mould and, when cold, it will turn out a solid jelly.
               Serve it surrounded with scaled cream in a deep dish. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="130">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">130. Apples With Pork Chops.</head>
            <p>Sour apples sliced and fried in pork steak gravy are delicious. They should be served
               with the chops.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="131">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">131. Boiled Apple Pudding.</head>
            <p>Line your pudding-basin with a good crust made in the proportion of eight ounces of
               beef suet to twelve ounces of flour; add a little salt; pare, core, and cut up your
               apples, and when filling your pudding, strew in some brown sugar and a little
               powdered cloves; cover it with a good thick top crust; tie it up, and boil for two
               hours.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="132">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">132. Pommes Soufflées.</head>
            <p>Take your apples, pare, core, and boil them until soft enough to pulp through a
               colander; then sweeten them to taste, and stir in a little powdered cinnamon; put the
               fruit into a deep dish, and when quite cold, pour rich custard over it. Whip up the
               whites of the eggs remaining from the custard, and when they form a stiff snow, lay
               it daintily in small pieces upon the surface of the custard; sift some
               finely-powdered loaf sugar over it, and put into a moderate oven for a quarter of an
               hour or twenty minutes. This is equally good hot or cold.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="133">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">133. Stewed Golden Pippins.</head>
            <p>Scoop out the cores, and, as you pare them, throw them into cold water to prevent
               their turning color. For every pound of apples weigh a pound and a-half of white
               sugar, boil it in a pint of cider until it becomes a strong syrup; skim it perfectly,
               and put in the apples; stew them very slowly, otherwise they will break; when clear
               they are done. Serve them in syrup.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="134">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">134. Preserved Apples.</head>
            <p>Cut up a quantity of lemon pippins, take the parings and the cores and boil them, by
               themselves, for an hour; strain the water from them and add it to the sliced fruit,
               put it into an enamelled saucepan upon a slow fire, and let it simmer until the
               apples are done, then weigh a pound and a-half of sugar to each quart of fruit. Let
               it boil gently for an hour and a-half, paying attention that it does not burn. This
               is a very convenient preserve for keeping to use with damson or any other jams, which
               are generally too scarce to be employed freely in the winter season.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="135">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">135. Scalded Codlins></head>
            <p>Take some small codlins, wrap each in a vine leaf, and pack them closely in a
               stewpan; pour in as much cold water as will barely cover them, put them on the fire
               and let them simmer very slowly until sufficiently tender to take their skins off
               when cold enough to do do so. Well powder them over with sifted white sugar, and
               serve upon cream or with custards in glasses.</p>
            <!-- "do do", should it be edited? -->
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="136">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">136. Boiled Apple Dumplings.</head>
            <p>Take some medium-sized apples, not too large, or they will not be nicely done; peel,
               but do not core them, as the pips enhance the flavor of the fruit; wrap each in a
               good beef-suet paste, made as for apple pudding (<emph>see</emph> No. 131), put them
               into boiling water, and let them boil gently for an hour. Serve them as hot as
               possible, and always with the following sauce.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="137">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">137. Ginger Sauce.</head>
            <p>Take half a pint of new milk, in which dissolve two ounces of fresh butter, and
               gradually dredge in enough flour to make it thick; then stir in two tablespoonfuls of
               white sugar, and two dessertspoonfuls of the best ginger in powder; stir it over the
               fire until it boils. This forms a most relishing sauce for apple dumplings, apple
               puddings, &amp;e., &amp;e.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="138">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">138. Apple Fool.</head>
            <p>Pare your fruit, and either scald or bake it until sufficiently soft to pulp it
               through a colander; sweeten it agreeably to taste, and fill your glasses three parts
               full with it; then plentifully sprinkle in some cinnamon and cloves in powder, put a
               good layer of rich scalded cream, and sift white sugar upon the top.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="139">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">139. Chartreuse De Pommes.</head>
            <p>Well boil half a pound of the best Carolina rice in a quart of fresh milk, taking the
               greatest pains to prevent it from catching at the bottom of the saucepan. Pare seven
               large or nine middle-sized pippins; take out the cores, without cutting the fruit
               quite through; put a little raspberry jam into each hole, and fill up with cream.
               Edge a deep pie-dish with a rich light paste; lay in the apples, and level up the
               spaces between them with the boiled rice. Brush it over with the yolk of an egg, dust
               it well with pounded loaf sugar, decorate it with a few pieces of candied lemon or
               orange peel, and bake it for about forty minutes in a brisk oven. This dish is better
               eaten hot.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="140">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">140. Apple Puffs.</head>
            <p>Pare, and bake the fruit; when cold, mix the pulp, free from the cores, with a
               sufficiency of either white or brown sugar, and a little grated lemon peel, or a few
               spoonfuls of orange-flower water; lay the apples in thin paste, fold it over them,
               and bake them in a lively oven for about twenty minutes. Sift sugar over them before
               sending them to table.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="141">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">141. Apple Trifle.</head>
            <p>Scald as much fruit as you require, pulp it smoothly, add sufficient sugar to sweeten
               it, and the grated rinds of two lemons; lay this thickly at the bottom of your dish.
               Mix a pint of cream, a pint of new milk, and the yolks of three eggs well beaten; put
               it over the fire, stirring it until it is just upon the boil; sweeten it with sugar,
               and let it grow cold; then put it over the paples with a spoon, and afterwards lay
               upon the whole a fine whip of cream made some hours previously.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="142">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">142. Apple Tart.</head>
            <p>Pare some good dressing apples, winter russetings are the best, cut them into long
               slices, scald them until quite soft, but use very little water; when tender enough,
               mash them smoothly with the liquor; add two ounces of fresh butter, a gill of cream,
               the grated rind of a lemon, and some white sugar; mix all well together, squeeze over
               it the juice of the lemon; put a very light paste round the dish, and a few
               ornamental bars across. Half an hour in a brisk oven will do this tart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="143">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">143. Confiture De Pommes.</head>
            <p>To each pound of boiling clarified sugar throw in the same weight of Newtown pippins
               cut into very thin slices, and the juice and finely-shred, rind of three oranges. Let
               it boil for twenty minutes, skimming it carefully; then retire it from the fire, and
               when sufficiently cold, put it into your preserving pots. The next day strew a little
               white sugar over each, cover them with brandied or oiled papers, and tie them
               down.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="144">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">144. Apple Sauce To Keep For Winter Use.</head>
            <p>Two pails of apples pared, cored, and quartered, put them over the fire with two
               quarts of molasses and sufficient water to cover them. Let them stew gently four or
               five hours, or until reduced to one-half. When they have boiled two hours, add one
               pint of the best corn whiskey. When done add cinnamon, or any spice to taste. Put in
               a stone jar and keep closely covered.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="145">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">145. Pommes Au Riz.</head>
            <p>Take some middle-sized or rather small apples; pare them, prick them well with a
               coarse needle, stew some sugar over, and bake them in a slack oven. While they are
               doing, boil half a pound of rice in a sufficiency of water, shaking it frequently.
               When nearly done, stir in three ounces of fresh butter, four ounces of white sugar,
               and a little powdered cinnamon. Have ready a strong infusion of saffron, which strain
               into the rice. Take it up, and arrange the apples upon the rice in a deep dish;
               garnish it with citron chips, and, if not quite warm enough to serve, put it into the
               oven for a few moments. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="146">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">146. Apple Syrup.</head>
            <p>Peel, but do not core, some spitzenbergen apples; cut them into very thin slices, and
               to each pound of fruit add a pound of white sugar and a teacupful of boiling water;
               put this into an earthen jar, which stands inside a saucepan of water. Let it remain
               boiling for two hours and a-half, occasionally shaking, but on no account stirring
               with a spoon or other utensil. When it is cold, pour off the clear syrup as gently as
               possible from the pulp, and put it into bottles for keeping.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="147">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">147. Baked Apple Pudding.</head>
            <p>Into a well-buttered pudding basin put a layer of bread crumbs, then a layer of
               apples cut up small, a sprinkling of grocer's currants, and some brown sugar; repeat
               this process of bread crumbs and fruit until the basin is full, then carefully pour
               in some melted butter; finish with a coating of bread crumbs on the top, and bake it
               for an hour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="148">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">148. Apple Omelette.</head>
            <p>Peel the apples and take out their cores, cut them into very thin slices, which dip
               into brandy, and dust over with finely-grated lemon peel; throw them into a
               frying-pan of boiling lard, shake them for a few minutes over a lively fire, and take
               them up. Beat some eggs, sweetened to taste, stir in the fruit, and fry with a very
               clear fire. When done, double up the omelette, dust it with sifted white sugar, and,
               if possible, glaze it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="149">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">149. Norfolk Biffins.</head>
            <p>Take some apples, put them into a very slack oven, between clean straw; as they
               become soft, flatten them occasionally with the hand. When done and cold, rub them
               over with syrup.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="150">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">150. Pommes Au Beurre.</head>
            <p>Peel the apples, and carefully remove the cores with a vide-pomme; well butter a deep
               dish, and cover it with squares of bread cut tolerably thin. Lay an apple upon each,
               and fill their orifices with a mixture of sugar and butter. Put them into a gentle
               oven, and replenish occasionally the butter and sugar. Twenty minutes will do them.
               Serve hot upon a clean dish.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="151">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">151. Apple Tart.</head>
            <p>Scald the fruit in a very small quantity of water; take off the skins, and arrange
               them whole in a tart dish, with a little of the liquor in which they were boiled.
               Strew over them a sufficiency of pounded white sugar, and when they are quite cold,
               border the dish with a rich tart paste, and cover them with the same. Take pains it
               does not burn; with half an hour's brisk baking it will be done.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="152">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">152. Salade De Pommes.</head>
            <p>Cut some ripe rich-flavored apples into round slices, arrange them in a small dish,
               cover them thickly with sifted loaf sugar, and pour a little of the best French
               brandy into the dish. This is very acceptable upon the dessert-table in the
               winter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="recipe" n="153">
            <head rend = "smallcaps">153. Miroton De Pommes</head>
            <p>Scald six large apples, and, when soft enough to do so, pulp them, and, after
               sweetening a little, plie them upon the dish you purpose serving them in. Take a
               teacupful of the liquor in which they were dressed, and boil the finely-shred rind of
               a lemon and three ounces of white sugar; then best well the yolks of three eggs and
               the white of one, add a dessertspoonful of fine flour, the same of brandy, and two
               ounces of fresh butter. Mingle these ingredients well together in a saucepan over a
               moderate fire; when perfectly smooth, take them off, and pour over the apples; then
               whisk the whites of the two eggs into a stiff froth, put it upon the miroton, sifting
               a little sugar over it. Place it for ten minutes in a slow oven, and serve hot or
               cold.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
