<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles</title>
            <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
            <editor>Em Backstrom</editor>
            <editor>Blue Jordan</editor>
            <editor>Rowan Herron</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>We plan to publish this edition of The Hound of the Baskervilles in June 2025.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <series>
                  <title>The Strand Magazine</title>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
               </series>
               <author>Arthur Conan Doyle</author>
               <title>The Hound of the Baskervilles></title>
               <publisher>George Newnes LTD.</publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>George Newnes LTD.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>7, 8, 9, 10, 11, &amp; 12, Southampton Street,</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>and Exeter Street, London</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </pubPlace>
               <date when="1901-08">August 1901</date>
               <availability>
                  <p>Held by UW Special Collections under the call number 051 SM v.22.</p>
               </availability>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This edition was created as part of TXTDS 404 at the University of Washington over
               the course of Spring Quarter 2025. Our first goal with this digital edition is to
               reproduce the copytext as close to the original as possible, including text itself as
               well as form, format, and illustrations, using the tools of digital editing such as
               XML, TEI, HTML, and CSS. Our second goal is to include interesting contextual
               information to the story to enrich and contextualize a reader's experience by
               connecting readers with Doyle’s history with The Strand and also to the geographic
               elements in the story and its mediation. We are also interested in how historic
               audiences received and reacted to the story. Our edition, including our HTML and CSS
               formatting of the TEI encoding, was published online using the Vergil web publishing
               system.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Our aim with editiorial decisions is to avoid altering the text and its presentation
               minimally. Original spelling, format, and punctuation is recreated wherever we can.
               We will normalize certain punctuation that resembles em dashes and dashes but are
               neither.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2025-05-11">Began creating draft TEI Header</change>
            <change when="2025-05-12">Finish draft TEI Header</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front xml:lang="en">
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <head>Editorial Intro</head>
            <p>Sherlock Holmes is such a widely known character it’s difficult to find a way to
               introduce him. He retains global popularity even after almost one hundred years since
               his last published adventure by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle. There are fifty-six short
               stories and four novels that comprise the sixty canon Sherlock stories, with The
               Hound of the Baskervilles being the third serialized novel. This text is significant
               not only because of its remarkable literary merit as a standout entry in the Sherlock
               Holmes canon, but also because it was the first text published after The Final
               Problem, where Sherlock had died. Sherlock’s death had sparked grief and outrage,
               including people unsubscribing from The Strand magazine. His return was welcomed and
               widely read and remains a must-read for people seeking the best of Sir Arthur Conan
               Doyle’s work.</p>
            <p>Our edition aims to produce a digital version of the original text and formatting of
               “The Hound of Baskervilles” that will connect modern readers to the original
               publication. Modern readers most often access the Sherlock Holmes stories through
               adaptations and remediations that, for example, collect the different serialized
               chapters into one unit. With our edition, readers can think about how the original
               way the story was published in the Strand magazine might have affected readers’
               experience, the significance of place to the story and to its publication, and
               experience a digital recreation of the original formatting and feel of the story.</p>
            <p>Our editorial decisions coalesce around the approach of attempting to create as close
               of a type facsimile as possible, in line with the aim of our editorial work. In this
               spirit we will maintain spelling and punctuation as they appear in the text. We will
               also maintain the layout of the text, including columns, pages, where images are
               placed, and where words are split between lines. One area where we might have to
               diverge from a type facsimile’s recreation of our source is with the column
               dimensions, depending on whether we can measure them in our source. This approach
               aligns with our project goals by providing our readers with insight into the
               serialized magazine publication format we are closely recreating. </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body xml:lang="en">
         <pb n="122"/>
         <figure place="center">
            <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage122.png"/>
            <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps"
               ><!-- in places where we need to have two rendition attribtes, can we we do rendition and rend?-->
               The Hound of the Baskerville</p>
            <p rend="italics">(See page 128.)</p>
            <figDesc> In the full page illustration, a man on horseback speed across a field while a
               hound pursues closely behind. In the background stands a shepherd. The man on the
               horse is dressed in an old-fashioned coat and hat. Both the horse and hound are dark.
               The illustration has a border around it, and the initials S P are inscribed in the
               bottom right corner. </figDesc>
         </figure>
         <pb n="123"/>
         <head><title type="magazine"><lb/>The Strand Magazine. <lb/>Vol. xxii. <date when="1901-08"
                  >August, 1901.</date> No. 128.<lb/></title>
            <title type="novel">The Hound of the Baskervilles.* <lb/>ANOTHER ADVENTURE
               OF<lb/>SHERLOCK HOLMES.</title>
            <title type="author">By Conan
            Doyle.</title><!-- cannot add a rend font in this author section--></head>
         <cb/>
         <div type="chapter" n="1" rend="title">
            <ab rend="caps">Chapter I.</ab>
            <ab rend="caps"><persName ref="#Holmes">Mr. Sherlock Holmes</persName>.</ab>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">MR. SHERLOCK HOLMES</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>who was
               usually very late in<lb break="yes"/>the mornings, save upon those<lb break="yes"
               />not infrequent occasions when<lb break="yes"/>he was up all night, was seated<lb
                  break="yes"/>at the breakfast table. I stood<lb break="yes"/>upon the hearth-rug
               and picked up the stick<lb break="yes"/>which our visitor had left behind him the
                  night<lb break="yes"/>before. It was a fine, thick piece of wood,<lb break="yes"
               />bulbous-headed, of the sort which is known<lb break="yes"/>as a "Penang lawyer."
               Just under the head<lb break="yes"/>was a broad silver band, nearly an inch<lb
                  break="yes"/>across. "To <persName ref="#Mortimer">James Mortimer, <abbr>M. R. C.
                     S</abbr></persName>.,<lb break="yes"/>from his friends of the <placeName
                  ref="#CCHospital"><abbr>C. C. H.</abbr></placeName>," was engraved <lb break="yes"
               />upon it, with the date "1884." It was just<lb break="yes"/>such a stick as the
               old-fashioned family<lb break="yes"/>practitioner used to carry—dignified, solid,<lb
                  break="yes"/>and reassuring.</p>
            <p><said>"Well, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, what do you make of
                  it?"</said></p>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName> was sitting with his back to me,<lb
                  break="yes"/>and I had given him no sign of my occupa-<lb break="no"/>tion.</p>
            <p><said>"How did you know what I was doing?<lb break="yes"/>I believe you have eyes in
                  the back of your<lb break="yes"/>head."</said></p>
            <p><said>"I have, at least, a well-polished silver-<lb break="yes"/>plated coffee-pot in
                  front of me,"</said> said he.<lb break="yes"/><s>"But, tell me, <persName
                     ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, what do you make of<lb break="yes"/>our
                  visitor's stick? Since we have been so<lb break="yes"/>unfortunate as to miss him
                  and have no<lb break="yes"/>notion of his errand, this accidental souvenir<lb
                     break="yes"/>becomes of importance. Let me hear you<lb break="yes"/>reconstruct
                  the man by an examination of it."</s></p>
            <p><said>"I think," said I, following as far as I could<lb break="yes"/>the methods of
                  my companion, "that <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr.<lb break="yes"
                     />Mortimer</persName> is a successful elderly medical man, <fw type="-----">
                     <!--what should we call this??????????-->* This story owes its inception to my
                     friend, Mr. Fletcher<lb break="yes"/>Robinson, who has helped me both in the
                     general plot and in<lb break="yes"/>the local details.—A. C. D.</fw>
                  <cb/><lb break="yes"/>well-esteemed, since those who know him<lb break="yes"/>give
                  him this mark of their appreciation."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Good!"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>.
                  <s>"Excellent!"</s></p>
            <p><said>"I think also that the probability is in <lb break="yes"/>favour of his being a
                  country practitioner<lb break="yes"/>who does a great deal of his visiting on
                  foot."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Why so?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Because this stick, though originally a<lb break="yes"/>very handsome one, has
                  been so knocked<lb break="yes"/>about that I can hardly imagine a town<lb
                     break="yes"/>practitioner carrying it. The thick iron<lb break="yes"/>ferrule
                  is worn down, so it is evident that he<lb break="yes"/>has done a great amount of
                  walking with it."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Perfectly sound !"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>.</p>
            <p><said>"And then again, there is the 'friends of<lb break="yes"/>the
                     <abbr>C.C.H.</abbr>' I should guess that to be the<lb break="yes"/>Something
                  Hunt, the local hunt to whose<lb break="yes"/>members he has possibly given some
                     surgical<lb break="yes"/>assistance, and which has made him a small<lb
                     break="yes"/>presentation in return."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Really, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, you excel yourself,"</said>
                  said<lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>, pushing back his
               chair and lighting <lb break="yes"/>a cigarette. <said>"I am bound to say that in all
                     <lb break="yes"/>the accounts which you have been so good <lb break="yes"/>as
                  to give of my own small achievements you <lb break="no"/>have habitually
                  underrated your own abilities. <lb break="yes"/>It may be that you are not
                  yourself luminous, <lb break="yes"/>but you are a conductor of light. Some <lb
                     break="yes"/>people without possessing genius have a <lb break="yes"
                  />remarkable power of stimulating it. I con-<lb break="no"/>fess, my dear fellow,
                  that I am very much in <lb break="yes"/>your debt."</said></p>
            <p>He had never said as much before, and I <lb break="yes"/>must admit that his words
               gave me keen <lb break="yes"/>pleasure, for I had often been piqued by his <lb
                  break="yes"/>indifference to my admiration and to the <lb break="yes"/>attempts
               which I had made to give publicity <lb break="yes"/>to his methods. I was proud too
               to think <lb break="yes"/>that I had so far mastered his system as to <lb break="yes"
               />apply it in a way which earned his approval. <lb break="yes"/>He now took the stick
               from my hands<fw type="--------------------">Vol. xxii.-16.</fw>
               <!-- what type would this fw be??????-->
               <pb n="124"/><fw type="RunnningHead" rend="caps"> 124 The Strand Magazine.</fw>
               <cb/>and examined it for a few minutes with his<lb break="yes"/>naked eyes. Then with
               an expression of<lb break="yes"/>interest he laid down his cigarette and, carry-<lb
                  break="no"/>ing the cane to the window, he looked over<lb break="yes"/>it again
               with a convex lens.</p>
            <p><said>"Interesting, though elementary,"</said> said he,<lb break="yes"/>as he
               returned to his favourite corner of the<lb break="yes"/>settee. <said>"There are
                  certainly one or two<lb break="yes"/>indications upon the stick. <figure
                     place="center">
                     <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage124.png"/>
                     <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps">"He looked over it again with a convex lens."</p>
                     <figDesc><persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock Holmes</persName>, stood by a window, examines a walking stick with a
                        magnifying glass. Holmes is wearing a light shirt and vest under a dark
                        jacket, a dark bow tie, and pants. He has short hair. The image does not
                        have a border around it, and the initials S P are inscribed in the bottom
                        right corner.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <lb break="yes"/>It gives us the basis for<lb break="yes"/>several
                  deductions."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Has anything escaped<lb break="yes"/>me?"</said> I asked, with some<lb
                  break="yes"/>self-importance. <said>"I trust<lb break="yes"/>that there is nothing
                     of<lb break="yes"/>consequence which I have<lb break="yes"
               />overlooked?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"I am afraid, my dear<lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Watson"
                  >Watson</persName>, that most of your<lb break="yes"/>conclusions were erro-<lb
                     break="no"/>neous. When I said that<lb break="yes"/>you stimulated me I
                     meant,<lb break="yes"/>to be frank, that in noting<lb break="yes"/>your
                  fallacies I was occa-<lb break="no"/>sionally guided towards the<lb break="yes"
                  />truth. Not that you are<lb break="yes"/>entirely wrong in this in-<lb break="no"
                  />stance. The man is cer-<lb break="no"/>tainly a country practi-<lb break="yes"
                  />tioner. And he walks a<lb break="yes"/>good deal."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Then I was right."</said></p>
            <p><said>"To that extent."</said></p>
            <p><said>"But that was all."</said></p>
            <p><said>"No, no, my dear Wat-<lb break="no"/>son, not all—by no means<lb break="yes"
                  />all. I would suggest, for<lb break="yes"/>example, that a presenta-<lb
                     break="no"/>tion to a doctor is more<lb break="yes"/>likely to come from an<lb
                     break="yes"/>hospital than from a<lb break="yes"/>hunt, and that when<lb
                     break="yes"/>the initials '<abbr>C.C.</abbr>' are<lb break="yes"/>placed before
                  that hospital<lb break="yes"/>the words 'Charing <lb break="yes"/>Cross' very
                  naturally suggest themselves."</said></p>
            <p><said>"You may be right."</said></p>
            <p><said>"The probability lies in that direction.<lb break="yes"/>And if we take this as
                  a working hypothesis<lb break="yes"/>we have a fresh basis from which to start
                     our<lb break="yes"/>construction of this unknown visitor."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Well, then, supposing that '<abbr>C.C.H</abbr>.' does<lb break="yes"/>stand
                  for '<placeName ref="#CCHospital">Charing Cross Hospital</placeName>,' what<lb
                     break="yes"/>further inferences may we draw?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Do none suggest themselves? You<lb break="yes"/>know my methods. Apply
                  them!"</said></p>
            <p><said>"I can only think of the obvious conclu-<lb break="no"/>sion that the man has
                  practiced in town<lb break="yes"/>before going to the country."</said></p>

            <cb/>
            <p><said>"I think that we might venture a little<lb break="yes"/>farther than this. Look
                  at it in this<lb break="yes"/>light. On what occasion would it be<lb break="yes"
                  />most probable that such a presentation<lb break="yes"/>would be made? When would
                  his friends<lb break="yes"/>unite to give him a pledge of their good will?<lb
                     break="yes"/>Obviously at the moment when <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr.
                     Mortimer</persName><lb break="yes"/>withdrew from the service of the hospital
                     in<lb break="yes"/>order to start in practice<lb break="yes"/>for himself. We
                     know<lb break="yes"/>there has been a presenta-<lb break="no"/>tion. We believe
                  there has<lb break="yes"/>been a change from a town <lb break="yes"/>hospital to a
                  country prac-<lb break="no"/>tice. Is it, then, stretching<lb break="yes"/>our
                  inference too far to say<lb break="yes"/>that the presentation was<lb break="yes"
                  />on the occasion of the<lb break="yes"/>change?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"It certainly seems<lb break="yes"/>probable."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Now, you will observe<lb break="yes"/>that he could not have been<lb
                     break="yes"/>on the <emph rend="italics">staff</emph> of the hospital,<lb
                     break="yes"/>since only a man well-<lb break="maybe"/>established in a
                     London<lb break="yes"/>practice could hold such a<lb break="yes"/>position, and
                  such a one<lb break="yes"/>would not drift into the<lb break="yes"/>country. What
                  was he then?<lb break="yes"/>If he was in the hos-<lb break="no"/>pital and yet
                  not on the<lb break="yes"/>staff he could only have<lb break="yes"/>been a
                  house-surgeon or a<lb break="yes"/>house-physician — little<lb break="yes"/>more
                  than a senior student.<lb break="yes"/>And he left five years ago<lb break="yes"
                  />—the date is on the stick. <lb break="yes"/>So on your grave, middle-aged<lb
                     break="yes"/>family practitioner vanishes<lb break="yes"/>into thin air,<lb
                     break="yes"/>my dear <persName ref="#Watson">Wat-<lb break="no"
                  />son</persName>, and there emerges a<lb break="yes"/>young fellow under
                     thirty,<lb break="yes"/>amiable, unambitious,<lb break="yes"/>absent-minded,
                  and the<lb break="yes"/>possessor of a favourite dog, which I should<lb
                     break="yes"/>describe roughly as being larger than a terrier<lb break="yes"
                  />and smaller than a mastiff."</said></p>
            <p>I laughed incredulously as <persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock<lb break="yes"
                  />Holmes</persName> leaned back in his settee and blew<lb break="yes"/>little
               wavering rings of smoke up to the<lb break="yes"/>ceiling.</p>
            <p><said>"As to the latter part, I have no means<lb break="yes"/>of checking
                  you,"</said> said I, <said>"but at least<lb break="yes"/>it is not difficult to
                  find out a few par-<lb break="no"/>ticulars about the man's age and profes-<lb
                     break="no"/>sional career."</said> From my small medical<lb break="yes"/>shelf
               I took down the Medical Directory and<lb break="yes"/>turned up the name. There were
               several <pb n="125"/><fw type="RunningHead" rend="caps">The Hound of the Baskervilles
                  125</fw> Mortimers, but only one who could be our<lb break="yes"/>visitor. I read
               his record aloud.</p>
            <p><said>"<persName ref="#Mortimer">Mortimer, James, <abbr>M.R.C.S.</abbr></persName>,
                     1882,<lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#Grimpen">Grimpen</placeName>, <placeName
                     ref="#Dartmoor">Dartmoor</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Devon"
                  >Devon</placeName>. House surgeon,<lb break="yes"/>from 1882 to 1884, at
                     <placeName ref="#CCHospital">Charing Cross<lb break="yes"
                  />Hospital</placeName>. Winner of the Jackson prize for<lb break="yes"
                  />Comparative Pathology, with essay entitled<lb break="yes"/>'Is Disease a
                  Reversion?' Corresponding<lb break="yes"/>member of the Swedish Pathological
                     Society.<lb break="yes"/>Author of 'Some Freaks of Atavism'<lb break="yes"/><q
                     rend="italics">(Lancet, 1882)</q>. 'Do We Progress?' <q rend="italics"
                        >(Journal<lb break="yes"/>of Psychology, March, 1883)</q>.
                  <!-- unsure whether we will be creating some sort of citation format--> Medical<lb
                     break="yes"/>Officer for the parishes of <placeName ref="#Grimpen"
                     >Grimpen</placeName>,<lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#Thorsley"
                     >Thorsley</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#HighBarrow">High
                  Barrow</placeName>."</said></p>
            <p><said>"No mention of that local hunt, <persName ref="#Watson"
                  >Watson</persName>,"</said><lb break="yes"/>said <persName ref="#Holmes"
                  >Holmes</persName>, with a mischievous smile, <said>"but<lb break="yes"/>a country
                  doctor, as you very astutely observed.<lb break="yes"/>I think that I am fairly
                  justified in my infer-<lb break="no"/>ences. As to the adjectives, I said, if I<lb
                     break="yes"/>remember right, amiable, unambitious, and<lb break="yes"
                  />absent-minded. It is my experience that it is<lb break="yes"/>only an amiable
                  man in this world who<lb break="yes"/>receives testimonials, only 
                     <figure place="bottom right">
                     <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage125.png"/>
                        <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps">"His eyes fell upon the stick in Holme's hand."</p>
                     <figDesc> <persName ref="#Mortimer">Mortimer</persName> is holding the door to the room Sherlock and Watson are in,
                        having just walked in. <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName> and <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName> are dressed in suits, Sherlock is
                        holding a cane, and Mortimer is dressed in a coat and holding a top hat in
                        his free hand. Across from a table set in the middle of the room, Mortimer
                        is looking towards Sherlock and the cane Sherlock holds. The image has a
                        border around it, except for its bottom, and the initials S P are inscribed
                        in the bottom right corner.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <lb break="yes"/>an unambitious one who<lb break="yes"/>abandons a London
                     career<lb break="yes"/>for the country, and only<lb break="yes"/>an
                  absent-minded one who<lb break="yes"/>leaves his stick and not his<lb break="yes"
                  />visiting-card after waiting<lb break="yes"/>an hour in your room."</said></p>
            <p><said>"And the dog?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Has been in the habit<lb break="yes"/>of carrying this stick behind<lb
                     break="yes"/>his master. Being a heavy<lb break="yes"/>stick the dog has held
                     it<lb break="yes"/>tightly by the middle, and<lb break="yes"/>the marks of his
                  teeth are<lb break="yes"/>very plainly visible. The<lb break="yes"/>dog's jaw, as
                  shown in the<lb break="yes"/>space between these marks,<lb break="yes"/>is too
                  broad in my opinion<lb break="yes"/>for a terrier and not broad<lb break="yes"
                  />enough for a mastiff. It may<lb break="yes"/>have been—yes, by Jove, it<lb
                     break="yes"/>is a curly-haired spaniel."</said></p>
            <p>He had risen and paced<lb break="yes"/>the room as he spoke. Now<lb break="yes"/>he
               halted in the recess of<lb break="yes"/>the window. There was<lb break="yes"/>such a
               ring of conviction in<lb break="yes"/>his voice that I glanced up<lb break="yes"/>in
               surprise.</p>
            <p><said>"My dear fellow, how<lb break="yes"/>can you possibly be so<lb break="yes"
                  />sure of that?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"For the very simple<lb break="yes"/>reason that I see the dog<lb break="yes"
                  />himself on our very door-<lb break="maybe"/>step, and there is the ring <cb/>of
                  its owner. Don't move, I beg you, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>.<lb
                     break="yes"/>He is a professional brother of yours, and your<lb break="yes"
                  />presence may be of assistance to me. Now is<lb break="yes"/>the dramatic moment
                  of fate, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, when<lb break="yes"/>you hear
                  a step upon the stair which is walking<lb break="yes"/>into your life, and you
                  know not whether for<lb break="yes"/>good or ill. What does <persName
                     ref="#Mortimer">Dr. James Mortimer</persName>, <lb break="yes"/>the man of
                  science, ask of <persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock Holmes</persName>,<lb break="yes"
                  />the specialist in crime? Come in!"</said></p>
            <p>The appearance of our visitor was a surprise<lb break="yes"/>to me, since I had
               expected a typical country<lb break="yes"/>practitioner. He was a very tall, thin
                  man,<lb break="yes"/>with a long nose like a beak, which jutted out<lb break="yes"
               />between two keen, grey eyes, set closely<lb break="yes"/>together and sparkling
               brightly from behind a<lb break="yes"/>pair of gold-rimmed glasses. He was clad in
                  <lb break="yes"/>a professional but rather slovenly fashion, for<lb break="yes"
               />his frock-coat dingy and his trousers<lb break="yes"/>frayed. Though young, his
               long back was<lb break="yes"/>already bowed, and he walked with a forward<lb
                  break="yes"/>thrust of his head and a general air of peering<lb break="yes"
               />benevolence. As he entered his eyes fell upon <pb n="126"/>
               <fw type="RunnningHead" rend="caps">126 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>
               <cb/>the stick in <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>'s hand, and he ran<lb
                  break="yes"/>towards it with an exclamation of joy. <said>"I am<lb break="yes"/>so
                  very glad,"</said> said he. <said>"I was not sure<lb break="yes"/>whether I had
                  left it here or in the <placeName ref="ShippingOffice">Shipping<lb break="yes"
                     />Office</placeName>. I would not lose that stick for the<lb break="yes"
                  />world."</said></p>
            <p><said>"A presentation, I see,"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes"
               >Holmes</persName>.</p>
            <p><said>"Yes, sir."</said></p>
            <p><said>"From <placeName ref="#CCHospital">Charing Cross
               Hospital</placeName>?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"From one or two friends there on the<lb break="yes"/>occasion of my
                  marriage."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Dear, dear, that's bad!"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes"
                  >Holmes</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>shaking his head.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName> blinked through his glasses<lb
                  break="yes"/>in mild astonishment.</p>
            <p><said>"Why was it bad?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Only that you have disarranged our little<lb break="yes"/>deductions. Your
                  marriage, you say?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Yes, sir. I married, and so left the<lb break="yes"/>hospital, and with it all
                  hopes of a consulting<lb break="yes"/>practice. It was necessary to make a home<lb
                     break="yes"/>of my own."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Come, come, we are not so far wrong<lb break="yes"/>after all,"</said> said
                  <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>. <said>"And now, <persName
                     ref="#Mortimer">Dr.<lb break="yes"/>James Mortmer</persName><g
                     ref="#LongEmdash"/>"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Mister, sir, Mister—a humble <abbr>M.R.C.S.</abbr>"</said></p>
            <p><said>"And a man of precise mind, evidently."</said></p>
            <p><said>"A dabbler in science, <persName ref="#Holmes">Mr. Holmes</persName>, a<lb
                     break="yes"/>picker up of shells on the shores of the<lb break="yes"/>great
                  unknown ocean. I presume that it is<lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Holmes">Mr.
                     Sherlock Holmes</persName> whom I am<lb break="yes"/>addressing and
                  not——"</said></p>
            <p><said>"No, this is my friend <persName ref="#Watson">Dr.
               Watson</persName>."</said></p>
            <p><ref target="#phrenology"><said>"Glad to meet you, sir. I have heard<lb break="yes"
                     />your name mentioned in connection with that<lb break="yes"/>of your friend.
                     You interest me very much,<lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Holmes">Mr.
                        Holmes</persName>. I had hardly expected so<lb break="yes"/>dolichocephalic
                     a skull or such well-marked<lb break="yes"/>supra-orbital development. Would
                     you have<lb break="yes"/>any objection to my running my finger along<lb
                        break="yes"/>you parietal fissure? A cast of your skull,<lb break="yes"
                     />sir, until the original is available, would be<lb break="yes"/>an ornament to
                     any anthropological museum.<lb break="yes"/>It is not my intention to be
                     fulsome, but I<lb break="yes"/>confess that I covet your
               skull."</said></ref></p>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock Holmes</persName> waved our strange visitor<lb
                  break="yes"/>into a chair. <said>"You are an enthusiast in your<lb break="yes"
                  />line of thought, I perceive, sir, as I am in<lb break="yes"/>mine,"</said> said
               he. <said>"I observe from your fore-<lb break="maybe"/>finger that you make your own
                     cigarettes.<lb break="yes"/>Have no hesitation in lighting one."</said></p>
            <p>The man drew out paper and tobacco and<lb break="yes"/>twirled the one up into the
               other with surpis-<lb break="no"/>ing dexterity. He had long, quivering fingers<lb
                  break="yes"/>as agile and restless as the antennæ of an<lb break="yes"
               />insect.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName> was silent, but his little darting<lb
                  break="yes"/>glances showed me the interest which he<lb break="yes"/>took in our
               curious companion.</p>

            <cb/>
            <p><said>"I presume, sir,"</said> said he at last, <said>"that it<lb break="yes"/>was
                  not merely for the purpose of examining<lb break="yes"/>my skull that you have
                  done me the honour<lb break="yes"/>to call here last night and again
                  to-day?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"No, sir, no; though I am happy to have<lb break="yes"/>had the opportunity of
                  doing that as well. I<lb break="yes"/>came to you, <persName ref="#Holmes">Mr.
                     Holmes</persName>, because I recog-<lb break="no"/>nise that I am myself an
                  unpractical man,<lb break="yes"/>and because I am suddenly confronted with<lb
                     break="yes"/>a most serious and extraordinary problem.<lb break="yes"
                  />Recognising, as I do, that you are the second<lb break="yes"/>highest expert in
                     <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName><g ref="#LongEmdash"/>"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Indeed, sir! May I inquire who has the<lb break="yes"/>honour to be the
                  first?"</said> asked <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>, with<lb
                  break="yes"/>some asperity.</p>
            <p><said>"To the man of precisely scientific mind<lb break="yes"/>the work <persName
                     ref="#Bertillon">Monsieur Bertillon</persName> must always<lb break="yes"
                  />appeal strongly."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Then had you not better consult him?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"I said, sir, to the precisely scientific<lb break="yes"/>mind. But as a
                  practical man of affairs it is<lb break="yes"/>acknowledged that you stand alone.
                  I trust,<lb break="yes"/>sir, that I have not inadvertently<g ref="#LongEmdash"
                  />"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Just a little," said <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>. "I think,<lb
                     break="yes"/><persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName>, you would do
                  wisely if without<lb break="yes"/>more ado you would kindly tell me plainly<lb
                     break="yes"/>what the exact nature of the problem is in<lb break="yes"/>which
                  you demand my assistance."</said></p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter" n="2">
            <ab><g ref="#ChapterLine"/></ab>
            <ab rend="caps">CHAPTER II.</ab>
            <ab rend="caps">THE CURSE OF THE BASKERVILLES.</ab>
            <p><said>"I have in my pocket a manuscript,"</said> said<lb break="yes"/><persName
                  ref="#Mortimer">Dr. James Mortimer</persName>.</p>
            <p><said>"I observed it as you entered the room,"</said><lb break="yes"/>said <persName
                  ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName>.</p>
            <p><said>"It is an old manuscript."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Early eighteenth century, unless it is a<lb break="yes"/>forgery."</said></p>
            <p><said>"How can you say that, sir?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"You have presented an inch or two of it<lb break="yes"/>to my examination all
                  the time that you have<lb break="yes"/>been talking. It would be a poor expert
                     who<lb break="yes"/>could not give the date of a document within<lb break="yes"
                  />a decade or so. You may possibly have read<lb break="yes"/>my little monograph
                  upon the subject. I put<lb break="yes"/>that at <date when="1730"
                  >1730</date>."</said></p>
            <p><said>"The exact date is <date when="1742">1742</date>."</said>
               <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName><lb break="yes"/>drew it from his
               breast-pocket. <said>"This family<lb break="yes"/>paper was committed to my care by
                     <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir<lb break="yes"/>Charles
                     Baskerville</persName>, whose sudden and tragic<lb break="yes"/>death some
                  three months ago created so<lb break="yes"/>much excitement in <placeName
                     ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName>. I may say<lb break="yes"/>that I was
                  his personal friend as well as his<lb break="yes"/>medical attendant. He was a
                     strong-minded<lb break="yes"/>man, sir, shrewd, practical, and as unimagi-<lb
                     break="no"/>native as I am myself. Yet he took this<lb break="yes"/>document
                  very seriously, and his mind was<lb break="yes"/>prepared for just such an end as
                  did even-<lb break="no"/>tually overtake him."</said></p>

            <pb n="127"/>
            <fw type="RunnningHead" rend="caps">THE HOUND OF THE BASKERVILLES 127</fw>

            <cb/>
            <p><persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName> stretched out his hand for the<lb
                  break="yes"/>manuscript and flattened it upon his knee.</p>
            <p><said>"You will observe, <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName>, the
                     alternative<lb break="yes"/>use of the long s and the short. It is one<lb
                     break="yes"/>of several indications which enabled me to fix the
               date."</said></p>
            <p>I looked over his shoulder at the yellow<lb break="yes"/>paper and the faded script.
               At the head<lb break="yes"/>was written: "<placeName ref="BaskervilleHall"
                  >Baskerville Hall</placeName>," and below, in<lb break="yes"/>large, scrawling
               figures: "<date when="1742">1742</date>."</p>
            <figure place="center">
               <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage127.png"/>
               <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps">
                     "<persName ref="#Mortimer">DR. MORTIMER</persName> TURNED THE MANUSCRIPT TO THE
                  LIGHT AND READ."</p>
               <figDesc><persName ref="#Mortimer">Mortimer</persName> and <persName ref="#Holmes">Holmes</persName> sit in chairs across from each other while Watson
                  stands nearby. Mortimer is holding and looking at a written material, and Holmes
                  leaning back while appearing to be in conversation. All three men are dressed in
                  suits. The image has a border around it, except for its bottom, and the initials S
                  P are inscribed in the bottom right corner.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p><said>"It appears to be a statement of some<lb break="yes"/>sort."</said></p>
            <p><said>"Yes, it is a statement of a certain legend<lb break="yes"/>which runs in the
                  Baskerville family."</said></p>
            <p><said>"But I understand that it is something<lb break="yes"/>more modern and
                  practical upon which you<lb break="yes"/> wish to consult me?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Most modern. A most practical, press-<lb break="no"/>ing matter, which must be
                  decided within<lb break="yes"/> twenty-four hours. But the manuscript is<lb
                     break="yes"/>short and is intimately connected with the<lb break="yes"/>affair.
                  With your permission I will read it<lb break="yes"/>to you."</said></p>
            <p>Holmes leaned back in his chair, placed<cb/>his finger-tips together, and closed his
                  eyes,<lb break="yes"/>with an air of resignation. <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr.
                  Mortimer</persName><lb break="yes"/>turned the manuscript to the light and read<lb
                  break="yes"/>in a high, crackling voice the following<lb break="yes"/>curious,
               old-world narrative:—</p>
            <p><said>"Of the origin of the Hound of the<lb break="yes"/>Baskervilles there have been
                  many state-<lb break="no"/>ments, yet as I come in a direct line from<lb
                     break="yes"/><persName ref="HBaskerville">Hugo Baskerville</persName>, and as I
                  had the story<lb break="yes"/>from my father, who also had it from his.<lb
                     break="yes"/>I have set it down with all belief that it oc-<lb break="no"
                  />curred even as is here set forth. And I would<lb break="yes"/>have you believe,
                  my sons, that the same<lb break="yes"/><ref>Justice</ref> which punishes sin may
                  also most<lb break="yes"/>graciously forgive it, and that no ban is so<lb
                     break="yes"/>heavy but that by prayer and repentance it<lb break="yes"/>may be
                  removed. Learn then from this<lb break="yes"/>story not to fear the fruits of the
                  past, but<lb break="yes"/>rather to be circumspect in the future, that<lb
                     break="yes"/>those foul passions whereby our family has<lb break="yes"
                  />suffered so grievously may not again be loosed to our undoing.</said></p>
            <p><said>"Know then that in the time of the <ref>Great<lb break="yes"/>Rebellion</ref>
                  (the history of which by the learned<pb n="128"/>
                  <fw type="RunnningHead" rend="caps">128 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>
                  <!-- what to do if these things are within saids and ps -->
                  <cb/><ref>Lord Clarendon<!-- This is a real guy apparently --></ref> I most
                  earnestly commend<lb break="yes"/>to your attention) this <placeName
                     ref="#BaskervilleHall">Manor of Baskerville</placeName><lb break="yes"/>was
                  held by <persName ref="#HBaskerville">Hugo</persName> of that name, nor can it<lb
                     break="yes"/>be gainsaid that he was a most wild, pro-<lb break="no"/>fane, and
                  godless man. This, in truth his<lb break="yes"/>neighbours might have pardoned,
                  seeing that<lb break="yes"/>saints have never flourished in those parts,<lb
                     break="yes"/>but there was in him a certain wanton and<lb break="yes"/>cruel
                  humour which made his name a by-<lb break="maybe"/>word through the West. It
                  chanced that<lb break="yes"/>this <persName ref="#HBaskerville">Hugo</persName>
                  came to love (if, indeed, so dark<lb break="yes"/>a passion may be known under so
                  bright a<lb break="yes"/>name) <persName ref="#theMaiden">the daughter</persName>
                  of a yeoman who held<lb break="yes"/>lands near the <placeName
                     ref="#BaskervilleHall">Baskerville estate</placeName>. But the<lb break="yes"
                  />young <persName ref="#theMaiden">maiden</persName>, being discreet and of
                     good<lb break="yes"/>repute, would ever avoid him, for she feared<lb
                     break="yes"/>his evil name. So it came to pass that one<lb break="yes"/><ref
                     target="#michaelmas">Michaelmas</ref> this <persName ref="#HBaskerville"
                     >Hugo</persName>, with five or six of his<lb break="yes"/>idle and wicked
                  companions, stole down<lb break="yes"/>upon the farm and carried off <persName
                     ref="#theMaiden">the maiden</persName>,<lb break="yes"/>her father and brothers
                  being from home, as<lb break="yes"/>he well knew. When they had brought her<lb
                     break="yes"/>to the <placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall">Hall</placeName>
                  <persName ref="#theMaiden">the maiden</persName> was placed in an<lb break="yes"
                  />upper chamber, while <persName ref="#HBaskerville">Hugo</persName> and his
                     friends<lb break="yes"/>sat down to a long carouse, as was their<lb break="yes"
                  />nightly custom. Now, the poor lass upstairs<lb break="yes"/>was like to have her
                  wits turned at the sing-<lb break="no"/>ing and shouting and terrible oaths
                     which<lb break="yes"/>came up to her from below, for they say that<lb
                     break="yes"/>the words used by <persName ref="#HBaskerville">Hugo
                     Baskerville</persName>, when<lb break="yes"/>he was in wine, were such as might
                  blast the<lb break="yes"/>man who said them. At last in the stress of<lb
                     break="yes"/>her fear she did that which might have<lb break="yes"/>daunted the
                  bravest or most active man, for<lb break="yes"/>by the aid of the growth of ivy
                  which covered<lb break="yes"/>(and still covers) the south wall she came down from
                  under the eaves, and so home-<lb break="no"/>ward across the moor, there being
                     three<lb break="yes"/>leagues betwixt <placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall">the
                     Hall</placeName> and her father's farm.</said></p>
            <p><said>"It chanced that some little time later<lb break="yes"/><persName
                     ref="#HBaskerville">Hugo</persName> left his guests to carry food and drink<lb
                     break="yes"/>—with other worse things, perchance—to <persName ref="#theMaiden"
                        >his<lb break="yes"/>captive</persName>, and so found the cage empty and
                     <persName ref="#theMaiden">the<lb break="yes"/>bird</persName> escaped. Then,
                  as it would seem, he<lb break="yes"/>became as one that hath a devil, for,
                     rushing<lb break="yes"/>down the stairs into the dining-hall, he<lb break="yes"
                  />sprang upon the great table, flagons and<lb break="yes"/>trenchers flying before
                  him, and he cried<lb break="yes"/>aloud before all the company that he would<lb
                     break="yes"/>that very night render his body and soul to<lb break="yes"/>the
                     <ref>Powers of Evil</ref> if he might but overtake<lb break="yes"/><persName
                     ref="theMaiden">the wench</persName>. And while the revelers stood<lb
                     break="yes"/>aghast at the fury of the man, one more<lb break="yes"/>wicked or,
                  it may be, more drunken than<lb break="yes"/>the rest, cried out that they should
                  put the<lb break="yes"/>hounds upon her. Whereat <persName ref="#HBaskerville"
                     >Hugo</persName> ran from<lb break="yes"/>the house, crying to his grooms that
                     they<lb break="yes"/>should saddle his mare and unkennel the<lb break="yes"
                  />pack, and giving the hounds a kerchief of<cb/>the maid's, he swung them to the
                  line, and so<lb break="yes"/>off full cry in the moonlight over <placeName
                     ref="#theMoor">the moor</placeName>.</said></p>
            <p><said>"Now, for some space the revelers stood<lb break="yes"/>agape, unable to
                  understand all that<lb break="yes"/>had been done in such haste. But anon their
                     =<lb break="yes"/>bemused wits awoke to the nature of the<lb break="yes"/>deed
                  which was like to be done upon <placeName ref="#theMoor">the<lb break="yes"
                     />moorlands</placeName>. Everything was now in an up-<lb break="no"/>roar, some
                  calling for their pistols, some for<lb break="yes"/>their horses, and some for
                  another flask of<lb break="yes"/>wine. But at length some sense came back<lb
                     break="yes"/>to their crazed minds, and the whole of them,<lb break="yes"
                  />thirteen in number, took horse and started in<lb break="yes"/>pursuit. The moon
                  shone clear above them,<lb break="yes"/>and they rode swiftly abreast, taking
                     that<lb break="yes"/>course which <persName ref="#theMaiden">the
                     maid</persName> must needs have taken<lb break="yes"/>if she were to reach her
                  own home.</said></p>
            <p><said>"They had gone a mile or two when they<lb break="yes"/>passed one of the night
                  shepherds upon <placeName ref="#theMoor">the<lb break="yes"
                  />moorlands</placeName>, and they cried to him to know if<lb break="yes"/>he had
                  seen the hunt. And the man, as the<lb break="yes"/>story goes, was so crazed with
                  fear that he could scarce speak, but at last he said that<lb break="yes"/>he had
                  indeed seen <persName ref="#theMaiden">the unhappy maiden</persName>,<lb
                     break="yes"/>with the hounds upon her track. 'But I<lb break="yes"/>have seen
                  more than that,'<!-- what do we do about quotes in said? --> said he, 'for<lb
                     break="yes"/><persName>Hugo Baskerville</persName> passed me upon his black<lb
                     break="yes"/>mare, and there ran mute behind him such a<lb break="yes"/>hound
                  of hell as God forbid should ever be<lb break="yes"/>at my heels.' So the drunken
                     squires<lb break="yes"/>cursed the shepherd and rode onwards. But<lb
                     break="yes"/>soon their skins turned cold, for there came<lb break="yes"/>a
                  galloping across <placeName ref="#theMoor">the moor</placeName>, and the black<lb
                     break="yes"/>mare, dabbled with white froth, went past<lb break="yes"/>with
                  trailing bridle and an empty saddle. Then<lb break="yes"/>the revelers rode close
                  together, for a great<lb break="yes"/>fear was on them, but they still followed
                     over<lb break="yes"/>the moor, though each, had he been alone,<lb break="yes"
                  />would have been right glad to have turned<lb break="yes"/>his horse's head.
                  Riding slowly in this<lb break="yes"/>fashion they came at last upon the
                     hounds.<lb break="yes"/>These, though known for their valour and<lb break="yes"
                  />their breed, were whimpering in a cluster at<lb break="yes"/>the head of a deep
                  dip or goyal, as we call<lb break="yes"/>it, upon <placeName ref="#theMoor">the
                     moor</placeName>, some slinking away and<lb break="yes"/>some, with starting
                  hackles and staring eyes,<lb break="yes"/>gazing down the narrow valley before
                  them.</said></p>
            <p><said>"The company then come to a halt, more<lb break="yes"/>sober men, as you may
                  guess, than when<lb break="yes"/>they started. The most of them would by<lb
                     break="yes"/>no means advance, but three of them, the<lb break="yes"/>boldest,
                  or it may be the most drunken, rode<lb break="yes"/>forward down the goyal. Now,
                  it opened<lb break="yes"/>into a broad space in which stood two of<lb break="yes"
                  />those great stones, still to be seen there,<lb break="yes"/>which were set by
                  certain forgotten peoples<lb break="yes"/>in the days of old. The moon was
                     shining<lb break="yes"/>bright upon the clearing, and there in the<lb
                     break="yes"/>centre lay <persName ref="#theMaiden">the unhappy maid</persName>
                  where she had <pb n="129"/>
            </p>
            <pb/>
         <figure place="top left">
            <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage129.png"/>
            <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps"> "There in the centre lay the unhappy maid where she
               had fallen." </p>
            <figDesc> A man and woman, <persName ref="#HuBaskerville">Hugo Baskerville</persName>
               and the maid, lay still on <placeName ref="#theMoors">a field</placeName> at night,
               and between them stands a dark hound, almost as large as Baskerville's corpse. Hugo
               Baskerville, who is laid out on his back in front of the picture, is in an old
               fashioned uniform, and a hat and cane are strewn near him. Closely behind him stands
               the hound, and behind it the woman lies on her side in a light dress. Behind these
               three main figures stand two larger rocks and three men on horseback reacting in
               horror to the scene, one of them obscured by the right border of the image. The image
               has a border around it, and the initials S P are inscribed in the bottom right
               corner. </figDesc>
         </figure>
         <cb/>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p>fallen, dead of fear and of fatigue. But it <lb break="yes"/>was not the sight of her
            body, nor yet was it <lb break="yes"/>that of the body of <persName ref="#HBaskerville"
               >Hugo Baskerville</persName> lying <lb break="yes"/>near her, which raised the hair
            upon the <lb break="yes"/>heads of these three dare-devil roysterers, <lb break="yes"
            />but it was that, standing over <persName ref="#HuBaskerville">Hugo</persName>, and <lb
               break="yes"/>plucking at his throat, there stood a foul <lb break="yes"/>thing, a
            great, black beast, shaped like a <lb break="yes"/>hound, yet larger than any hound that
            ever <lb break="yes"/>mortal eye has rested upon. And even as <lb break="yes"/>they
            looked the thing tore the throat out of <lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#HuBaskerville"
               >Hugo Baskerville</persName>, on which, as it turned its <lb break="yes"/>blazing
            eyes and dripping jaws upon them, <lb break="yes"/>the three shrieked with fear and rode
            for <lb break="yes"/>dear life, still screaming, across the moor. <lb break="yes"/>One,
            it is said, died that very night of what <lb break="yes"/>he had seen, and the other
            twain were but <lb break="yes"/>broken men for the rest of their days.</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p>
            <said>"Such is the tale, my sons, <lb break="yes"/>of the coming of the hound which is
               said to have plagued <lb break="yes"/>the family so sorely ever since. If I have <lb
                  break="yes"/>set it down it is because that which is clearly <lb break="yes"
               />known hath less terror than that which is but <lb break="yes"/>hinted at and
               guessed. Nor can it be denied</said>
         </p>
         <ab>Vol. xxii,—17</ab>
         <cb/>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>that many of the family have <lb break="yes"/>been unhappy in their deaths, <lb
                  break="yes"/>which have been sudden, <lb break="yes"/>bloody, and mysterious. Yet
                  <lb break="yes"/>may we shelter ourselves in the <lb break="yes"/>infinite
               goodness of Providence, <lb break="yes"/>which would not for ever punish <lb
                  break="yes"/>the innocent beyond that third <lb break="yes"/>or fourth generation
               which is <lb break="yes"/>threatened in Holy Writ. To <lb break="yes"/>that
               Providence, my sons, I <lb break="yes"/>hereby command you, and I <lb break="yes"
               />counsel you by way of caution <lb break="yes"/>to forbear from crossing the <lb
                  break="yes"/>moor in those dark hours when <lb break="yes"/>the powers of evil are
               exalted."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"[This from <persName ref="#HuBaskerville">Hugo Basker-<lb break="no"
                  />ville</persName> to his sons <persName>Rodger</persName> and <lb break="yes"
                  /><persName>John</persName>, with instructions that they <lb break="yes"/>say
               nothing thereof to their <lb break="yes"/>sister
               <persName>Elizabeth</persName>.]"</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p>When <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName> had <lb break="yes"/>finished
            reading this singular <lb break="yes"/>narrative he pushed his spec-<lb break="no"
            />tacles up on his forehead and <lb break="yes"/>stared across at <persName
               ref="#Holmes">Mr. Sherlock <lb break="yes"/>Holmes</persName>. The latter yawned <lb
               break="yes"/>and tossed the end of his <lb break="yes"/>cigarette into the fire. </p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Well?"</said> said he.</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Do you not find it interest<lb break="no"/>-ing?"</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"To a collector of fairy tales."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName> drew a folded <lb break="yes"
            />newspaper out of his pocket.</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Now, <persName ref="#Holmes">Mr. Holmes</persName>, we will give you <lb
                  break="yes"/>something a little more recent. This is the <lb break="yes"/><hi
                  rend="italics"><placeName ref="#Devon">Devon</placeName> County Chronicle</hi> of
                  <date>May 14th</date> of this <lb break="yes"/>year. It is a short account of the
               facts <lb break="yes"/>elicited at the death of <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir
                  Charles Basker-<lb break="no"/>ville</persName> which occurred a few days before
               that <lb break="yes"/>date."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p>My friend leaned a little forward and his <lb break="yes"/>expression became intent. Our
            visitor re-<lb break="yes"/>adjusted his glasses and began:—</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"The recent sudden death of <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles <lb
                     break="yes"/>Baskerville</persName>, whose name has been mentioned <lb
                  break="yes"/>as the probable Liberal candidate for <placeName ref="#Mid-Devon"
                     >Mid-<lb break="maybe"/>Devon</placeName> at the next election, has cast a
               gloom <lb break="yes"/>over the county. Though <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir
                  Charles</persName> had <lb break="yes"/>resided at <placeName
                  ref="#BaskervilleHall">Baskerville Hall</placeName> for a compara-<lb break="no"
               />tively short period his amiability of character <lb break="yes"/>and extreme
               generosity had won the <lb break="yes"/>affection and respect of all who had been <lb
                  break="yes"/>brought into contact with him. In these <lb break="yes"/>days of
                  <foreign rend="italics">nouveaux riches</foreign> it is refreshing to <lb
                  break="yes"/>find a case where the scion of an old county <lb break="yes"/>family
               which has fallen upon evil days is able <lb break="yes"/>to make his own fortune and
               to bring it back</said></p>
         <pb n="130"/>
         <fw type="RunningHead">130 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>
         <cb/>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>with him to restore the fallen grandeur of his <lb break="yes"/>line. <persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName>, as is well known, made <lb break="yes"
               />large sums of money in South African <lb break="yes"/>speculation. More wise than
               those who go <lb break="yes"/>on until the wheel turns against them, he <lb
                  break="yes"/>realized his gains and returned to <placeName ref="#England"
                  >England</placeName>
               <lb break="yes"/>with them. It is only two years since he <lb break="yes"/>took up
               his residence at <placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall">Baskerville Hall</placeName>, <lb
                  break="yes"/>and it is common talk how large were those <lb break="yes"/>schemes
               of reconstruction and improvement <lb break="yes"/>which have been interrupted by his
               death. <lb break="yes"/>Being himself childless, it was his openly-<lb break="maybe"
               />expressed desire that the whole <lb break="yes"/>countryside should, within his own
                  <figure place="center">
                  <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage130.png"/>
                  <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps"> "His body was discovered." </p>
                  <figDesc> A man, <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Charles Baskerville</persName>, is
                     laid on his stomach and is unresponsive to another man standing behind him
                     holding a lamp with a shocked expression. Both men are dressed in suits. The
                     lamp is the only light source and most of the background is obscured in dark.
                     The image has a border around it, except for its bottom, and the initials S P
                     are inscribed in the bottom right corner. </figDesc>
               </figure>
               <lb break="yes"/>lifetime, profit by his good fortune, <lb break="yes"/>and many will
               have personal reasons <lb break="yes"/>for bewailing his untimely end. His <lb
                  break="yes"/>generous donations to local and <lb break="yes"/>county charities
               have been frequently <lb break="yes"/>chronicled in these columns.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"The circumstances connected <lb break="yes"/>with the death of <persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName> can-<lb break="no"/>not be said to have
               been entirely <lb break="yes"/>cleared up by the <lb break="yes"/>inquest, but at <lb
                  break="yes"/>least enough has <lb break="yes"/>been done to dis-<lb break="no"
               />pose of those <lb break="yes"/>rumours to which <lb break="yes"/>local superstition
                  <lb break="yes"/>has given rise. <lb break="yes"/>There is no <lb break="yes"
               />reason whatever <lb break="yes"/>to suspect foul <lb break="yes"/>play, or to <lb
                  break="yes"/>imagine that <lb break="yes"/>death could be <lb break="yes"/>from
               any but <lb break="yes"/>natural causes. <lb break="yes"/><persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName> was <lb break="yes"/>a widower, and <lb
                  break="yes"/>a man who may <lb break="yes"/>be said to have <lb break="yes"/>been
               in some <lb break="yes"/>ways of an eccen-<lb break="no"/>tric habit of <lb
                  break="yes"/>mind. In spite of <lb break="yes"/>his considerable <lb break="yes"
               />wealth he was <lb break="yes"/>simple in his <lb break="yes"/>personal tastes, and
               his indoor servants at <lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall">Baskerville
                  Hall</placeName> consisted of a married <lb break="yes"/>couple named <persName
                  ref="#Barrymore">Barrymore</persName>, the husband acting <lb break="yes"/>as
               butler and the wife as housekeeper. Their <lb break="yes"/>evidence, corroborated by
               that of several <lb break="yes"/>friends, tends to show that <persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName>'s <lb break="yes"/>health has for some
               time been impaired, and <lb break="yes"/>points especially to some affection of the
                  <lb break="yes"/>heart, manifesting itself in changes of colour, <cb/><lb
                  break="yes"/>breathlessness, and acute attacks of nervous <lb break="yes"
               />depression. <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. James Mortimer</persName>, the friend <lb
                  break="yes"/>and medical attendant of the deceased, has <lb break="yes"/>given
               evidence to the same effect.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"The facts of the case are simple. <lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#CBaskerville"
                  >Sir Charles Baskerville</persName> was in the habit every <lb break="yes"/>night
               before going to bed of walking down <lb break="yes"/>the famous <placeName
                  ref="#YewAlley">Yew Alley</placeName> of <placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall"
                  >Baskerville Hall</placeName>. <lb break="yes"/>The evidence of the <persName
                  ref="#Barrymore">Barrymores</persName> shows <lb break="yes"/>that this had been
               his custom. On the <date when="1889-05-04"><lb break="yes"/>4th of May</date>
               <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName> had declared his <lb break="yes"
               />intention of starting next day for <placeName ref="#London">London</placeName>, <lb
                  break="yes"/>and had ordered <lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Barrymore"
                  >Barrymore</persName> to <lb break="yes"/>prepare his lug-<lb break="no"/>gage.
               That night <lb break="yes"/>he went out as <lb break="yes"/>usual for his <lb
                  break="yes"/>nocturnal walk, <lb break="yes"/>in the course of <lb break="yes"
               />which he was in <lb break="yes"/>the habit of <lb break="yes"/>smoking a cigar. <lb
                  break="yes"/>He never re-<lb break="no"/>turned. At <lb break="yes"/>twelve
               o'clock <lb break="yes"/><persName ref="#Barrymore">Barrymore</persName>, find-<lb
                  break="no"/>ing the hall door <lb break="yes"/>still open, be-<lb break="no"/>came
               alarmed <lb break="yes"/>and, lighting a <lb break="yes"/>lantern, went in <lb
                  break="yes"/>search of his <lb break="yes"/>master. The day <lb break="yes"/>had
               been wet, <lb break="yes"/>and <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName>'s
                  <lb break="yes"/>footmarks were <lb break="yes"/>easily traced <lb break="yes"
               />down the <placeName ref="#YewAlley">Alley</placeName>. <lb break="yes"/>Half-way
               down <lb break="yes"/>this walk there is <lb break="yes"/>a gate which <lb
                  break="yes"/>leads out on to <lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#theMoor">the
                  moor</placeName>. There <lb break="yes"/>were indications <lb break="yes"/>that
                  <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName>
               <lb break="yes"/>had stood for <lb break="yes"/>some little time <lb break="yes"
               />here. He then <lb break="yes"/>proceeded down <lb break="yes"/>the <placeName
                  ref="#YewAlley">Alley</placeName>, and it was at the far end of it that <lb
                  break="yes"/>his body was discovered. One fact which has <lb break="yes"/>not been
               explained is the statement of <persName ref="#Barrymore">Barry-<lb break="no"
                  />more</persName> that his master's footprints altered their <lb break="yes"
               />character from the time that he passed the <lb break="yes"/>moor-gate, and that he
               appeared from thence <lb break="yes"/>onwards to have been walking upon his toes. <lb
                  break="yes"/>One <persName ref="#Murphy">Murphy</persName>, a gipsy horse-dealer,
               was on the <lb break="yes"/>moor at no great distance at the time, but</said></p>
         <pb n="131"/>
         <fw type="RunningHead">THE HOUND OF THE BASKERVILLES 131</fw>
         <cb/>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>he appears by his own confession to have <lb break="yes"/>been the worse for
               drink. He declares that <lb break="yes"/>he heard cries, but is unable to state from
                  <lb break="yes"/>what direction they came. No signs of <lb break="yes"/>violence
               were to be discovered upon <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir <lb break="yes"
                  />Charles</persName>'s person, and though the doctor's <lb break="yes"/>evidence
               pointed to an almost incredible <lb break="yes"/>facial distortion—so great that
                  <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName>
               <lb break="yes"/>refused at first to believe that it was indeed <lb break="yes"/>his
               friend and patient who lay before him—it <lb break="yes"/>was explained that that is
               a symptom which <lb break="yes"/>is not unusual in cases of dyspnœa and death <lb
                  break="yes"/>from cardiac exhaustion. This explanation <lb break="yes"/>was borne
               out by the post-mortem examina-<lb break="no"/>tion, which showed long-standing
               organic <lb break="yes"/>disease, and the coroner's jury returned a <lb break="yes"
               />verdict in accordance with the medical <lb break="yes"/>evidence. It is well that
               this is so, for it <lb break="yes"/>is obviously of the utmost importance that <lb
                  break="yes"/><persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName>'s heir should
               settle at the <placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall">Hall</placeName>
               <lb break="yes"/>and continue the good work which has been <lb break="yes"/>so sadly
               interrupted. Had the prosaic find-<lb break="no"/>ing of the coroner not finally put
               an end <lb break="yes"/>to the romantic stories which have been <lb break="yes"
               />whispered in connection with the affair it <lb break="yes"/>might have been
               difficult to find a tenant for <lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall"
                  >Baskerville Hall</placeName>. It is understood that the <lb break="yes"
               />next-of-kin is <persName ref="#HBaskerville">Mr. Henry Baskerville</persName>, if
               he be <lb break="yes"/>still alive, the son of <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir
                  Charles Baskerville</persName>'s <lb break="yes"/>younger brother. The young man
               when last <lb break="yes"/>heard of was in <placeName ref="#America"
                  >America</placeName>, and inquiries are <lb break="yes"/>being instituted with a
               view to informing him <lb break="yes"/>of his good fortune."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName> refolded his paper and <lb break="yes"
            />replaced it in his pocket.</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Those are the public facts, <persName ref="#Holmes">Mr. Holmes</persName>, <lb
                  break="yes"/>in connection with the death of <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir
                  Charles <lb break="yes"/>Baskerville</persName>."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"I must thank you,"</said> said <persName ref="#Holmes">Sherlock
            Holmes</persName>, <lb break="yes"/><said>"for calling my attention to a case which <lb
                  break="yes"/>certainly presents some features of interest. <lb break="yes"/>I had
               observed some newspaper comment at <lb break="yes"/>the time, but I was exceedingly
               preoccupied <lb break="yes"/>by that little affair of the <placeName ref="#Vatican"
                  >Vatican</placeName> cameos, <lb break="yes"/>and in my anxiety to oblige the Pope
               I lost <lb break="yes"/>touch with several interesting English cases. <lb break="yes"
               />This article, you say, contains all the public <lb break="yes"/>facts?"</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"It does."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Then let me have the private ones."</said> He <lb break="yes"/>leaned back, put
            his finger-tips together, and <lb break="yes"/>assumed his most impassive and judicial
               <lb break="yes"/>expression.</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"In doing so,"</said> said <persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName>, who
               <lb break="yes"/>had begun to show signs of some strong <lb break="yes"/>emotion,
               <said>"I am telling that which I have not <lb break="yes"/>confided to anyone. My
               motive for with-<lb break="no"/>holding it from the coroner's inquiry is that a <lb
                  break="yes"/>man of science shrinks from placing himself <cb/><lb break="yes"/>in
               the public position of seeming to indorse <lb break="yes"/>a popular superstition. I
               had the further <lb break="yes"/>motive that <placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall"
                  >Baskerville Hall</placeName>, as the paper says, <lb break="yes"/>would certainly
               remain untenanted if anything <lb break="yes"/>were done to increase its already
               rather <lb break="yes"/>grim reputation. For both these reasons I <lb break="yes"
               />thought that I was justified in telling rather <lb break="yes"/>less than I knew,
               since no practical good <lb break="yes"/>could result from it, but with you there is
               no <lb break="yes"/>reason why I should not be perfectly frank.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"<placeName ref="#theMoor">The moor</placeName> is very sparsely inhabited, <lb
                  break="yes"/>and those who live near each other are <lb break="yes"/>thrown very
               much together. For this reason <lb break="yes"/>I saw a good deal of <persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles Baskerville</persName>. <lb break="yes"/>With the
               exception of <persName ref="#Frankland">Mr. Frankland</persName>, of <lb break="yes"
                  /><placeName ref="#LafterHall">Lafter Hall</placeName>, and <persName
                  ref="#Stapleton">Mr. Stapleton</persName>, the naturalist, <lb break="yes"/>there
               are no other men of education within <lb break="yes"/>many miles. <persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName> was a retiring man <lb break="yes"/>but
               the chance of his illness brought us <lb break="yes"/>together, and a community of
               interests in <lb break="yes"/>science kept us so. He had brought back <lb break="yes"
               />much scientific information from <placeName ref="#SouthAfrica">South <lb
                     break="yes"/>Africa</placeName>, and many a charming evening we <lb break="yes"
               />have spent together discussing the com-<lb break="no"/>parative anatomy of the
               Bushmen and the <lb break="yes"/>Hottentot.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Within the last few months it became <lb break="yes"/>increasingly plain to me
               that <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName>'s <lb break="yes"/>nervous
               system was strained to breaking <lb break="yes"/>point. He had taken this legend
               which I <lb break="yes"/>have read you exceedingly to heart—so <lb break="yes"/>much
               so that, although he would walk in his <lb break="yes"/>own grounds, nothing would
               induce him to <lb break="yes"/>go out upon the moor at night. Incredible <lb
                  break="yes"/>as it may appear to you, <persName ref="#Holmes">Mr.
                  Holmes</persName>, he <lb break="yes"/>was honestly convinced that a dreadful fate
                  <lb break="yes"/>overhung his family, and certainly the records <lb break="yes"
               />which he was able to give of his ancestors <lb break="yes"/>were not encouraging.
               The idea of some <lb break="yes"/>ghastly presence constantly haunted him, <lb
                  break="yes"/>and on more than one occasion he has asked <lb break="yes"/>me
               whether I had on my medical journeys <lb break="yes"/>at night ever seen any strange
               creature or <lb break="yes"/>heard the baying of a hound. The latter <lb break="yes"
               />question he put to me several times, and <lb break="yes"/>always with a voice which
               vibrated with <lb break="yes"/>excitement.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"I can well remember driving up to his <lb break="yes"/>house in the evening, some
               three weeks <lb break="yes"/>before the fatal event. He chanced to be at <lb
                  break="yes"/>his hall door. I had descended from my gig <lb break="yes"/>and was
               standing in front of him, when I <lb break="yes"/>saw his eyes fix themselves over my
               shoulder, <lb break="yes"/>and stare past me with an expression of the <lb
                  break="yes"/>most dreadful horror. I whisked round and <lb break="yes"/>had just
               time to catch a glimpse of some-<lb break="yes"/>thing which I took to be a large
               black calf <lb break="yes"/>passing at the head of the drive. So excited <lb
                  break="yes"/>and alarmed was he that I was compelled to</said></p>
         <pb n="132"/>
         <fw type="RunningHead">132 THE STRAND MAGAZINE</fw>
         <figure place="top left">
            <graphic url="../images/BaskervillePage132.png"/>
            <p rendition="bottom" rend="caps"> "I saw his eyes fix themselves over my shoulder." </p>
            <figDesc>
               <persName ref="#Watson">Watson</persName> and <persName ref="#Mortimer"
                  >Mortimer</persName> stand at the entrance to a building, Mortimer outside near a
               carriage, and face towards each other in conversation. Mortimer is wearing a dark
               suit and tophat, and Watson is in a light-colored suit. The image has a border around
               it, except for its bottom, and the initials S P are inscribed in the bottom right
               corner. </figDesc>
         </figure>
         <cb/>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>go down to the spot where the animal had <lb break="yes"/>been and look around for
               it. It was gone, <lb break="yes"/>however, and the incident appeared to make <lb
                  break="yes"/>the worst impression upon his mind. I <lb break="yes"/>stayed with
               him all the evening, and it was on <lb break="yes"/>that occasion, to explain the
               emotion which <lb break="yes"/>he had shown, that he confided to my keeping <lb
                  break="yes"/>that narrative which I read to you when first <lb break="yes"/>I
               came. I mention this small episode because <lb break="yes"/>it assumes some
               importance in view of the <lb break="yes"/>tragedy which followed, but I was
               convinced <lb break="yes"/>at the time that the matter was extremely <lb break="yes"
               />trivial and that his excitement had no <lb break="yes"/>justification.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"It was at my advice that <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName> was
                  <lb break="yes"/>about to go to <placeName ref="#London">London</placeName>. His
               heart was, I knew, <lb break="yes"/>affected, and the constant anxiety in which he
                  <lb break="yes"/>lived, however chimerical the cause of it might <lb break="yes"
               />be, was evidently having a serious effect upon <cb/><lb break="yes"/>his health. I
               thought that a <lb break="yes"/>few months among the dis-<lb break="no"/>tractions of
               town would <lb break="yes"/>send him back a new man. <lb break="yes"/><persName
                  ref="#Stapleton">Mr. Stapleton</persName>, a mutual <lb break="yes"/>friend who
               was much con-<lb break="no"/>cerned at his state of <lb break="yes"/>health, was of
               the same <lb break="yes"/>opinion. At the last in-<lb break="no"/>stant came this
               terrible <lb break="yes"/>catastrophe.</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"On the night of <persName ref="#CBaskerville">Sir <lb break="yes"
                  />Charles</persName>'s death <persName ref="#Barrymore">Barrymore</persName>
               <lb break="yes"/>the butler, who made the <lb break="yes"/>discovery, sent <persName
                  ref="#Perkins">Perkins</persName> the <lb break="yes"/>groom on horseback to <lb
                  break="yes"/>me, and as I was sitting <lb break="yes"/>up late I was able to reach
                  <lb break="yes"/><placeName ref="#BaskervilleHall">Baskerville Hall</placeName>
               within an <lb break="yes"/>hour of the event. I <lb break="yes"/>checked and
               corroborated <lb break="yes"/>all the facts which were <lb break="yes"/>mentioned at
               the inquest. <lb break="yes"/>I followed the footsteps <lb break="yes"/>down the
                  <placeName ref="#YewAlley">Yew Alley</placeName>, I saw <lb break="yes"/>the spot
               at the moor gate <lb break="yes"/>where he seemed to have <lb break="yes"/>waited, I
               remarked the <lb break="yes"/>change in the shape of the <lb break="yes"/>prints
               after that point, I <lb break="yes"/>noted that there were no <lb break="yes"/>other
               footsteps save those <lb break="yes"/>of <persName ref="#Barrymore"
                  >Barrymore</persName> on the soft <lb break="yes"/>gravel, and finally I care-<lb
                  break="no"/>fully examined the body, <lb break="yes"/>which had not been <lb
                  break="yes"/>touched until my arrival. <lb break="yes"/><persName
                  ref="#CBaskerville">Sir Charles</persName> lay on his face, his arms out, his <lb
                  break="yes"/>fingers dug into the ground, and his features <lb break="yes"
               />convulsed with some strong emotion to such <lb break="yes"/>an extent that I could
               hardly have sworn to <lb break="yes"/>his identity. There was certainly no physical
                  <lb break="yes"/>injury of any kind. But one false statement <lb break="yes"/>was
               made by <persName ref="#Barrymore">Barrymore</persName> at the inquest. He <lb
                  break="yes"/>said that there were no traces upon the <lb break="yes"/>ground round
               the body. He did not observe <lb break="yes"/>any. But I did—some little distance
               off, but <lb break="yes"/>fresh and clear."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Footprints?"</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"Footprints."</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"A man's or a woman's?"</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><persName ref="#Mortimer">Dr. Mortimer</persName> looked strangely at us for an <lb
               break="yes"/>instant, and his voice sank almost to a <lb break="yes"/>whisper as he
            answered:—</p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><said>"<persName ref="#Holmes">Mr. Holmes</persName>, they were the footprints of <lb
                  break="yes"/>a gigantic hound!"</said></p>
         <lb break="yes"/>
         <p><hi rend="italics">(To be continued.)</hi></p>
         </div>   
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <bibl> </bibl>
      <listPerson>
         <person xml:id="Holmes" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <forename>Sherlock</forename>
               <surname>Holmes</surname>
            </persName>
            <note><p>Sherlock Holmes is the main protagonist.</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Watson" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
               <forename>John</forename>
               <surname>Watson</surname>
            </persName>
            <note><p>The first person narrator and closest companion to Sherlock Holmes.</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Mortimer" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
               <forename>James</forename>
               <surname>Mortimer</surname>
            </persName>
            <note><p>Personal friend and physician to Charles Baskerville. Fills Holmes and Watson
                  in on both the published details of the case and his own personal
               experiences.</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Bertillon" role="fictional">
            <persName>Bertillon</persName>
            <note><p>Note</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="CBaskerville" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <roleName>Sir</roleName>
               <forename>Charles</forename>
               <surname>Baskerville</surname></persName>
            <note><p>He dead</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="HBaskerville" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <forename>Henry</forename>
               <surname>Baskerville</surname>
            </persName>
            <note><p>Charles Baskerville's newphew and heir.</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="HuBaskerville" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <forename>Hugo</forename>
               <surname>Baskerville</surname>
            </persName>
            <note><p/></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="theMaiden" role="fictional">
            <persName>Maiden</persName>
            <note><p>Note</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Barrymore" role="fictional">
            <persName>
               <surname>Barrymore</surname>
            </persName>
            <note><p>The surname of a couple who live at Baskerville hall and were Charles
                  Baskerville's butler and housekeeper. The butler is the one who discovered
                  Charle's body.</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Murphy" role="fictional">
            <persName>Murphy</persName>
            <note><p>Note</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Frankland" role="fictional">
            <persName>Mr. Frankland</persName>
            <note><p>Note</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Stapleton" role="fictional">
            <persName>Mr. Stapleton</persName>
            <note><p>Note</p></note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="Perkins" role="fictional">
            <persName>Perkins</persName>
            <note><p>The stable groom at Baskerville Hall.</p></note>
         </person>
      </listPerson>
      <listPlace>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="CCHospital"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="London"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Grimpen"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Dartmoor"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Devon"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Thorsley"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="HighBarrow"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="ShippingOffice"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Europe"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Devonshire"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="BaskervilleHall"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="theMoor"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Mid-Devon"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="SouthAfrica"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="America"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="Vatican"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="LafterHall"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="YewAlley"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placeName xml:id="England"/>
            <note><p/></note>
         </place>
      </listPlace>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
