<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bleak House</title>
            <author><ref target="#Dick"/></author>
            <editor>Steven Haker</editor>
            <editor>Karalee Harris</editor>
            <editor>Paul Jason Perez</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Bleak House itself is a fiction about the lives of the rich and poor in London
               society during the Victorian era. However, our main focus is on the advertisements
               appearing before and after the serialized novel. These advertisements are appealing
               to a certain group of consumers during the mid-Victorian era of London. From our
               edition, readers would be able to peek into the world of 1852 when Bleak House was
               being published as a serial. The advertisements present in Bleak House are an
               artifact of that time; though they were likely ignored during it, they now provide a
               unique window into that time period. The audience for this edition would likely be
               people researching this time period rather than people who want to read Bleak House
               as a text; this means that it would lend itself moreso to scholars rather than
               laypeople.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Bleak House</title>
                  <author><ref target="#Dick">Dickens, Charles</ref>, <date type="birth"
                        >1812</date>-<date type="death">1870</date></author>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>illustrated by</resp>
                     <persName xml:id="HKB">Browne, Hablot Knight, <date type="born"
                           >1815</date>-<date type="death">1882</date></persName>
                  </respStmt>
                  <edition>[First edition]</edition>
                  <extent>70 pp</extent>
                  <publisher xml:id="BandE">Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
                  <pubPlace><placeName type="city">London,
                     <country>England</country></placeName></pubPlace>
                  <date><date when="1852">1852</date>-<date when="1853">1853</date></date>
                  <idno type="OCLC">38689984</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head>Bleak House no. 3</head>
            <p rend="subtitle">Edited by Karalee Harris, Steven Haker, and Paul Jason Perez</p>
            <p> This edition focuses on the advertisements that appeared alongside the original <ref
                  type="note" target="#n1">serialized publication</ref> of Bleak House written by
               Charles Dickens and illustrated by Hablot Knight Browne. This first edition was
               published in monthly parts between 1852 and 1853 and a well preserved complete set is
               available at the Special Collections of the University of Washington Libraries. While
               the novel itself has been widely studied for its plot, characters, and social
               commentary, the ads printed in each issue are often overlooked. These advertisements
               offer a lot of information about what people were buying, what they cared about, and
               how products and services were marketed to them. From cures for illnesses to new
               inventions and fashion trends, the ads show what everyday life might have looked like
               for mid-Victorian era of London. </p>
            <p> Our approach treats each advertisement as a single unit of analysis, carefully
               examining its components such as images, product descriptions, catalogs,
               testimonials, and more. What remedies for ailments were marketed to the public 150
               years ago? Do they resemble the products sold to us today? How about their fashion,
               do some of those trends still exists today? What can these advertisements reveal
               about Victorian-era society, and how might those insights still resonate with our
               present-day culture? These are the questions we found compelling, and we hope you, as
               the reader, will find them just as intriguing. </p>
            <p> In creating this edition, our team chose to present a diplomatic transcription to
               preserve the original appearance and appeal of these advertisements as they were seen
               by the public. We maintained the original language and the layout of images alongside
               the text. In cases where words were hyphenated due to space constraints in the
               original print, we have standardized them into single words for clarity. We've also
               highlighted distinctive elements within the advertisements that we believe offer
               valuable opportunities for further analysis of print media from that era. We hope you
               enjoy this unique edition of Bleak House. </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="edmiston">
            <pb n="0"/>
            <head rend="ac">Edmiston's pocket siphonia</head>
            <p><hi rend="ac">To sportsmen, tourist, &amp; travelers.</hi>
               <graphic url="img/p0_1.png"/>
               <hi rend="ac">Edmiston's pocket siphonia</hi>, or waterproof overcoat. weight 10
                  oz.<graphic url="img/p0_2.png"/>Sole Manufacturer of the celebrated Pocket
               Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for
               Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on
               Saddle ; the most important feature in this Waterproofing is being mineralised, which
               effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also
               obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.--
               Price according to size, 40s. to 55s. ; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s.
               Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat <graphic
                  url="img/p0_3.png"/>Notice--Name &amp; address stamped inside. None others are
               genuine. Edmiston &amp; Son, 416 &amp; 69, Strand Near the Adelphi Theatre.</p>
            <p><hi rend="ac">Opinions of the press.</hi>Waterproof--<q type="testimony">The lightest
                  and most effectual, is the Siphonia, made by Edmiston &amp; Son, of 69, Strand ;
                  they can be carried in the hat or pocket.</q>-- Bell's Life, April 20th, 1851. <q
                  type="testimony">A new waterproof garment adapted to the very changeable weather
                  of the season, has been manufactured by Edmiston &amp; Son. It is remarkably light
                  and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an ingenious substitute
                  for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome umbrella.</q>--Home News, May
               24th, 1851.</p>
            <p><graphic url="img/p0_4.png"/>Leggings or Overall. Yacht Jackets. Fishing and Shooting
               Hats or Caps Driving Gloves. Cricketing do. Gun Covers. Gig Aprons. Sou-Westers.
               Goloshes.</p><p>Ladies' Capes, with Hoods. Do. Paletots. Air
               Cushions. Do. Pillows. Do. Beds. India Rubber Portable Folding Baths. Nursing Aprons.
               Crib Sheets.<graphic url="img/p0_6.png"/></p>
            <p>The newly invented Swimming Gloves, Of great propelling power. <hi rend="ac"
                  >Edmiston's life-belts none should be without.</hi>Fishing and shooting boots,
               soft and pliable, require no dressing, and every description of India Rubber and
               Gutta Percha Goods, Piping, Tubing for Watering Gardens, &amp;c. Belfast--Albion
               Cloth Company. Edinbrugh--Grieve &amp; Oliver, Princes-street. Liverpool--Radcliffe
               &amp; Corlet, Castle-street; J.H. Smith, 22, Lord-street. Shaftsbury--Jas. Seagrove,
               Brothers. Southampton--Batten &amp; Lukes. <hi rend="ac">London: Edmiston &amp; Son,
                  416 &amp; 69, Strand, near Adelphi.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="dakinCompany">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <opener><salute><name rend="ac">Chas. Dickens, Esq.</name> Sir,</salute></opener>
            <p><ref type="note" target="#n2">We thank you for your new work</ref>. Though its name
               is <q rend="ac">Bleak House,</q>we know well that its inmates will be warm and
               life-like. We thank you for it, not only for the pleasure that we, in common with all
               its other readers, shall receive in its perusal, but we thank you on more solid
               grounds; ,ve thank you for it as a matter of business.</p>
            <p>If it be true, that an observer must know of the existence of a place before he can
               arrange for visiting it, it must be equally true, that the public must be aware of
               the existence of an establishment before they can contemplate patronising it; and
               further, that they must be aware of the advantages offered by a particular concern
               before they will select that in preference to any other. On these grounds, then, we
               thank you for <q rend="ac">Bleak House</q> in a business point of view, because it
               affords us an opportunity of conveying to all its readers the advantages or our
               Establishment, and the principles upon which it continues to be conducted.</p>
            <p>Many thousands of readers have, we doubt not, entered upon their tasks since even <q
                  rend="ac"><name type="person">David Copperfield</name></q> monthly appeared,
               between his <q>green leaves,</q> and some of these readers may note with favour the
               statement we here subjoin.</p>
            <p><q>We keep for the selection of purchaser all kinds or Tea and Coffee fit for use
                  imported into this country, and we supply them at the most moderate cost at which
                  they can possibly be sold.</q></p>
            <p><q>We have endeavoured to render ourselves particularly celebrated for supplying Teas
                  of the most sound and excellent qualities.</q></p>
            <p><q>We have a Patented Invention for Roasting Coffee, Cocoa, &amp;c. in Silver. By
                  this plan the ordinary evils of roasting such produce in a cylinder made of base
                  metal are avoided, whilst the cost of the produce is not increased.</q></p>
            <p><q>We deliver by our Vans all Orders from any part of the <name type="place"
                     >Metropolitan Districts</name>, within eight miles of <name type="place">St.
                     Paul's</name>, on tho day after such orders are given.</q></p>
            <p><q>We also send into the Country, free of carriage, all Orders, if they be
                  accompanied by a remittance for payment, whether by half-notes, Post Office Order,
                  or otherwise, provided the goods ordered amount to £2 or upwards.</q></p>
            <p><q>We sell our goods only for immediate payment. Our tariff of profit is fixed
                  without allowing for the interest on capital necessary to support a heavy amount
                  of debts.</q></p>
            <p>For the facilities that this excellent medium of publicity has allowed us for making
               known the above particulars, we sincerely thank you, and we trust and hope that by
               our care and attention, and by the excellence of the Goods we supply, those readers
               of <q rend="ac">Bleak House</q> who may turn their favourable patronage to <q>Number
                  One</q>, will never regret having glanced over the first page of its white paper,
               on this 1st day of May.</p>
            <p>Wishing that you may long live to give birth to heaps of <q rend="ac">Household
                  Words</q>, and to numerous Brothers and Sisters of <q rend="ac"><name
                     type="person">David Copperfield</name>,</q></p>
            <closer><salute>We remain, Sir, Very respectfully, Your obedient Servants</salute><name
                  type="organization">Dakin &amp; Company</name><location>
                  <address>
                     <street>No. 1, St. Paul's Church-yard</street>
                     <settlement>London</settlement>
                  </address>
               </location><date when="1852-05-01">May 1st, 1852</date></closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="gardeningAndBotany">
            <pb n="2"/>
            <head>Works on Gardening and Botany.</head>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="paxtonFlowerGarden">
               <head rend="ac">Paxton's Flower-Garden.</head>
               <p rend="ac">Edited by <name type="person">Dr. Lindley</name> and <name type="person"
                     >Sir Joseph Paxton</name></p>
               <p rend="ac">Each volume is illustrated by thirty-six highly finished plates and more
                  than two hundred beautiful engravings on wood.</p>
               <p>Volumes I, and II, are published. Price 33s. each, elegantly bound in cloth.</p>
               <p>&#8757;This work is also published in Monthly Parts of which 27 are published, and
                  may be procured by order of any bookseller. Price 2s. 6d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="paxtonBotanicalDictionary">
               <head rend="ac">Paxton’s botanical dictionary.</head>
               <p>Comprising the names, history, and culture of all plants known in <name
                     type="place">Britain</name>; with a full explanation of technical terms. Crown
                  8vo, 16s.</p>
               <p>&#8757;The supplement, containing all the new plants since the first edition, may
                  be had separately, price 5s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theElementsOfBotany">
               <head rend="ac">The elements of botany;</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">Structural and physiological.</p>
               <p>With a glossary of technical terms, and numerous illustrations. By <name rend="ac"
                     type="person">Dr. Lindley</name>. 12s. cloth.</p>
               <p>&#8757;The glossary may be had separately, price 5s. cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="elementsOfMedAndEconBotany">
               <head rend="ac">The elements of medical and economical botany.</head>
               <p>By <name rend="ac" type="person">Dr. Lindley</name>. With numerous illustrations.
                  8vo, price 14s. cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="schoolBotany">
               <head>School botany;</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">Or, the rudiments of botanical science.</p>
               <p>By <name rend="ac" type="person">Dr. Lindley</name>.</p>
               <p>With nearly 400 illustrations. 8vo, price 5s. 6d. half-bound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="orchidaceae">
               <head rend="ac">Orchidaceæ Lindenianæ</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">Or notes upon a collection of orchids formed in Colombia and
                  Cuba.</p>
               <p>By <name rend="ac" type="person">Mr. J. Linden</name>. 8vo, price 2s. 6d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="ladiesCompanionFlowerGarden">
               <head rend="ac">The ladies’ companion to the flower-garden.</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">Being an alphabetical arrangement of all the ornamental plants
                  grown in gardens and shrubberies, with full directions for their culture.</p>
               <p rend="ac">By <name>Mrs. Loudon</name>.</p>
               <p>The fifth edition. Price 7s. cloth, with numerous woodcuts representing the
                  processes of grafting, budding, layering, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="howToLayOutASmallGarden">
               <head rend="ac">How to lay out a small garden.</head>
               <p>Intended as a guide to amateurs in choosing, forming, or improving a place (from a
                  quarter of an acre to thirty acres in extent), with reference to both design and
                  execution.</p>
               <p><seg rend="ac">By <name type="person">Edward Kemp</name></seg>, landscape
                  gardener, <name type="place">Birkenhead Park</name>. Price 3s. 6d., bound in
                  cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theHandbookOfGardening">
               <head rend="ac">The hand-book of gardening.</head>
               <p rend="ac">By the same author.</p>
               <p>A new edition, enlarged and improved. Price to 2s. cloth.</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="ac">
               <p><location>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>Bradbury and Evans</addrLine>
                        <street>11, Bouverie Street</street>
                     </address>
                  </location></p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="waverleyNovels">
            <pb n="3"/>
            <head rend="ac">The Waverley Novels,</head>
            <p rend="subtitle">Vol. I of a new library edition, uniform with the standard English
               authors of,</p>
            <p rend="ac">By Sir Walter Scott, Bart.</p>
            <p>Just published, in Demy 8vo., price nine shillings,</p>
            <p>With frontispiece, by John Faed, R.S.A., Engraved by L. Stocke, and Vignette, by
               Birket Foster, Engraved by W. Forest</p>
            <p rend="ac">To be completed in twenty-five monthly volumes.</p>
            <p>No works of imagination of the same extent have ever been received with so great
               favour as the <hi rend="ac">Waverley novels</hi>.</p>
            <p>Since their first publication that fewer than a <hi rend="ac">hundred and twenty
                  thousand copies</hi> have been sold in this country, and at least as many in the
               United states. These have been published in a great variety of modes to suit the
               tastes of the public; but there has been long wanted an Edition in the octavo form,
               to range with the Standard English Authors, combining the advantages of a large type
               and portable size. This desiteratum it is proposed to supply by means of this series,
               denominated the <hi rend="ac bold">library edition</hi>, which will consist of <hi
                  rend="ac">twenty-five volumes</hi>, demy 8vo., to be published Monthly. The
               printing, however, will proceed more rapidly, so that those who desire to complete
               their Sets before the termination of the periodical issue, will have an opportunity
               of doing so a considerable time before the <hi rend="italics">regular</hi>
               publication of the last volume.</p>
            <p>Each volume will contain a complete novel or novels, illustrated with the
               Frontispiece and Vignette, painted and engraved by the most eminent artists of the
               day. The <hi rend="ac">library edition</hi> will contain all the latest corrections
               of the Author. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="elementsOfStructuralBotany">
            <head rend="ac">Elements of structural botany,</head>
            <p rend="subtitle">forming part I. of a new botanical class book</p>
            <p rend="ac">by J. H. Balfour, M.D., F.R.S.E., Professor of botany in the University of
               Edinburgh.</p>
            <p rend="ac">Just published, in demy octavo, with 1060 illustrations, price 10s. 6d.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="theLifeOfLordJeffrey">
            <head rend="ac">The life of lord Jeffrey,</head>
            <p rend="subtitle">with a selection from his correspondence.</p>
            <p rend="ac">By Lord Cockburn.</p>
            <p rend="ac">in two volumes, demy octavo, price 25s.</p>
            <p rend="ac">Edinburgh: Adam &amp; Charles Black. London: Longman &amp; Co.; Simpkin
               &amp; Co.; Hamilton &amp; Co.; and Houlston &amp; Stoneman.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="colburn">
            <pb n="4"/>
            <head rend="ac">Colburn and Co.'s new publications.</head>
            <p rend="ac">13, Great Marlborough Street</p>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theLifeOfMarieDeMedicis">
               <head rend="ac">The Life of Marie de Medicis,</head>
               <p>Queen of France, Consort of Henry IV., and Regent of the Kingdom under Louis XIII.
                     <hi rend="ac">By Miss Pardok</hi>, Author of "Louis XIV. and the Court of
                  France," &amp;c. 3 vols., with Portraits, &amp;c. (<hi rend="italics"
                     >Immediately</hi>).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theLiteratureAndRomanceOfNorthEurope">
               <head rend="ac">The literature and romance of Northern Europe,</head>
               <p>With copious Specimens. <hi rend="ac">By William and Mary Howitt</hi>. 2 vols.
                  21s.</p>
               <p><q type="testimony">A work replete with interest to the scholar, the philosopher,
                     the antiquarian, and the general reader.</q> --<hi rend="italics"
                  >Post</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="fiveyearsInTheWestIndies">
               <head rend="ac">Five years in the West Indies.</head>
               <p>By <hi rend="ac">Charles W. Day</hi>, Esq. 2 vols. with illustrations, 21s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="canada">
               <head rend="ac">Canada as it was, is, and may be;</head>
               <p>With an account of recent transactions, by Sir <hi rend="ac">James E.
                     Alexander</hi>. 2 vols., with Map, &amp;c., 21s.</p>
               <p><q type="testimony">A very valuable and interesting work.</q> --<hi rend="italics"
                     >John Bull</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="adamGraeme">
               <head rend="ac">Adam Graeme of Mossgray.</head>
               <p>A new story of Scottish life. By the Author of <q>Maragaret Maitland,</q>
                  <q>Merkland,</q> and <q>Caleb Field.</q> 3 vols.</p>
               <p><q type="testimony">A story awakening genuine emotions of interest and delight, by
                     its admirable pictures of Scottish life and scenery.</q> --<hi rend="italics"
                     >Morning Post</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="aurelia">
               <head>Aurelia. A novel</head>
               <p>3 vols.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="thePerilsOfFashion">
               <head>The perils of fashion.</head>
               <p>3 vols. <q type="testimony">A highly entertaining and popular novel. The world of
                     fashion is here painted by an artist who has studied closely, and traces its
                     lineaments with a mastery hand.</q> --<hi rend="italics">Post</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="confessionsOfAnEtonian">
               <head>Confessions of an Etonian.</head>
               <p>By <hi rend="ac">Charles Rowcroft</hi>, Esq., Author of <q>Tales of the
                     Colonies,</q> &amp;c. 3 vols.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="aNewNovelByMrsGrey">
               <head>A new novel by Mrs. Grey,</head>
               <p>Author of <q>The Gambler's Wife,</q> &amp;c., is just ready in 3 vols.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="carpentersArithmeticNewEd">
               <head rend="ac">Carpenter's (T.) Arithmetic.</head>
               <p><hi rend="ac">New edition. By W. Rutherford, Esq.</hi> Price, bound in cloth, 1s.
                  6d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="carpentersArithmetic">
               <head rend="ac dropcap">Carpenter's arithmetic:</head>
               <p>designed for the use of Schools, by <hi rend="ac">Thomas Carpenter</hi>, Author of
                     <q>The Scholar's Spelling Assistant,</q> New Edition, carefully corrected and
                  considerably enlarged. By <hi rend="ac">W. Rutherford, LL.D., F.R.A.S.,</hi> Royal
                  Military Academy, Woolwich.</p>
               <p>London: <hi rend="ac">William Tego &amp; Co.,</hi> 85, Queen-street,
                  Cheapside.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="mudies">
               <head>Mudie's select library.</head>
               <p><hi rend="ac dropcap">One hundred and fifty copies</hi> of the <hi rend="ac"
                     >Life</hi> of <hi rend="ac">Lord Jeffrey</hi>, and a proportionate supply of
                  every other good new Work, are in circulation at <hi rend="ac">Mudie's select
                     library,</hi> 510 New Oxford Street, and 20, Museum Street, removed from 28,
                  Upper King Street, Bloomsburry Square.--Single subscription, one guinea per annum.
                  First class country susbscription, two guineas and upwards, according to the
                  number of volumes required.--For further prospectuses apply to <hi rend="ac"
                     >Charles Edward Mudie</hi>, 510, New Oxford Street.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theDaysOfBruce">
               <head rend="ac">The days of Bruce:</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">A story from a Scottish history.</p>
               <p rend="ac">By Grace Aguilar,</p>
               <p>New work by the Author of <q>Home Influence.</q> On the 6th day of May, in one
                  vol., illustrated with frontispiece and vignette title, price 7s., 6d.,</p>
               <p>Author of <q>Home Influence,</q>
                  <q>The Mother's Recompense,</q>
                  <q>Women's Friendship,</q>
                  <q>The Vale of Cedars,</q> &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
               <p rend="ac">London: Groombridge &amp; Sons, 5, Paternoster row.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="leFollet">
               <head>Le Follet.-- Important and valuable gratuity.</head>
               <p><hi rend="ac dropcap">With</hi> the <hi rend="ac">May</hi> number of <q rend="ac"
                     >Le Follet</q> Journal du Grande Monde, will be presented, <hi rend="ac"
                     >gratis</hi>, a beautifully coloured Steele Plate Engraver, representing all
                  the newest styles for jackets, waistcoats, caps, sleeves, &amp;c. Also, three
                  coloured plates of ladies' fashions, designed and executed in the first style of
                  art. <hi rend="ac">La mode</hi> for the month, translated from the French, and
                  eight pages of literary matter. The new Law of International Copyright will
                  prevent contemporaneous works from printing the designs of <hi rend="ac">Le
                     Follet</hi>.</p>
               <p><q type="testimony">No comparison whatever can be drawn between it and its
                     numerous predecessors.</q> --<hi rend="italics">Sun</hi>.</p>
               <p><q type="testimony"><hi rend="ac">Le Follet</hi> must eclipse all other works
                     devoted to the dresses of ladies</q> --<hi rend="italics">Weekly
                  Despatch</hi>.</p>
               <p><q type="testimony">No plates comparable to these have ever been issued for the
                     same purpose. They elevate dress to its proper station among the fine arts.</q>
                     --<hi rend="italics">Britannia</hi>.</p>
               <p>Single numbers, 1s. 6d. each; Subscription, 16s. per year. Office, 9,
                  Argyle-place. <hi rend="ac">Simpkin, Marshall, &amp; Co.</hi>, and all
                  booksellers.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="p5newWorks">
            <pb n="5"/>
            <head rend="ac">New works.</head>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theStoryOfNellGwyn">
               <head rend="ac">The story of Nell Gwyn</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">And the sayings of King Charles II.</p>
               <p>Related and collected by <hi rend="ac">Peter Cunningham, F.S.A</hi></p>
               <p rend="italics">This day is published, in crown octavo, price 6s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="howToSeeTheBritishMuseum">
               <head rend="ac">How to see the British Museum.</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">In four visits.</p>
               <p rend="ac">By William Blanchard Jerrold.</p>
               <p rend="italics">Complete in one volume, price 2s. 6d., bound in cloth,</p>
               <p><q type="testimony">As a Guide-book through the vast collection it will be prized
                     for the simplicity of its arrangement, and the clearness of its style.</q>
                     --<hi rend="italics">Leader</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theComicHistoryOfRome">
               <head rend="ac">The comic history of Rome.</head>
               <p rend="ac">By G. A. A'Beckett.</p>
               <p rend="italics">In one volume 8vo, price 11s., illustrated with ten large coloured
                  engravings and numerous woodcuts by <hi rend="ac">John Leech</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theComicHistoryOfEngland">
               <head rend="ac">The comic history of England.</head>
               <p rend="ac">Illustrated with twenty coloured engravings and numerous woodcuts, by
                  John Leech.</p>
               <p rend="italics">By the same author, in two vols., 8vo, price 21s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="writingsOfDouglassJerrold">
               <head rend="ac">The third volume of the collected edition of the writings of Douglass
                  Jerrold.</head>
               <p>Containing <q rend="ac">Mrs. Caudle's lectures,</q> the <q rend="ac">Story of
                     feather,</q> and <q rend="ac">The sick giant and the doctor dwarf.</q></p>
               <p rend="italics">This day is published, price 4s. in cloth</p>
               <p>&#8757; These works are also publishing in weekly numbers, price 11d. each, and in
                  monthly parts, price 7d. each.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="proseAndVerse">
               <head rend="ac">Prose and verse.</head>
               <p rend="ac">By Mark Lemon.</p>
               <p rend="italics">Price 4s., in cloth boards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theEnchantedDoll">
               <head rend="ac">The enchanted doll.</head>
               <p rend="subtitle">A fairy tale for young people.</p>
               <p>Illustrated by <hi rend="ac">Richard Doyle.</hi></p>
               <p rend="italics">By the same author, 3s. 6d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="whatShallWeHaveForDinner">
               <head rend="ac">What shall we have for dinner?</head>
               <p rend="ac">By Lady Maria Clutterbuck.</p>
               <p rend="italics">Price 1s. A new edition enlarged and improved.</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="ac">
               <p><location>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>Bradbury and Evans</addrLine>
                        <street>11, Bouverie Street</street>
                     </address>
                  </location></p>
            </div>

         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="childsHistoryEngland">
            <pb n="9"/>
            <head><hi rend="ac hugeFont">A Child's History of England</hi></head>
            <p rend="ac"><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="bigFont">The first volume of</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="hugeFont">A Child's History of England</hi><lb/><hi rend="bigFont">By
                           <persName><forename>Charles</forename>
                        <surname>Dickens</surname></persName>.</hi>With a frontispiece from a
                  drawing by <persName>F. W. <surname>Topham</surname></persName>Corrected and
                  revised from "Household Words," with a table of dates</hi></p>
            <p>Price 3s, neatly bound in cloth</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">The History will be competed in Three Volumes of the same size
                  and price.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="ac">Bradbury and Evans, 11, Bouverie Street</hi></p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="magnallQuestions">
            <head><hi rend="ac"><persName><surname>Mangnall</surname></persName>'s questions, by
                        <persName><surname>Guy</surname></persName> and
                        <persName><surname>Wright</surname></persName></hi></head>
            <p>With an Historical Frontispiece and Envgravings. New Edition corrected to the Present
               Time, by <persName>Joseph Guy</persName>, Jun., of
                     <persName><surname>Magdalen</surname></persName> Hall, Oxford, Author of the
               "Juvenile Letter Writer," &amp;c. 12mo, roan. Price 4s. 6s.</p>
            <p><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap">H</hi>istorical and
                  Miscel</hi><lb/>aneous Questions</hi> for the Use of Young People, with a
               Selection of British and General Biography, &amp;c., by <persName>R.
                     <surname>Mangnall</surname></persName>. Adapted for the USe of Schools, by
                     <persName><roleName>Rev</roleName>. G. N.
                     <surname><surname>Wright</surname></surname></persName>. A New Edition,
               corrected to the Present Time, by <persName><forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname>Guy</surname></persName>, Jun. Illustrated with a New Historical
               Frontispiece, and many <hi rend="italics">New Engravings</hi>.</p>
            <p>London: <hi rend="sc"><persName><forename>William</forename>
                     <surname>Tegg</surname></persName></hi> &amp; Co, <address>
                  <street>85, Queen-street, Cheapside.</street>
               </address></p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="educationalTrusts">
            <head rend="bigFont">Educational Trusts.</head>
            <p><hi rend="ac">Free Boys</hi>
               <hi rend="italics">versus</hi>
               <hi rend="ac">Boarders;<lb/>or,<lb/>Free school revelations.</hi></p>
            <p>On the 1st. of May will be published, price One Shilling, the First Number of the
               Free Schools of Worcestershire. By <hi rend="sc"
                        ><persName><forename>George</forename>
                     <surname>Griffith</surname></persName></hi>, of Kidderminster. To be completed
               in about Eight Numbers.</p>
            <p>London: <hi rend="sc"><persName><forename>Charles</forename>
                     <surname>Gilfin</surname></persName></hi>. Dublin: <hi rend="sc">J.B.
                     <surname>Gilfin</surname></hi>. Edinburgh: A. &amp; C. <hi rend="sc"
                     ><surname>Black</surname></hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="instructionsForConcertina">
            <head><hi rend="ac bigFont">Instructions for the Concertina</hi></head>
            <p>Just Published,<lb/><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap"
                     >I</hi>nstructions for the Con<lb/></hi>certina</hi> by <hi rend="ac"
                        ><persName><forename>Carlo</forename>
                     <surname>Minasi</surname></persName></hi>, 42 pp. folio, 5s. The Third Edition
               (enlarged) of <hi rend="ac">Warren's Complete Instructions for the concertina</hi>,
               10s. 6d.</p>
            <p><hi rend="ac">Instructions for the harmonium</hi>, by <hi rend="ac"
                        ><persName><forename>Joseph</forename>
                     <surname>Warren</surname></persName></hi>, 4s. Also, suitable for the same <hi
                  rend="ac"><persName><surname>Lindley</surname></persName>'s practical introduction
                  to the organ</hi>, a New Eidtion, revised and enlarged by <persName>J. <hi
                     rend="ac"><surname>Warren</surname></hi>; containing 41 Preludes, Introductary,
                  Middle, and Full Voluntaries, and 37 Psalm Tunes with Interludes, 128pp., oblong
                  8vo, 5s.</persName></p>
            <p>Messrs. <hi rend="ac">Wheatstone &amp; Co.</hi>, Investors, and Patentees of the
               Concertina, <address>
                  <street>29, Conduit-street, Regent-street</street>
               </address>, where may be had a Descriptive Prospectus of the Ten Guinea
               Harmonium.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="memorialsFromBen">
            <head><hi rend="ac bigFont">Memorials From
                        <persName><forename>Ben</forename><surname>Rhydding</surname></persName></hi></head>
            <p>Just published, crown 5vo, price 5s., with 6 Engravings and numerous Woodcuts,
               elegantly bound.</p>
            <p><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap">M</hi>emorials From
                           <persName><forename>Ben</forename></persName></hi><lb/><persName><surname>Rhydding</surname></persName>,
                  concerning the place, its people, </hi>and <hi rend="ac">its cures.</hi></p>
            <p>"This is the most handsome and well-embellished volume ever laid upon our table. * *
               * Besides much that is entertaining, it gives the only real scientific view of the
               water cure that we have met with, and presents it in a light that cannot fail to
               commend it to every unprejudiced mind. The work is published from a sense of benefits
               recieved and a desire to enlighted the community." -<hi rend="italics">British
                  Friend</hi>.</p>
            <p>London: <persName><forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname>Gilpin</surname></persName>, 5, Bishopsgate Without.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="schewppesSoda">
            <head><hi rend="ac bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap">S</hi>cheweppe's Soda, Potas,</hi></head>
            <p>and <hi rend="ac">Magnesia Waters</hi> and <hi rend="ac">Aerated Lemonade</hi>
               continue to be manufactured upon the largest scale at their several Establishments in
               London, Liverpool, Bristol, and Derby. The celebrity of these well-known waters and
               the preference they universally command, are evidence that their original superior
               quality over all others is well sustained. Every bottle is protected by a label with
               the name of their firm, without which none is genuine, and it may be had of nearly
               all respectable chemists throughout the kingdon. Importers of the German Selters
               Water direct from the springs, as for the last twenty years.</p>
            <p><hi rend="medFont"><address>
                     <street>51, Berners Street, London</street>
                  </address></hi></p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="toiletOfBeauty">
            <head><hi rend="ac bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>he Toilet of Beauty</hi></head>
            <p>furnishes innumerable proofs of the high estimation in which <hi rend="ac">Gowland's
                  Lotion</hi> is held by the most distinguished possessors of brilliant complexions.
               This elegant preperation comprehends the preservation of the complexion both from the
               effects of cutaneous malady and the operation of variable temperature, by refreshing
               its delicacy and sustaining the brightest tints with which beauty is adorned.
                     "<persName><forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname>Shaw</surname></persName>, London" is in white letters on the Government
               stamp of the genuine. Prices, 2s. 9d. and 5s. 6d. ; quarts, 8s. 6d.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="gerardsCelebratedPomade">
            <head><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap">G</hi>erard's
                     Celebrated</hi><hi rend="medFont">Pomade for the hair.</hi></hi></head>
            <p>Superior to all nominally-styled restoratives, as <hi rend="italics">Bears' Grease,
                  Creams, Oils, Estracts, &amp;c., &amp;c. ;</hi> eradicates scurf and dandriff;
               thoroughly cleanses and renders the hair peculiarly soft and luxuriant, without the
               greasy clamminess so greatly complained of in similar articles. IN cases of premature
               baldness, from whatever cause, it will be found a complete resotrative. The inventor
               does not assert that it will reproduce hair after falling off from declining years,
               but garantees that it will greatly prevent it. It is particularly recommended to
               sufferers from an Eastern climate. To be procured only at <address>
                  <street>399, Strand</street>
               </address>, London, in Pots, 2s. each.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="hollowaysPills">
            <head><hi rend="ac bigFont"><persName><surname><hi rend="dropcap"
                        >H</hi>olloway</surname></persName>'s Pills,</hi></head>
            <p><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="medFont">A Most</hi><lb/>efficient</hi>
               <hi rend="sc">remedy for bile, indigestion, and debilitated cocnstitutions.-</hi>The
               extraordinary powers of this medicine in curing disorders of the stomach, bile,
               indigestion, and liver complaints are wonderful. Thousands whose lives were a burden
               to them whilst suffering from these complaints are now enjoying the best of health by
               taking these invaluable pills, and now strongly recommend their use to others
               similarly afflicted. A few doses give relief, and a continuance of them for a short
               time effects a perfect cure. Persons whose constitutions have been weakened by long
               residence in hot climates cannot have a more certain remedy to restore them to robust
               health than <persName><surname>Holloway</surname></persName>'s Pills.- Sold by all
               Druggists, and at <persName><roleName>Professor</roleName>
                  <surname>Holloway</surname></persName>'s Establishment, <address>
                  <street>244, Strand</street>
               </address>, London</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="rowlandsMacassarOil">
            <pb n="10"/>
            <head rend="ac bigFont"><persName><surname>Rowlands</surname></persName>' Macassar
               Oil</head>
            <p><hi rend="ac bigFont"><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>his elegant, fragrant,</hi>
               <hi rend="medFont">and</hi>
               <hi rend="ac bigFont">pellucid oil</hi><hi rend="medFont">, in its <hi
                     rend="italics">preservative,</hi></hi> restorative, and <hi rend="italics"
                  >beautifying</hi> qualities for the Human Hair, is unequalled over the whole
               world. It <hi rend="italics">preserves</hi> and <hi rend="italics"
                  >reproduces</hi> the <hi rend="italics">hair</hi>, prevents it from <hi
                  rend="italics">turning grey</hi>; frees it from <hi rend="italics"
                  >scurf</hi> and <hi rend="italics">impurity</hi> and renders it <hi
                  rend="italics">soft, silky, curly</hi>, and <hi rend="italics"
               >glossy</hi>.</p>
            <p><graphic url="../img/p0_7.png"/><hi rend="ac">Caution.</hi>- A. R. and Sons have
               complaints repeatedly from parties who have materially suffered from the use of
               spurious imitations; and to frusterate to some extent such impositions, they here
               added a small copy in outline of their genuine label from the burin of <hi rend="ac"
                        ><persName><surname>Messers</surname></persName>,
                        <persName><surname>Perkins</surname></persName>,
                        <persName><surname>Bacon</surname></persName>, &amp;
                        <persName><surname>Petch</surname></persName></hi>, the eminent engravers of
               London, on which will be seen the names and addresses of the Propietors in full
               (these are in red ink on the label), any deviation from which will always prove a
               spurious article.</p>
            <p>The prices are 3s. 6d. ; 7s.; family bottles (equal to four small) 10s. 6d.; and
               double that size 12s. Sold by the Propietors, and by Chemists and Perfumers.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="royalBankBuildings">
            <head><hi rend="medFont">Royal Bank Buildings,</hi><lb/><hi rend="ac medFont"><hi
                     rend="bold">Liverpool</hi></hi>, <date when="1882">1882</date></head>
            <p><hi rend="ac"><hi rend="dropcap">W</hi>e</hi> did not feel justified, until the month
               of <hi rend="ac"><date when="--02">February</date></hi> of the present year, in
               recommending this season's imports of Black Teas, the quality of the earlier arrivals
               having confessedly been much inferior to those former years. This is attributed to
               the continued rains which have prevailed in some parts of the Tea districts in China,
               owing to which the crops have considerably deteriorated.</p>
            <p>Our delay, in order to see the results of a <hi rend="italics">general
                  imporation</hi> has already proved most beneficial to the interest of our
               Connexion. Watchfulness and judgement, exercised in the <hi rend="italics"
                  >selection qualities</hi>, wlil we think, be more than usually appriciated this
               year. With this conviction, we particularly refer <hi rend="italics">Family
                  Purchasers</hi> to the following quotations from our general list of prices.</p>
            <p><hi rend="medfont indented">Fine Congou, Souchong kind . . . . . . <hi
                     rend="left-align">3s. 6d.</hi></hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="medfont centered">Strong Congou, Pekoe Souchong kind . . . . <hi
                     rend="left-align">3s. 9d.</hi></hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="medfont centered">First Class Congou, . . Rich Pekoe Sou. flavor <hi
                     rend="left-align">4s. 0d.</hi></hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="medfont centered">The Extra Fine . . . (Very Ripe Pekoe flavor)<hi
                     rend="left-align"> 4s. 4d.</hi></hi></p>
            <p>The <hi rend="sc">first cost</hi> of good and choice kinds being unusually
               reasonable, at the same time, there is an increasing demand for the commonest <hi
                  rend="sc">black tea</hi>.- This indicates that- <hi rend="sc">cheapness</hi>- is
               more regarded by many Dealers than <hi rend="sc">quality</hi>- Disappointment is the
               necessary consequence to <hi rend="sc">families</hi> whose supplies are derived from
               parties not possessing the requisite advantage in Selection and Purchase.</p>
            <p>-- The present moderate rate of <hi rend="italics">Carriage of Parcels by
                  Railway</hi>, affords to Families in the Country facilities for obtaining their
               supplies without material additional expense. Whenever desired, we <hi
                  rend="italics">pre-pay the Carriage</hi> of parcels, including the charge in the
               invoice.</p>
            <p>-- Some parties offer to defray the carriage; we take the better alternative, by
                  <hi rend="italics">sending</hi>
               <hi rend="ac">a superior quality of tea, at a price</hi><hi rend="italics"> which
                  must tend to secure further transactions.--</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">"This Branch of our Trade- the serving of Families with Tea and
                  Coffee- was opened in <date when="1810">1810</date>, upon a principle calculated
                  to afford the greatest advantage in Price, with every possible security as to
                  Quality.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="medFont bold">Bankers.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="centered medFont">The <hi rend="sc">Br,</hi>
                  <hi rend="ac">Bank of England</hi></hi>.....................<hi rend="dropCap"
                  >}</hi>.......... <hi rend="italics">Liverpool</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="centered medFont"> ,, <hi rend="ac">Royal
               Bank</hi></hi>..........................</p>
            <p><hi rend="centered medFont"> ,, <hi rend="ac">British
               Bank</hi></hi>.................................. <hi rend="italics"
               >London.</hi>..</p>
            <p><hi rend="centered medFont"> ,, <hi rend="ac">Bank of
               Ireland</hi></hi>............................ <hi rend="italics"
               >Dublin.</hi>..</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Amounts paid into any of these Banking Houses, on our account,
                  adising us of the same, will be duly passed to credit, and acknowledged, without
                  charge for Banker's Commission.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bigFont">Rob<hi rend="superscript">T</hi> Roberts &amp; Comp<hi
                     rend="superscript">Y</hi></hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sc">Royal Bank Building</hi> (<hi rend="italics">Enterance up the
                  Steps</hi>),</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold bigFont">Liverpool.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="nortonPills">
            <pb n="58"/>
            <head><hi rend="ac hugeFont">Important Family Medicine</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="ac bold hugeFont">Norton's Camomile Pills,</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac medFont">The<lb/> most certain preserver of health; </hi><hi
                  rend="sc">A<lb/> mild, yet speedy, safe, and<lb/></hi><hi
                  rend="ac bold medFont">Effectual Aid in cases of indigestion,<lb/> And all stomach
                  complaints,<lb/>
               </hi><hi rend="sc">And, as a natural consequence,</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc medFont">A purifier of the blood, and a sweetener of the whole
                  system.</hi><lb/> Indigestion is a weakness or want of power of the digestive
               juices in the stomach to convert what we eat and drink into healthy matter, for the
               proper nourishment of the whole system. It is caused by every thing which weakens the
               system in general, or the stomach in particular. From it proceed nearly all diseases
               to which we are liable; for it is very certain, that if we could always keep the
               stomach right we should only die by old age or accident. Indigestion produces a great
               variety of unpleasant sensations: amongst the prominent of its miserable effects are
               a want of, or an inordinate, appetite, sometimes attended with a constant craving for
               drink, a distension or feeling enlargement of the stomach, flatulency, heartburn,
               pains in the stomach, acidity, unpleasant taste in the mouth, perhaps sickness,
               rumbling noise in the bowels: in some cases of depraved digestions there is nearly a
               complete disrelish for food, but still the appetite is not greatly impaired, as at
               the stated period of meals persons so afflicted can eat heartily, although without
               much gratification; a long train of nervous symptoms are also frequent attendants,
               general debility, great languidess, and incapacity for exertion. The minds of persons
               so afflicted frequently become irraitable and desponding, and great anxiety is
               observable in the countenance; they appear thoughtful, melancholy, and dejected,
               under great apprehension of some imaginary danger, will start at any unexpected noise
               or occurrence, and become so agitated that they require some time to calm and collect
               themselves; yet for all this the mind is exhilarated without much difficulty;
               pleasing events, society, will for a time dissipate all appearance of disease; but
               the excitement produced by an agreeable change vanishes soon after the cause has gone
               by. Other symptoms are, voilent palpitations, restlessness, the sleep disturbed by
               frightful dreams and startings, and affording little or no refreshment: occasionally
               there is much moaning, with a sense of weight and oppression upon the chest,
               nightmare, &amp;c.<lb/> It is almost impossible to enumerate all the symptoms of this
               first invader upon the constitution, as in a hundred cases of <hi rend="ital"
                  >Indigestion</hi> there will probably be something peculiar to each; but, be
               they what they may, they are all occassioned by the food becoming a burden rather
               than a support to the stomach; and in all its stages the medicine most wanted is that
               which will afford speedy and effectual assistance to the digestive organs, and give
               energy to the nervous and muscular systems,-nothing can more speedily or with more
               certainty effect so desirable an object than <hi rend="ital">Norton's Extract of
                  Camomile Flowers</hi>. The herb has from time immemorial been highly esteemed in
               England as a grateful anodyne, imparting an aromatic bitter to the taste, and a
               pleasing degree of warmth and strength to the stomach; and in all cases of
               indigestion, gout in the stomach, windy colic, and general weakness, it has for ages
               been strongly recommended by the most eminent practitioners as very useful and
               beneficial. The great, indeed only, objection to its use has been the large quantity
               of water which it takes to dissolve a small part of the flowers and which must be
               taken with it into the<pb n="59"/><fw type="page_number" place="top_right">2</fw>
               stomach. It requires a quarter of a pint of boiling water to dissolve the soluble
               portion of one drachm of camomile flowers; and, when one or even two ounces may be
               taken with advantage, it must at once be seen how impossible it is to take a proper
               dose of this wholesome herb in the form of tea; and the only reason why it has not
               long since been placed the very first in rank of all restorative medicines is that in
               taking it the stomach has always been loaded with water which tends in a great
               measure to counteract, and very frequently wholly to destroy the effect. It must be
               evident that loading a weak stomach with a large purpose of conveying into it a small
               quantity of medicine must be injurious; and that the medicines must possess powerful
               renovating properties only to counteract the bad effects likely to be produced by the
               water. Generally speaking, this has been the case with camomile flowers, a herb
               possessing the highest restorative qualities, and when properly taken, decidedly the
               most speedy restorer, and the most certain preserver of health.<lb/> These <hi
                  rend="sc"> pills</hi> are wholly <hi rend="sc">camomile</hi>, prepared by a
               peculiar process, accidentally discovered, and known only to the proprietor, and
               which he firmly believes to be one of the most valuable modern discoveries in
               medicine, by which all the essential and extractice matter of more than an ounce of
               the flowers is concentrated in four moderate-sized pills. Experience has afforded the
               most ample proof that they possess all the fine aromatic and stomachic properties for
               which the herb has been esteemed; and, as they are taken into the stomach
               unencumbered by any diluting or indigestible substance, in the same degree has their
               enefit been more immediate and decided. Mild in their operation and pleasant in their
               effect, they may be taken at any age, and under any circumstance, without danger or
               inconvenience. A person exposed to cold and wet a whole day or night could not
               possibly receive any injury from taking them, but, on the contrary, they would
               effectually prevent a cold being taken. After a long acquaintance with and strict
               observance of the medicinal properties of <hi rend="ital">Norton's Camomile
                  Pills</hi>, it is only doing them justice to say, that they are really the most
               valuable of all <hi rend="sc">tonic medicines</hi>. By the word tonic is meant a
               medicine which gives strength to the stomach sufficient to digest in proper
               quantities all wholesome food, which increases the power of every nerve and muscle of
               the human body, or, in other words, invigorates the nervous and muscular systems. The
               solidity or firmness of the whole tissue of the body which so quickly follows the use
               of <hi rend="ital">Norton's Camomile Pills</hi>, their certain and speedy effects
               in repairing the partial dilapidations from time or intemperance, and their lasting
               salutary in fluence on the whole frame, is most con vincing, that in the smallest
               compass is contained the largest quantity of the tonic principle, of so peculiar a
               nature as to pervade the whole system, through which it diffuses health and strength
               sufficient to resist the formation of disease, and also to fortify the consitution
               against contagion; as such, their general use is strongly recommended as a
               preventative during the prevalence of malignant fever or other infectious diseases,
               and to persons attending sick rooms they are invaluable as in no one instance have
               they ever failed in preventing the taking of illness, even under the most trying
               circumstances.<lb/> As <hi rend="ital"> Norton's Camomile Pills</hi> are
               particularly recommended for all stomach complaints or indigestion, it will probably
               be expected that some advice should be given respecting diet, though after all that
               has been written upon the subject, after the publication of volume upon volume, after
               the country has, as it were, been inundated with practical essays on diet, as a means
               of prolonging life, it would be unnecessary to say more, did we not feel it our duty
               to make the humble endeavor of inducing the public to regard them not, but to adopt
               that course which is dictated by nature, by reason, and common sense. Those persons
               who study the wholesomes, and are governed by the opinions of writers on diet, are
               uniformly both unhealthy in body and weak in mind. There can be no doubt that the
               palate is designed to inform us what is proper for the stomach, and of course that
               must best instruct us what food to take and what to avoid: we want no other adviser.
               Nothing can be more clear than that those articles which are agreeable to the taste
               were by nature intended for our food and sustenance, whether liquid or solid, foreign
               or of native production: if they are pure and unadulterated, no harm need be dreaded
               by their<pb n="60"/><fw type="page_number" place="top_right">3</fw> use; they will
               only injure by abuse. Consequently, whatever the palate approves, eat and drink
               always in moderation, but never in excess; keeping in mind that the first process of
               digestion is performed in the mouth, the second in the stomach; and that, in order
               that the stomach may be able to do its work properly, it is requisite the first
               should be well performed; this consists in masticating or chewing the solid food, so
               as to break down and separate the fibres and small substances of meat and vegetables,
               mixing them well, and blending the whole together before they are swallowed; and it
               is particularly urged upon all to take plenty of time to their meals and never eat in
               haste. If you conform to this short and simple, but comprehensive advice, and find
               that there are various things which others eat and drink with pleasure and without
               inconvenience, and which would be pleasant to yourself only that they disagree, you
               may at once conclude that the fault is in the stomach, that it does not possess the
               power which it ought to do, that it wants assistance, and the sooner that assistance
               is afforded the better. A very short trial of this medicine will best prove how soon
               it will put the stomach in a condition to perform with ease all the work which nature
               intended for it. By its use you will soon be able to enjoy, in moderation, whatever
               is agreeable to the taste, and unable to name one individual article of food which
               disagrees with or sits unpleasantly on the stomach. Never forget that a small meal
               well digested affords more nourishment to the system than a large one, even of the
               same food, when digested imperfectly. Let the dish be ever so delicious, ever so
               enticing a variety offered, the bottle ever so enchanting, never forget that
               temperance tends to preserve health, and that health is the soul of enjoyment. But
               should an impropriety be at any time, or ever so often, committed, by which the
               stomach becomes overloaded or disordered, render it immediate aid by taking a dose of
                  <hi rend="ital">Norton's Camomile Pills</hi>, which will so promtly assist in
               carrying off the burden thus imposed upon it that all will soon be right again.<lb/>
               It is most certainly true that every person in his lifetime consumes a quantity of
               noxious matter, which if taken at one meal would be fatal; it is these small
               quantities of noxious matter, which are introduced into our food, either by accident
               or wilful adulteration, which we find so often upset the stomach, and not
               unfrequently lay the foundation of illness, and perhaps final ruination to health. To
               preserve the constitution, it should be our constant care, if possible, to counteract
               the effect of these small quantities of unwholesome matter; and whenever, in that
               way, an enemy to the consitution finds its way into the stomach, a friend should be
               immediately sent after it, which would prevent its mischievous effects, and expel it
               altogether; no better friend can be found, nor one which will perform the task with
               greater certainty, than <hi rend="sc">norton's camomile pills</hi>. And let it be
               observed that the longer this medicine is taken the less it will be wanted; it can in
               no case become habitual, as its entire action is to give energy and force to the
               stomach, which is the spring of life, the source from which the whole frame draws its
               succour and support. After an excess of eating or drinking, and upon every occasion
               of the general health being at all disturbed, these <hi rend="sc">pills</hi>
               should be immediately taken, as they will stop and eradicate disease at its
               commencement. Indeed it is most confidently asserted, that by the timely use of this
               medicine only, and a common degree of caution, any person may enjoy all the comforts
               within his reach, may pass through life without an illness, and with the certainty of
               attaining a healthy <hi rend="sc">old age</hi>.<lb/> On account of their volatile
               properties, they must be kept in bottles; and if closely corked their qualities are
               neither impaired by time nor injured by any change of climate whatever. Price 13
               1/2d. and 2s.9d.each, with full directions. The large bottle contains the quantity of
               three small ones, or <hi rend="sc">pills</hi> equal to fourteen ounce of <hi
                  rend="sc">camomile flowers</hi>.<lb/>
               <hi rend="medFont">Sold by nearly all respectable Medicine Vendors.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="bold medFont">Be particular to ask for "<hi rend="ac">norton's
                     pills</hi>," and do not be persuaded to purchase an imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="godfreyFlowers">
            <pb n="61"/>
            <head><hi rend="bold sc MedFont">A Clear Complexion.</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="ac fancyFont medFont">Godfrey's Extract of Elder Flowers</hi><lb/> is
               strongly recommended for Softening, Improving, Beautifying, and Preserving the SKIN,
               and giving it a blooming and charming appearance; being at once a most fragrant
               perfume and delightful cosmetic. It will completely remove Tan, Sunburn, Redness,
               &amp;c.; and, by its Balsamic and Healing qualities, render the skin soft, pliable,
               and free from dryness, scurf, &amp;c.; clear it from every humour, pimple, or
               eruption; and, by continuing its use only a short time, the skin will become and
               continue soft and smooth, and the complexion perfectly clear and beautiful. In the
               process of shaving it is invaluable, as it allays the irritation and smarting pain,
               annihilates every pimple and all roughness, and renders the skin smooth and firm. It
               protects the skin from the effects of the cold winds and damp atmosphere which
               prevail during the winter months, and will be found beyond all praise to use as a
               Family Lotion on all occasions.<lb/> Sold in Bottles, price 2s.9d., with Directions
               for using it, by all Medicine Vendors and Perfumers. </p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="simcoGout">
            <head><hi rend="bold sc medFont">A Cure for Gout and Rheumatism.</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="normFont"><hi rend="ital">"The Eighth Plague,"</hi> said the learned
                  Dr. Johnson, <hi rend="ital">"is the Gout, and that man who discovers a Medicine
                     to alleviate its torments deserves well of his country; but he who can effect a
                     cure should have a Monument raised to his memory as high as St. Paul's, as wide
                     as the Thames, and as lasting as time."</hi></hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac fancyFont medFont">Simco's Gout and Rheumatic Pills</hi><lb/> are
               sold by nearly all Medicine Venders at <hi rend="ital">1s. 1 1/2d., and 2s.9d. per
                  Box; the former containing does for</hi> five <hi rend="ital">and the latter
                  for</hi> fifteen <hi rend="ital">days</hi>; and so many individuals, who
               considered themselves martyrs to Gout or Rheumatism, are now ready and willing to
               bear testimony of the wonderful effects of Simco's Pills, that the Proprietor
               fearlessly challenges the whole world to produce Medicine which at all deserves to be
               compared to them. There are <hi rend="ital">many</hi> instances in which person
               have been completely restored to health and activity by taking <hi rend="sc"
                  >Simco's Gout Pills</hi>, who have suffered from Rheumatic Gout for several
               years, and had drawn on a miserable existence, having lost the use of their limbs,
               believing that death alone could terminate their sufferings.<lb/> Whilst taking the
               Pills, no particular rules or restrictions are necessary, as they are warranted not
               to contain any preparation of Mercury whatever; they seldom produce perspiration,
               purging, or sickness, but invariably improve the general health, sharpen the
               appetite, and facilitate digestion. Those periodically subject to Gout, Rheumatic
               Gout, Rheumatic Fever, &amp;c., should keep these Pills by them, as by their timely
               use an approaching attack may always be averted, and the tendency of these complaints
               to attack a vital part be effectually counteracted.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="simcoLinseed">
            <head><hi rend="bold sc medFont">Influenza, Coughs, and Colds.</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="ac fancyFont medFont">Simco's Essence of Linseed</hi><lb/> is the most
               efficacious remedy ever discovered for the relief of persons suffering from
               Influenza; the first two doses generally arrest the progress of this distressing
               complaint, and a little perseverance completely removes it. Children's Coughs, as
               well as recent ones in Adults, will be removed by a few doses (frequently by the
               first); and Asthmatic persons, who previously had not been able to lie down in bed,
               have received the utmost benefit from the use of<lb/>
               <hi rend="ac medFont">Simco's Essence of Linseed.</hi><lb/> Sold in Bottles at
                  <hi rend="ital">1s 1/2d.</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">2s. 9d.</hi> each. </p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="williamAuto">
            <pb n="62"/>
            <head><hi rend="fancyFont hugeFont">The Autobiograph of William Jerdan;</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sc">with his</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="bold medFont">Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="fancyFont medFont">And Correspondence,</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc medFont">During the last forty years</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="bold medFont">As Editor of the "Sun" Newspaper, 1812-17, &amp; of the
                  "Literary Gazette," 1817-50,</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc">IN CONNECTION WITH MOST OF THE EMINENT PERSON WHO HAVE BEEN
                  DISTINGUISED IN THE PAST HALF CENTURY AS STATESMEN, POETS, AUTHORS, MEN OF
                  SCIENCE, ARTISTS, ETC.</hi><lb/> The First Volume, price 5s., with a Portrait of
               the Author, Engraved by <hi rend="sc">Robinson</hi>, from a Painting by <hi
                  rend="sc">Harlowe</hi>, will appear on the <date when="1852-05-01">1st of
                  May</date>, and it is proposed to complete the Work in Four or Six Volumes, to be
               published Quarterly.<lb/>
               <hi rend="ital bold">Among many Distinguished Names introduced in the Narrative and
                  Correspondence will be found,</hi><lb/>
               <list>
                  <item><surname>Ainsworth</surname>, <forename>W. Harrison</forename>, and
                        <forename>W. Francis</forename></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Arbuthnot</surname>,
                        <forename>Charles</forename></persName></item>
                  <item><persName>Bangor, <roleName>Bishop</roleName> of
                     (Magendle)*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bannister</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Barham</surname> (Ingoldsby)*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Barrow</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        John</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Barry</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                     C.*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Blackwood</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Blessington</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lady</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bowles</surname>, Lislo*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Braham</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bray</surname>,
                     <roleName>Mrs</roleName>.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bristol</surname>, <roleName>Bishop</roleName> of
                        (Gray)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Brougham</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bulwer</surname>, Lytton <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        E.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Burgess</surname>, <roleName>Bishop</roleName> of
                        Sallisbury</persName></item>
                  <item><ref target="#byron"/><persName><surname>Byron</surname>,
                           <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Campbell</surname>, Thomas</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Canning</surname>, George</persName></item>
                  <item><surname>Chambers</surname>, <forename>W.</forename> &amp;
                        <forename>R.</forename></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Chantrey</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        F.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Clarendon</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Coleridge</surname>, S.T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Colman</surname>, G.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Colton</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Cooke</surname> (tragodian), Tom*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Cooke</surname>, T.P.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Croly</surname>,
                     <roleName>Dr.</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Cunningham</surname>, Allan</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>De Tabley</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><ref target="#Dick"><persName><surname>Dickens</surname>,
                        Charles</persName></ref></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Disraeli</surname>, Isaac and <ref target="#disraeliB"
                           >Benjamin</ref></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Eldon</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Erskine</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Essex</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lady</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Faraday</surname>,
                        <roleName>Professor</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Farnborough</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Freeling</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        Francis</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Galt</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Godwin</surname>, William</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Grenville</surname>, T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Griffin</surname>, G.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Guizot</surname>, M.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hall</surname>, <roleName>Mr.</roleName> and
                           <roleName>Mrs.</roleName> S.C.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hallam</surname>,</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hemans</surname>,
                     <roleName>Mrs</roleName>.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hogg</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hood</surname>, Thomas</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hook</surname>, Theodore</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hunt</surname>, Leigh</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Huskisson</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Irving</surname>, Washington</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>James</surname>, G.P.E.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Keats</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Kemble</surname> (family)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lamb</surname>, Charles</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Landon</surname> (L.E.L.)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Landseers</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lansdowne</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Laurence</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lockhart</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Londesborough</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Longman</surname>, Thomas Norton</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lover</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>M'Clise</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Macintosh</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        J.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Macready</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Maginn</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Marryat</surname>,
                        <roleName>Captain</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Mathews</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Milman</surname>, Ian*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Milnes</surname>, Monckton*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Mitford</surname>,
                     <roleName>Miss</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Montomgery</surname>, James</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Moore</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Munden</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Munster</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Murchison</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        R.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Murray</surname>, John</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Nares</surname>, Archdescon</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Normanby</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Northampton</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Orme</surname>, Cosmo</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ousely</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName> Wm. and
                           <roleName>Sir</roleName> Gore</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Owen</surname>,
                     <roleName>Professor</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Perceval</surname>, Spencer</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ferry</surname>, James</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Pollock</surname>, <roleName>Lord Chief</roleName>
                        Baron</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Proctor</surname>, B.W. (Barry
                           <surname>Cornwall</surname>)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ripon</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Roberts</surname>, D.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ross</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName> James
                        Clark</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Russell</surname>, <roleName>Lord</roleName>
                        John</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Scott</surname>,
                        <roleName>Sir</roleName>Walter</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Sedgwick</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Shelley</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Sheridan</surname>, R. Brinsley, Tom &amp;
                        Frank</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Smith</surname>, James</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Smith</surname>, Sydney</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Southey</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Stanfield</surname>, Clarkson</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Swain</surname>, Charles</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Talfourd</surname>, Justice</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Thackeray</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Truro</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Turaer</surname>, Sharon</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Tytler</surname>, P.P.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ward</surname>, R. Plumer</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><roleName>Wellington, Duke of</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>West</surname>, B.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Westmacott</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        R.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Whewell</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Wilkie</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        David</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Willoughby de Eresb</surname>y,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><roleName>Winchester, Biship of
                     (Summer)</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Wordsworth</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Wright</surname>, T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Young</surname>, (tragedian)</persName></item>
               </list>
               <hi rend="sc bold">Subscribers' Names Received by All Booksellers.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc">Arthur Hall, Virtue, and Co., 25, Paternoster Row.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="bartlettGiftBook">
            <pb n="63"/>
            <head><hi rend="fancyFont medFont">Mr. Bartlett's New Gift Book.</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="footSteps">
               <p> Third Edition, in super-royal 7vo, Twenty-three Envgravings on Steel and several
                  Woodcuts, price 14s. cloth, gilt edges, or 26s Morocco elegant, <lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac medFont">Footsteps of our lord and his apostles</hi><lb/> In
                  Syria, Greece, and Italy, a Succession of Vists to the Scenes of New Testament
                  Narrative.<lb/> "If beauty of design and execution, combined with elegance of
                  narrative and trustworthy description, can be any recommendation to a book, it is
                  sufficient to say that this excellent volume posseses every one of these features,
                  and establishes its own character without the need of any further praise." -Bell's
                  Messenger.<lb/> "Mr. Bartlett has with success brought together in an effective
                  and attractive volume, a series of written and engraved memorials of the early
                  days of our faith, which cannot but find a welcome in many a domestic circle, and
                  cheer with its reccolections every Christian heart, whilst it pleases with its
                  artistic beauty the most careless inspectors. We close the book with regret, and
                  recommend it without fear." -Britanica<lb/> "This is one of the happiest of the
                  many happy Christmas ventures that their publishers have put forth. It is got up
                  in excellent taste, and written in a pleasing and attractive style." -Church and
                  State Gazette.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="gleanings">
               <p> 2.<lb/> Second Edition, in super-royal 8vo, price 16s. handsomely bound in cloth
                  gilt, or 28s. Morocco elegant, <lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac medFont">Gleanings, Antiquarian and Pictorial,</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">on</hi><lb/> the <hi rend="sc">Overland Route</hi>,
                  illustrated with 28 Steel Plates and Maps, and 23 Woodcuts.<lb/> "The present work
                  is as excellent as his former productions, for its lively and picturesque
                  narrative, and for the exquisite engravings by which it is illustrated."-Athenaeum
                  <lb/> "It is unquestionably one of the most elegant volumes ever published. The
                  letterpress gives an excellent historical account of Malta, with graphic sketches
                  of travelling adventures, both at that place and at Gibraltar." -Atlas<lb/>
                  "Should be in the hands of every person travelling by the Overland Route, as well
                  as in every library in the kingdom with at least pretensions to completeness."
                  -Observer.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="nileBoat">
               <p> 3.<lb/> Third Edition, in super-royal 8vo, price 16s. cloth gilt; 28s. morocco
                  gilt, <lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac medFont">The Nile Boat;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, Glimpses of the Land of Egypt.</hi><lb/> Illustrated by
                  35 Steel Engravings and Maps, with numerous Cuts.<lb/> "Of Mr.Bartlett's merit as
                  a pictorial traveler we have frequently had occasion to speak in terms of high
                  commendation. In the present work he has been eminently
                  successful."-Athenaeum.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="fortyDays">
               <p> 4.<lb/> Forth Edition, in super-royal 8vo, price 12s. cloth gilt; Morocco gilt, 21s.,<lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac medFont">Forty Days in the Desert</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">on the Track of the</hi><lb/> Israelites; or A Journey from
                  Cairo by Wady Feiran to Mount Sinai and Petra. With 27 Engravings on Steel, a Map
                  and numerous Woodcuts.<lb/> "The author presents, in this volume, one of the most
                  picturesque accounts of the route across the wilderness of sand we have ever
                  read." -Morning Herald.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="walksJerusalem">
               <p> 5.<lb/> New Edition, in super-royal 8vo, cloth gilt, 12s.; Morocco gilt, 21s.,<lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac medFont">Walks about Jerusalem and its Environs.</hi><lb/>
                  Illustrated by 24 Steel Engravings, 2 Maps, and many superior Woodcuts.<lb/> "The
                  volume is well got up in point of embellishments, and contains much valuable
                  matter, with illustrations beautifully executed." -Church of England
                  Magazine.<lb/> "It is very elegantly got up, and will be richly ornamental to the
                  table of any drawing-room, library, or boudoir." -Wesleyan Association
                  Magazine.<lb/> "We have at length, in this attractive volume, the desideratum of a
                  complete picturesque guide to the topography of Jerusalem." -Patriot.<lb/> "Our
                  impression is, that Jerusalem was never before so successfully delineated."
                  -Evangelical Magazine.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="scriptureSites">
               <p> 6.<lb/> Now ready, price 4s. cloth gilt, post 8vo,<lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac medFont">Scripture Sites and Scenes</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">from actual Survey,</hi><lb/> in Egypt, Arabia, and
                  Palestine. Illustrated by 17 Steel Engravings, 3 Maps, and 37 Woodcuts.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi rend="ac medFont">Arthur Hall, Virtue, and Co., 25, Paternoster Row.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="johnCumming">
            <pb n="64"/>
            <head><hi rend="fancyFont medFont">Works by the <ref type="note" target="#n3"
                           ><persName><roleName>Rev</roleName>. <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Cumming</surname>
                        <roleName>D. D.</roleName></persName></ref></hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="foreshadows">
               <p> Fifth Thousand, in 2 vols. fcap 8vo, price 9s, cloth, full gilt,<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Forshadows;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, Lecutres on our Lord's Miracles</hi><lb/> and <hi
                     rend="sc">parables</hi> as Earnests of the Age to Come.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="propheticStudies">
               <p> 2.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Prophetic Studies;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, Lectures on the Book of</hi><lb/> Daniel. Sixth
                  Thousand, in fcap 8vo, 9s. cloth, elegantly gilt; or 13s. Morocco.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="apocalyptic">
               <p> 3.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Apocalyptic Sketches;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, Lecutres on the Book</hi><lb/> of Revelation. Delivered
                  at Exter Hall, and Crown Court Church. New Editions, revised and corrected, with
                  Two Indiees. Eleventh Thousand, in two vols. price 9s. each, cloth gilt, or 26s.
                  Morocco.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="apocalypticThird">
               <p> 4.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Apocalyptic Sketches-</hi><hi rend="medFont">Third
                     Series. Or, Lectures</hi><lb/> on the Seven Churches of Asian Minor.
                  Illustrated by Wood Engravings, representing the present state of the Apostolic
                  Churches. Eight Thousand, uniform with the above.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="isChristianity">
               <p> 5.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">"Is Christianity from God?"</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">a Manual of</hi><lb/> Christian Evidences for Scripture
                  Readers, Sunday School Teachers, City Missionaries, and Young Persons. Eighth
                  Edition, fcap 8vo, cloth, price 3s.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="ourFather">
               <p> 6.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Our Father;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">a Manual of Family Prayers for General</hi><lb/> and
                  Special Occasions, with Short Prayers for Spare Minutes, and Passages for
                  Reflection. Fifth Edition, fcap 8vo, price 3s. cloth, gilt edges.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="communionTable">
               <p> 7.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">The Communion Table;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, Communicant's Manual:</hi><lb/> a Plain and Practical
                  Exposition of the Lord's Supper. New Eidtion, fcap 8vo, price 3s. cloth,<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="romish">
               <p> 8.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Romish Miracles:</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">a Lecture delivered in the Town</hi><lb/> Hall, Birmingham,
                  Third Thousand, price 1s.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="celebratedProtestant">
               <p> 9.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">The Celebrated Protestant Discussion</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">be-</hi><lb/> tween the Rev. John Cumming, D.D. and Daniel
                  French, Esq., held at Hammersmith, in 1839, Cheap Edition, Price 6s. cloth
                  lettered.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="lectures">
               <p> 10.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Lecutres for the times;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or Iluustrations and</hi><lb/> Refutations of the Errors of
                  Romanism and Tractarianism. New Edition, Revised, with Additions, price 6s. in
                  cloth.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="infantSalv">
               <p> 11.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Infant Salvation;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, All Saved who Die in Infancy.</hi><lb/> Specially
                  addressed to Mothers mourning the loss of Infants and Children. Fourth Edition,
                  fcap 8vo, cloth, gilt edges, price 2s.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="bapFront">
               <p> 12.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">The Baptismal Font;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">an Exposition of the Nature</hi><lb/> and Obligations of
                  Christian Baptism. With an Appendix. Third Eddition, fcap 8vo, gilt edges, price
                  2s.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="messageGod">
               <p> 13.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">A Message from God;</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">or, Thoughts on Religion for</hi><lb/> Thinking Men. Fourth
                  Edition, fcap 8vo, cloth, gilt edges, 2s.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="discourses">
               <p> 14.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc medFont">Occasional Discourses.</hi>
                  <hi rend="medFont">Two vols., price 4s. each,</hi><lb/> cloth. Contents:-1,
                  Liberty. 2. Equality. 3. Fraternity. 4. The Revolutionists. 5. The True Charter.
                  6. The True Succession. 7. Psalm for the Day. 8. Thanksgiving. 9. Salvation. 10.
                  Autumn Thoughts, &amp;c.<lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi rend="ac medFont">Arthur Hall, Virtue, and Co., 25, Paternoster Row.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="newWorks">
            <pb n="65"/>
            <head><hi rend="fancyFont medfont">New Works and New Editions.</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="CeltRomanSaxon">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">The Celt, the Roman, and the
                        Saxon.</hi> A His-</hi><lb/> tory of the Early Inhabitants of Britain
                  down to the Conversion of the Anglo-Saxons to Christianity Illustrated by the
                  Ancient Remains brought to light by recent Research. By <hi rend="sc">Thomas
                     Wright</hi>, Esq., M.A., F.S.A. With numerous Illustrations.<hi rend="ital"
                     >[Shortly.</hi>
               </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="Persepolis">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Nineveh and Persepolis:</hi> An
                     Historical Sketch</hi><lb/> of Ancient Assyria and Persia, with an Account of
                  the recent Researches in those Countries. By W.S.W. Vaux, M.A., of the British
                  Museum. Third Edition, revised and enlarged, in post 8vo, with numerous
                  Illustrations. Price 8s. bound in cloth; or 17s morocco antique </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="indianPoetry">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Speciments of Old Indian Poetry.</hi>
                     Translated from</hi><lb/> the Original Sanskrit into English Verse, by Ralph
                  T.H. Griffith, M.A., Member of the Royal Asiatic Society, and Boden Sanskrit
                  Scholar in the University of Oxford. <hi rend="ital">[In preparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="anatomyPhysiology">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="ac bold medFont">A Manual of the Anatomy and Physiology</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">of the human mind.</hi> By <hi rend="sc"
                           ><persName><roleName>Rev.</roleName>
                        <forename>James</forename>
                        <surname>Carlile</surname>,</persName> D.D.</hi>, of Personstown and
                  Dublin, Ireland. Feap, price 5s. cloth.<lb/> "Dr. Carlile has aimed at doing for
                  metaphysics what Sir John Herschel accomplished for astronomy in his popular <hi
                     rend="ital">Manual</hi>, and Paley for his subject in his celebrated <hi
                     rend="ital">Evidences of Christianity</hi>. He has not merely compiled or
                  analyzed, but has read and thought for himself, and what he writes, though no
                  doubt directly traceable to other sources, is yet stamped with his own character
                  and feeling." -- <hi rend="ital">Gaurdian</hi>. </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="forestRanger">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Old Forest Ranger;</hi> or, Wild
                     Sports of India in the</hi><lb/> Neilgherry Hills, in the Jungles, and on the
                  Plains. By <hi rend="sc">Major Walter Campell</hi>, of Skipness. With
                  Illustrations on Steel. New Edition, in post 8vo. <hi rend="ital">[In
                     preparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="tupperPoems">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Ballads for the Times</hi>, and Other
                     Poems. By</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Martin Farquhar Tupper</hi>, Esq., D.C.L., F.R.S.,
                  &amp;c.,&amp;c. Second Complete Edition, price 7s. 6d., with Vignette and
                  Frontispiece, uniform with "Proverbial Philosophy."<lb/> "With smoothness of
                  measure, Mr. Tupper's design is always excellent, and his versification is brought
                  to bear upon things of no transient interest. It is one of the best
                  characteristics of his labours, that he does not write for praise, but for the
                  benefit of his felow-men -- not merely for time, but for eternity." -- <hi
                     rend="ital">Bell's Messenger</hi>
               </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="canadianCrusoes">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">The Canadian Crusoes:</hi> A Tale of
                     the Rice Lake</hi><lb/> Hunting Grounds. By Mrs. <hi rend="sc"
                     >Traill</hi> (late Miss Strickland), Author of "The Backwoods of Canada." In
                  feap*, with numerous Illustrations. <hi rend="ital">[In preparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="loveandReality">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Love and Reality, not Romance.</hi> By
                     Mrs. Thomas</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Geldart</hi>, Author of "Truth is Everything," &amp;c. With
                  Illustrations by Gilbert. Price 3s. 6d, feap*, cloth, gilt edges. </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="woman">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Woman,</hi>--Her Mission and her Life.
                     From the French of</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Monod</hi>, by Rev. W.G. <hi rend="sc">Barrett</hi>. Second
                  Edition, revised. Price 1s. 6d., in a neat Pocket Volume.<lb/> "Never was the
                  theme handled before with greater delicacy, or with more a thorough poetical
                  result. We should like to see this cheap <hi rend="ital">telling</hi> volume
                  in the hands of every woman througout the land. It is calculated to do immense
                  good, and especially to awaken and strengthen in every woman's heart <hi
                     rend="ital">the feeling of responsibiliy." -- Evangelical Magazine.</hi><lb/>
                  "More admirable dicourses were never written than these: they enter wisely and
                  judiciously into the subject they are intended to expound." -- <hi rend="ital"
                     >Bell's Messenger.</hi>
               </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="yeMaiden">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Ye Maiden</hi> and <hi rend="ac"
                        >Married Life</hi> of <hi rend="ac">Mary Powell</hi>.</hi><lb/>
                  Afterwards <hi rend="sc">Mistress Milton</hi>. New Edition, in post 8vo, with
                  Portrait. Price 7s. 6d. antique.<lb/> "This is a charming little book; and whether
                  we regard its subject, cleverness, or delicacy of sentiment and expression--to say
                  nothing of its type and orthography--it is likely to be a most acceptable present
                  to young or old, be their peculiar taste for religion, moral, poetry, history, or
                  romance." -- <hi rend="ital">Christian Observer</hi>. </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="queenPhilippa">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Queene Philippa's Golden Booke</hi>.
                     Handsomely</hi><lb/> bound and gilt, with Illuminations. </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="yeHousehold">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold medFont"><hi rend="ac">Ye Household of Sir Thomas More</hi>.
                     Libellus a</hi><lb/> Margareta More, quindecim* annos nata, Chelseiae
                  inceptus. Uniform with "<persName>Mary Powell</persName>." </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi rend="ac medFont">Arthur Hall, Virtue, and Co., 25, Paternoster
               Row.</hi><lb/> Reed and Pardon, Printers Paternoster Row. </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="newLondon">
            <pb n="66"/>
            <head><hi rend="bold ac medFont">New London Weekly Newspaper, Price
               Fourpence,</hi></head>
            <lb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="ital">Will be Published on Saturday, the 15th of May.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="bold medFont">A Presentation Plate <hi rend="ac">Gratis</hi>! Cost
                  Engraving,<lb/> Four Hundred Guineas.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ital">A Beautiful Print, the</hi><hi rend="sc">Origin of the
                  Stocking-Loom</hi><hi rend="ital">, painted by</hi><hi rend="ac">Alfred
                  Elmore</hi>, A.R.A., and <hi rend="ital">Engraved on <hi rend="ac"
                     >Steel</hi> by</hi><hi rend="ac">Francis Hol</hi><hi rend="ital">,
                  (published at £1 1s.) will be presented,</hi>
               <hi rend="ac">Gratis</hi><hi rend="ital">, to Subscribers, with the Thirteenth
                  Number.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc">This Sketch Represents the</hi>
               <hi rend="ac">Steel Engraving</hi>
               <hi rend="sc">of the</hi>
               <hi rend="ac">Origin of the Stocking-Loom</hi>, <hi rend="sc">the size of which
                  is 22in, by 16 1/2in</hi>.<lb/>
               <figure type="image" place="center">
                  <graphic url="img/66graphic.png"
                  />
               </figure><lb/>
               <hi rend="smallFont">[William Lee, of St. Johns College, Cambridge, was about the
                  1589 expelled from the University for marrying contrary to the statutes. Having no
                  fortune, the wife was obliged to contribute to their joint support by knitting;
                  and Lee, while watching the motion of her fingers, conceived the idea of imitating
                  those movements by a machine.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">The</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac bold hugeFont">London Weekly Paper,</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">And</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="hugeFont fancyFont">Organ of the Middle Classes.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">A Record of Political, Domestic, and Foreign News, Literature, Arts,
                  Science, etc.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc">Under the Direction of</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="medFont ac">William Jerdan, Esq</hi>.,<lb/>
               <hi rend="ital">(Late Editor of the Literary Gazette.)</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="medFont ac">To the Middle Classes.</hi><lb/> In offering the <hi
                  rend="sc">London Weekly Paper</hi> to represent you in that great and still
               growing power, the Parliament of the British Press, we are aware that, previous to
               giving us your sufferages, you will demand--and justly--a full, clear, and candid
               statement of the part we propose to act on this great stage of Social and Political
               Life. With candour then we say, if we are returned, (and as those Members of
               Parliament who represent the larger constituencies are those whose opinions are
               attached the greater weight, so the greater number of votes you register in <pb
                  n="67"/>our favor the greater will be our influence, and consequently our sphere
               of usefulness,) that it is our purpose to enforce two high principles: I. Social
               Improvement; II. Political Reform.<lb/> With our Social Duties then we will commence.
               We desire to supply a want long felt by a large portion of the Public: -- <hi
                  rend="ital">viz</hi>, a <hi rend="sc">Weekly Paper</hi> that shall at once
               embrace all the <hi rend="ital">news and topics of the week</hi>, and, at the
               same time, maintain a <hi rend="ital">higher literary character</hi> than has
               generally been assumed by the weekly press. It will be of the full size, consisting
               of sixty-four columns, printed on superior paper, from bold, clear type.<lb/> As our
                  <hi rend="sc">London Weekly Paper</hi> is especially intended for the Family
               Circle, the utmost care will be taken to preserve, throughout, a strictly Moral Tone,
               and with this view, <hi rend="ital">all advertisements of an objectionable
                  character will be carefully excluded</hi>. The proceedings of the Law and Police
               Courts will be fully reported, and no pains will be spared to obtain the best and
               latest Foreign, Town, and Country News, with Accurate Accounts of Public Meetings,
               Lectures, Exhibitions, &amp;c. Carefully digested Reports of the Parliamentary
               Proceedings and Debates will also be given. Due attention will be paid to the
               Markets, Funds, Railways, Sporting Intelligence, &amp;c.<lb/> We intend making the
               Reviews of New Books, Science, Archaeology, the Fine Arts, Music, the Theatres,
               &amp;c., especial features: this portion will be confided to gentlemen distinguised
               by their attainments in the Arts, Science, and Literature.<lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">A Principal Novelty</hi> in this Paper, distinguishing it from all
               others, will be the devotion, from week to week, of a portion of its Columns <hi
                  rend="ital">to the <hi rend="ac">History of the Origin</hi> of contemporary
                  events, with Biographical notices of persons lately sprung into notoriety</hi>.
               Thus, we shall not think it enough to record a passing occurrence, but when it
               possesses anny importance, make it a portion of our duty to give the particular of
               such event, and the <hi rend="ital">cause</hi> which led to it. It has been a
               matter of complaint, that, in the newspapers generally, great political incidents as
               they occur are brought <hi rend="ital">abruptly</hi> before the public, without
               that sort of information relating to their <hi rend="ital">antecedents</hi> which
               would make them intelligible to the general reader; this defect we hope to
               remedy.<lb/> But, while we devote a portion of our space to all these subjects, the
               Political Department of our Paper will be earnestly conducted, nor shall we shrink,
               in the slightest degree, from the responsibility attached to it. We will honestly
               advocate the great cause of National Progress, and we need scarcely add the
               continuance of the free and enlightened Commercial Policy which has so largely
               contributed to the present material comforts of the humbler classes, and thus to the
               general prosperity of the country: while we no less firmly support, on the other
               hand, the interests of Social Order against Mob Despotism, and the great principles
               of Constitutional Liberty against Individual or Combined Oppression.<lb/> With regard
               to the Church, we profess ourselves Staunch Protestants, but we shall advocate the
               cause of Religious Liberty, and do all in our power to promote Reform of Abuses which
               have crept into Ecclesiastical Establishments. In short, we shall suport deliberate
               and well-conducted Reform wherever it is required, in Church or in State, in Law, or
               other Learned Professions, in Corporate Bodies and Institutions, in the Commerical
               and Colonial Relations of the Kingdom, in Education, and in everyhthing which regards
               the Social Condition and Social Comforts of our Countrymen. It is for them that our
                  <hi rend="sc">Paper</hi> is designed; we shall espouse the cause of no sect or
               party; but, whatever set of men may be in power, we shall judge every Measure of
               Government only by its intrinsic merits and the benefits it is likely to secure for
               the country.<lb/> An Edition will be published on Friday, in time for the Evening
               Mails for the country, and the last Edition on Saturday evening at Six o'clock, which
               will contain the latest general news, the market and commercial intelligence, with
               quotations of prices corrected to the hour of going to press.<lb/> Orders will be
               attended to by all News-vendors throughout the United Kingdom; or the Publisher will
               send it directly from the office upon the receipt of a Quarter's Subscription, <hi
                  rend="ital">viz</hi>., 4s. 4d.<lb/> Money orders to be made payable to
                  <persName>Frederick Tallis</persName>, 1, Crane-court, Fleet-street.<lb/>
               <hi rend="medFont ac">London:<lb/> Published by <persName>Frederick
                     Tallis</persName>, 1, Crane Court, Fleet Street.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="crochet">
            <pb n="68"/>
            <head><hi rend="hugeFont ac">Crochet Cotton</hi></head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="medFont ac sansSerif">For the</hi><graphic url="img/68graphic.png"/><hi rend="medFont ac sansSerif">Million.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="hugeFont ac">Marsland, Son, &amp; Co.</hi><lb/>
               Beg to present the annexed <hi rend="ac bold">Crochet Pattern</hi>, and solicit and recommend a trial of their <hi rend="ac sansSerif">cotton</hi>, which is superior to any other in use.<lb/>
               Their <hi rend="ac sansSerif">Crochet Cotton</hi> is made of a peculiar material, which renders it exceedingly pleasant to work with; it has a soft, yet cabled surface, is extremely free from fibre, is warranted not to wtist or curl in the working, or to shrink in the washing, and has an extraordinary silkiness of finish, which causes the pattern, when crocheted and washed, to possess a beautiful pearly appearance never before attained by an other manufacture.<lb/>
               M.S. &amp; Co.'s manufacture of <hi rend="ac sansSerif">crochet cotten</hi> contains every variety of Colors, warranted fast.
               The Editresses of the <orgName>"Ladies' Newspaper,"</orgName> the <orgName>"Ladies' Own Book,"</orgName> the Editor of the <orgName>"Shortway Edging and Round R'Oyley,"</orgName> <sic>he</sic> <orgName>"Exhibition and Teingnmouth,"</orgName> the Editor of the <orgName>"Bijou,"</orgName> and all the leading Publishers of the present day, are bringing out their works and patterns to suit the numbers of <hi rend="sc">Marsland, Son,</hi> &amp; Co.'s Crochet Cotton.<lb/>
               M.S. &amp; Co. also manufacture <hi rend="ac sansSerif">nine cord, six cord,</hi> and <hi rend="ac sansSerif">three cord sewing cotton</hi>, of a quality equal to their Crochet Cotton, which is sold at the same establishments.<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">The full Lengths are guaranteed.</hi><lb/>
               Sold retail by the principal Berlin wool venders, drapers, haberdashers, <sic/>all-ware dealers, &amp;c.<lb/>
               N.B.--The trade supplied by Messrs. Daudel Phillips, <sic>Me srs.</sic> Hutton and Co., Newgate Street, London, by all the leading warehouses in Manchester, or at the Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester, where all orders by post or personal application will be attended to.<lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">London Agent: Edward Wright</hi>, 33, <hi rend="sc">Lawrence Lane, Cheapside.</hi><lb/>
               <pb n="69"/>
               <hi rend="medFont ac">Crests &amp; Centres for Doyleys</hi><hi rend="medFont">&amp;c.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="sc">Marsland, Son,</hi> and Co's. Crochet Thread, No. 24;<lb/>
               Penelope Crochet Hook, No. 3.  Work the ground in open, and design in close squares. <hi rend="ital">Vide "<orgName>Ladies' Newspaper</orgName>,"</hi> page 182, March 27th, 1852; Edited by <persName>Madlle. <hi rend="sc">Dufour</hi></persName><lb/>
               <graphic url="img/69graphic.png"/><lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Manufactory, Bridge Mills, Blackfriars, Manchester.</hi><lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="waterlowPrinters">
            <pb n="70"/>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="autographicPress">
               <head><hi rend="medFont ac">Waterlow's</hi><lb/><hi rend="medFont ac bold">Patent Improved Autographic Press,</hi><lb/></head>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="img/70graphic.png"/><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Or Portable</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont sansSerif bold">Printing Machine,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac">For the Counting-House, Office, or Library,<lb/> by means of which<lb/>
                     <hi rend="bold">Every Person May Become His Own Printer.</hi><lb/></hi> The
                  process is simple, and thousands of copies may be produced from any writing, drawing,
                  or piece of music, or design (previously made on paper), and the requisite number of
                  copies being finished, the subject may be effaced and another substituted.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">Many hundreds of these Presses have now been sold, and are being
                     successfully used by Railway and Public Companies, Bankers, Merchants, Amateurs,
                     &amp;c, &amp;c.; also in Public and Private Schools, for the production of lessons
                     in Music, Drawing, &amp;c, &amp;c.</hi><lb/> The Press may be seen at work at the
                  Patentees', and specimens of its production will be forward free, upon application.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac SansSerif">Prices</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">
                     <table rows="3" cols="4">
                        <row role="label">
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell/>
                           <cell role="label">On Mahogany Stand.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="item">
                           <cell role="item">To print a Subject</cell>
                           <cell role="dimensions">11 x 9 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="prices">£7 7 0 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="mahoganyPrices">£9 9 0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="item">
                           <cell role="item">Ditto</cell>
                           <cell role="dimensions">16.5 x 10.25 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="prices">8 8 0 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="mahoganyPrices">10 10 0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="item">
                           <cell role="item">Ditto</cell>
                           <cell role="dimensions">16 x 13.5 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="prices">9 9 0 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="mahoganyPrices">12 12 0</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold">Patent Autographic Press for Travellers,</hi><lb/> <graphic url="img/70graphic2.png"/><lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac">Which from its compact form is recommended for use on</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold"> Voyages and Foreign Missions.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">To Print a Subject 11 x 9 Price complete £9 9 0.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac">Patenters--Waterlow &amp; Sons, Manufacturing Stationers</hi>,
                  &amp;c.<lb/> 65 to 68, <hi rend="ac">London Wall, London</hi>.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="ital">For Notices of the Press, see other side.</hi><lb/>
                  <pb n="71"/><graphic url="img/71graphic.png"/><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">The</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="hugeFont bold ac">Patent Autographic Press,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">(Hand Power),</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac sansSerif">Adapted for Exploration to the Colonies</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Occupying Little Space and Very Portable.</hi><lb/> The attention of
                     <hi rend="ac">merchants</hi> and <hi rend="ac">shippers</hi> is particularly
                  called to the importance of this invention, for the Colonies and Foreign Countries:
                  and when it is considered that in many places no printer is to be found, and that in
                  some countries, especially in the East, the complication of the numerous Oriental
                  characters renders it necessary for all documents to be multiplied by the tedious
                  process of transcribing, the peculiar advantages of the Autographic Press become manifest.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold">Prices.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">
                     <table rows="3" cols="3">
                        <lb/>
                        <row role="item">
                           <cell role="item">To print a Subject</cell>
                           <cell role="dimensions">14 x 9 - - </cell>
                           <cell role="prices">£4 4 0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="item">
                           <cell role="item">Ditto</cell>
                           <cell role="dimensions">16 x 10 - - - </cell>
                           <cell role="prices">5 5 0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="item">
                           <cell role="item">Ditto</cell>
                           <cell role="dimensions">18 x 13 - - - </cell>
                           <cell role="prices">6 6 0</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac">Patentees--Waterlow and Sons, London.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac hugeFont bold sansSerif">Opinions of the Press.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">From the City Article of "The <hi rend="sc">Times</hi>."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont">A very useful invention has been patented by <hi rend="ac"
                        >Messrs. Waterlow &amp; Sons</hi> which will be productive of great convenience
                     to Banking Establishments and other concerns requiring to send out circulars with
                     dispatch. It is called the Autographic Press, and a letter written on prepared
                     paper with which it is furnished, can be transferred by a short process to a
                     metallic plate, from which any number of copies may afterwards be taken on common
                     paper and by ordinary pressure. In the colonies and other places where facilities
                     for such operations are now scarce, and in all cases where the documents to be
                     copied are of a confidential nature, it is likely to prove particularly
                     valuable.</hi><lb/>
                  <pb n="72"/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">Waterlow &amp; Sons'</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="hugeFont ac">Patent Autographic Press.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac">Opinions of the Press.</hi>--<hi rend="medFont ital"
                     >(Continued.)</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Morning Chronicle"</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont"><hi rend="sc bold">Autographic Press.</hi>--An invention has
                     been patented which is likely to prove of great utility to public companies and
                     men of business generally. It will become a great desideratum to merchants in the
                     colonies, and will be found very useful at the chief offices of banks, in
                     suspending the necessity for copying any number of circulars which it may be
                     necessary to send to the Branches from time to time. We understand it has received
                     the patronage of <persName>His Royal Highness Prince Albert</persName>, and it is
                     the invention of <hi rend="sc bold">Messrs. Waterlow and Sons</hi>, London Wall,
                     by whom it has been patented.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Westminster Review."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont"><hi rend="sc bold">The Autographic Press, or Portable Printing
                        Machine.</hi>--Under this name the Messrs. <hi rend="sc">Waterlow</hi>, of
                     London Wall, have patented a very simple but effective apparatus, the merits of
                     which cannot fail to be duly appreciated as soon as they are known. The subject to
                     be printed is transferred from paper to the surgace of a highly-polished metallic
                     plate, and being charged with ink in the usual manner, the paper on which it is to
                     be printed is placed upon it, and the tympan being laid down, a wooden scraper
                     with a sharp edge is passed over it by the hand, when a perfect impression is at
                     once obtained. All this may be done even upon the drawing-room table: and the
                     whole of the apparatus, when not in use, is enclosed in a neat French-polished
                     box, which may be carried beneath the arm. The utility of such a simple
                     application of the lithographic principle must be obvious to mercantile men and
                     others, who require a number of copies of their correspondence.<lb/> The name of
                     "Autographic Press" may perhaps induce the idea that this is some cumbrous machine
                     similar to that used in lithographic printing. Such, however, is not the case, for
                     no <hi rend="ital">press</hi>, in the ordinary acceptation of the term, is used at
                     all, the impression, as we have before mentioned, being produced by hand. The
                     requisite number of copies having been obtained, the design is effaced from the
                     plate, which is then ready to receive another.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Atlas."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont"><hi rend="sc bold">Bankers' and Merchants'Circulars.</hi>--An
                     invention has been submitted to us, which is likely to prove of great utility to
                     public companies and men of business generally. It consists of a press and
                     materials, by means of which any person may, from a document previously written on
                     paper, produce any required number of copies. Circulars, letters, prospectuses,
                     &amp;c., can be produced by this invention with the greatest facility; and any
                     number of designs, music, plans, &amp;c., may be expeditiously printed in the same
                     manner. The apparatus is extremely simple, and is all contained in a box of small
                     size, perfectly portable. It will become a great desideratum to merchants in the
                     colonies, and will be found very useful at the chief offices of banks. In
                     suspending the necessity for copying any number of circulars which it may be
                     necessary to send to the Branches from time to time. We understand it has received
                     patronage of <persName>H.R.H. Prince Albert</persName>, and it is the invention of
                     Messrs. <hi rend="sc bold">Waterlow and Sons</hi>, London Wall, by whom it has
                     been patented.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Illustrated London News."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont"><hi rend="sc bold">Waterlow's Autographic Press</hi>--Amongst
                     the most practically useful inventions which have recently come under our notice,
                     whether we regard it in reference to the commercial world, or as an instrumet in
                     the hands of a private gentleman. "The Autographic Press," patented by <hi
                        rend="sc">Waterlow</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Sons</hi>, is entited to foremost
                     mention. By this apparatus, any person may with facility print any number of
                     letters, circulars, pen and ink sketches, musical notations, or other matters in
                     which duplicate copies are wanted; the whole machinery being compassed in a neat
                     box not larger than a lady's writing-case. The mode in which the transfer is
                     effected may be briefly described. For instance: a letter is written on prepared
                     paper, and then transferred to a polished metallic plate by means of hand-power,
                     assisted by a "scraper." The paper is then washed off the plate with water, when
                     the writing remains on the plate, and is charged with ink from a roller somewhat
                     similar to the ordinary printing roller. Paper is now laid on the plate, and upon
                     the application of pressure, in the manner before described, the impression is
                     derived, and the process may be repeated sixty of seventy times in the hour, the
                     plate being subjected to the ink roller for each impression. When sufficient
                     copies are cast off, the plate is cleaned, and ready for a fresh operation. The
                     specimens we have seen are equal to lithography.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Bankers' Magazine."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont"><hi rend="sc bold">Autographic Press</hi>--An invention of great
                     utility, Bankers' Circulars may be printed from it with the greatest facility. It
                     will become very useful at the chief offices of banks, in suspending the necessity
                     for copying any number of circulars which it may be necessary to send to the
                     branches from time to time. It has received the patronage of <persName>H.R.H.
                        Prince Albert</persName>, to whom it has been submitted by the Patentees,
                     Messrs. <hi rend="sc">Waterlow</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Sons</hi>, London Wall.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Saunders's Dublin News Letter."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont">During the course of the week we have had exhibited to us a
                     novel but highly useful machine, called the "Autographic Press," invented and
                     patented by <hi rend="sc">Waterlow</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Sons</hi>, of London.
                     The object of the inventors is to enable merchants, bankers, clerks, &amp;c., to
                     take an <hi rend="ital">ad infinitum</hi> number of copies of their circulars,
                     letters, documents, &amp;c. It entirely supersedes the old mode of copying by the
                     ordinary press, and far outstrips the "manifold" system. In fact, it is a complete
                     lithographic press, put up in a neat portable box, and can be purchased at a
                     moderate price. To the commerical community it must prove a great
                     desideratum."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Bombay Gazette."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont">We see that a very useful invention has been patented by Messrs.
                        <hi rend="sc">Waterlow</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Sons</hi>, of London, which will
                     be productive of great convenience to banking establishments, and other concerns
                     requiring to send out circulars with despatch. It is called the "Autographic
                     Press," and a letter written on prepared paper, with which it is furnished, can be
                     transferred, by a short process, to a metallic plate, from which any number of
                     copies may afterwards be taken on common paper, and by ordinary pressure. In the
                     Colonies, and other places where facilities for such operations are now scarce,
                     and in all cases where documents to be copied are of a confidential nature, this
                     invention is represented as being likely to prove particularly valuable.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold ac">"Railway Record."</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="smallFont"><hi rend="sc bold">General Orders to Station
                     Clerks.</hi>--Messrs. <hi rend="sc">Waterlow</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Sons</hi>,
                     London Wall, have recently patented an invention which is likely to prove of great
                     utility to all public Companies. A press and material are put together in a neat
                     box, in such a way that any person may, with the greatest facility, reproduce from
                     MS. any number of copies that may be required. It is called the "Autographic
                     Press"--is very neat, and pefectly portable. Railway Companies would find it
                     exceedingly convenient in issuing orders to their Stations; and it would in point
                     of expense very soon repay its moderate cost.</hi><lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="lettercopyPress">   
               <head><hi rend="medFont ac bold">Patent Letter Copying Presses</hi><lb/></head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73"/>
                  <graphic url="img/73graphic1.png"/>Lever Press.<lb/>
                  <graphic url="img/73graphic2.png"/>Screw Press.<lb/><graphic url="img/73graphic3.png"/>First Quality Screw Press.<lb/><graphic url="img/73graphic4.png"/>Wrought Iron Beam Screw
                  Press.<lb/>These Machines, although <hi rend="ital">lower in price than those of any
                     other manufacturer</hi>, are all <hi rend="ital">warranted</hi>, and will be
                  immediately exchanged, or the money returned, if any fault is discovered.<lb/>
                  <table rows="3" cols="7">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell role="label">Lever Press.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Screw Press</cell>
                        <cell role="label">1st quality Screw.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Screw Press, wrt.iron beam.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Mahogany Tables</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Damping Boxes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell role="item">Large 4to ...</cell>
                        <cell role="levelPrices">£1 10</cell>
                        <cell role="screwPrices">£2 10</cell>
                        <cell role="1stqualityscrewPrices">£3 3</cell>
                        <cell role="ironbeamPrices">£3 15</cell>
                        <cell role="mahogPrices">£1 5</cell>
                        <cell role="dampingboxPrices">11s.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell role="item">Foolscap Folio ...</cell>
                        <cell role="levelPrices">2 0</cell>
                        <cell role="screwPrices">3 3</cell>
                        <cell role="1stqualityscrewPrices">4 10</cell>
                        <cell role="ironbeamPrices">5 5</cell>
                        <cell role="mahogPrices">2 2</cell>
                        <cell role="dampingboxPrices">12s.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell role="item">Post Folio ...</cell>
                        <cell role="levelPrices">--</cell>
                        <cell role="screwPrices">4 4</cell>
                        <cell role="1stqualityscrewPrices">6 0</cell>
                        <cell role="ironbeamPrices">6 6</cell>
                        <cell role="mahogPrices">3 10</cell>
                        <cell role="dampingboxPrices">14s.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table><lb/>
                  <table rows="5" cols="3">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell><hi rend="ital">Fittings for Quarto Machine.</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="ital">Fittings for Foolscap Machine</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="ital">Fittings for Folio Machine</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Cloth Pads, per pair ...2s. 6d.</cell>
                        <cell>Cloth Pads, per pair ...3s. 6d.</cell>
                        <cell>Cloth Pads, per pair ...4s. 6d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Damping Brush ...1 6</cell>
                        <cell>Damping Brush ...1 6</cell>
                        <cell>Damping Brush ...1 6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Drying Book or Sheets ...1 0</cell>
                        <cell>Drying Book or Sheets ...2 0</cell>
                        <cell>Drying Book or Sheets ...2 6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>6 Oiled Sheets ...1 0</cell>
                        <cell>6 Oiled Sheets ...1 9</cell>
                        <cell>6 Oiled Sheets ...2 0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold">Copying Books,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Of Blue or Cream-Vove Copying Paper, of First Quality</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc bold">Type-Paged by Steam Power,</hi><lb/>
                  <table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell><hi rend="sc">Quarter Round.</hi></cell>
                        <cell>Each.></cell>
                        <cell>per dox.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>500 <hi rend="ac">leaves</hi> ...</cell>
                        <cell>8s.</cell>
                        <cell>84s.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>750 <hi rend="ac">leaves</hi> ...</cell>
                        <cell>10s.</cell>
                        <cell>105s.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>1000 <hi rend="ac">leaves</hi> ...</cell>
                        <cell>12s.</cell>
                        <cell>126s.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell><hi rend="sc">Half Round.</hi></cell>
                        <cell>Each.></cell>
                        <cell>per dox.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>500 <hi rend="ac">leaves</hi> ...</cell>
                        <cell>10s.</cell>
                        <cell>102s.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>750 <hi rend="ac">leaves</hi> ...</cell>
                        <cell>13s.</cell>
                        <cell>138s.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>1000 <hi rend="ac">leaves</hi> ...</cell>
                        <cell>15s.</cell>
                        <cell>156s.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold">Copying Paper,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Best French Make.</hi><lb/><table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>s.</cell>
                        <cell>d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Two Reams for ...</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Five Reams for ...</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Ten Reams for ...</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <hi rend="sc">Best English Make.</hi><lb/><table rows="4" cols="3">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>s.</cell>
                        <cell>d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Two Reams for ...</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Five Reams for ...</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="item">
                        <cell>Ten Reams for ...</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold">Waterlow's Instantaneous Communicative Ink,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold sansSerif">For Copying Letters.</hi><lb/> The only <hi rend="ital"
                     >really fluid</hi> Copying Ink, is <hi rend="ital">used</hi> in most of the <hi
                     rend="ital">Principal Establishments in the City</hi>, and is universally admitted
                  the best yet produced.<lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">Per <hi rend="sc">Print</hi>, 2s. Per <hi rend="sc">Quart</hi>, 3s.
                     Per <hi rend="sc">Dozen Quarts</hi>, 30s. Per <hi rend="sc">Gallon</hi><lb/> Per
                        <hi rend="sc">Half-Gallon</hi>, packed for the Country, 6s. 6d. Per <hi
                        rend="sc">Gallon</hi>, do., do., 12s.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac bold">Portable Copying Machine for Travellers,</hi><lb/> 
                  <graphic url="img/73graphic5.png"/><lb/>
                  Highly finished and fitted complete, £6 6 0<lb/> Do. do. Polished Steel, £7 7 0<lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont ac sanSerif">Waterlow &amp; Sons,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont fancyFont">Manufacturing Stationers, Printers, Lithographers, and
                     Engravers,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold">65 to 68, London Wall, London.</hi><lb/>
               </p>   
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="mayFlowers">
            <pb n="74"/>
            <head><hi rend="bigFont ac bold">May Flowers.</hi></head><lb/>
            <p> 
               <hi rend="bigFont ac">V</hi><hi rend="medFont"><hi rend="ac">ery pretty indeed</hi>, as they lift up their heads like injured innocence,</hi> but in claiming protection are frequently cut down, and sometimes they are trodden under foot by some careless or incautions little stranger, thus is their glory destroyed for a whole season. There are likewise other beautiful Plants, which, lifting their heads higher in the world, are not so easily crushed, some of them, may look well in the distance, though they serve but little purpose, and frequently become offensive when brought into immediate proximity with our senses.<lb/>
               But the May <hi rend="sc">flowers</hi> of <hi rend="sc">art, taste, style, fashion,</hi> and <hi rend="sc">ingenuity</hi>, the efforts of the talented and the Industrious, without imperfections, and associated with every Gentleman's comfort, are the <hi rend="sc">spring fashions</hi> all ready at the universally celebrated Establishments of <hi rend="sc">E. Morrs &amp; Son</hi>. These Garments are rich as Nature's lovely Flowers: they are useful, light, and tasteful habiliments, uninjured by the Wet, and unfading in the Sun, cogenial to one's feelings as a Bleak House would be on a sultry day.<lb/>
               The variety of May Flowers is one of the most cheering vestiges of the season. The thousands of forms tints, and colours, which they display is a source of endless gratification to admirers of natural productions. The variety displayed in the Spring Styles of Dress at <hi rend="sc">E. Moses &amp; Son</hi>'s is of the most ample and gratiftying character, exceeding all previous grand expositions, unequalled for elegance manifested in thousands of fabrics. of different colours, shades, and patterns, while the unparalleled skill for which <hi rend="sc">E. Moses &amp; Son</hi>'s <hi rend="sc">Establishments</hi> have been for many years so celebrated, has formed them with elevated taste into the most <hi rend="ital">novel, varied,</hi> and <hi rend="ital">fashionable</hi> Styles of <hi rend="sc">Dress</hi>, suitable for all classes, for young or aged, for nobility, clergy, gentry, tradesmen, or mechanics, in shapes and devices more pleasing, comfortable, and useful than ever presented before.<lb/>
               <hi rend="medFont bold ac">List of Prices.</hi><lb/>
               <table rows="7" cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac sansSerif medFont">Winter Overcoats</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>The new Bequeme Overcoat, designed by <hi rend="sc">E. Moses &amp; Son</hi>...£1 5s. to</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Pen Coats, from...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Coloured and Plain Witney Overcoats, in all shapes, from...15s. to</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>The Bulwer...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>The Premier, expressly made for this establishment...12s. to</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>The Albert Cape, made in the most approved waterproof materials, including the Devonshire Kersey, lined throughout, and velvet collar...£1 5s. to</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table rows="10" cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac sansSerif medFont">Boys' Winter Overcoats</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Chesterfield, from...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>The Byron Jacket and Overcoat, in all materials...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Prince of Wales' Wrapper, elegantly trimmed, and in various materials...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Dress Coats...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Super ditto...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Best manufactured...</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Frock Coats...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Super ditto...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Best manufactured...</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table rows="7"  cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac sansSerif medFont">Waistcoats.</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Fancy Vest, from...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Witney and plain cloth...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Satin, plain and figure...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Black cloth...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Ditto, best manufactured...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>White Marcella...4s. 6d. to</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table rows="7"  cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac sansSerif medFont">Trousers.</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Fancy Trousers, from...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Buckskin...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Black cloth...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Black and Fancy Doeskin...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Best Black Cassimere Trousers...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Boys' Hussar and Tunic Suits...13s. to.</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table rows="4"  cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac sansSerif medFont">Ladies' Riding Habits.</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Summer cloth, with 1/2 train...</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Superior ditto...</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Superfine ditto...</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  
               </table>
               <table rows="5"  cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac sansSerif medFont">Liveries.</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Page's suit...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Footman's...</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Groom's...</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Coachman's...</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                 
               </table>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell><hi rend="ac bold medFont">Mourning.</hi></cell>
                     <cell>£</cell>
                     <cell>s.</cell>
                     <cell>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Suit complete...</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="item">
                     <cell>Boys' ditto...</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
               </table><lb/>
               Made to Measure in Five Hours.<lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">Notice.</hi>--The Shawl and Fur Departments are now replete with every novelty of the season.<lb/>
               A New Book, entitled "The Library of Elegance," containing full directions for self-measurement, can be had gratis on application or forwarded post free to any part of the kingdom.<lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">Observe.</hi>--Any article purchased either ready made or made to measure, if not approved of, wil be exchanged or the money returned.<lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">Caution.</hi>--<hi rend="sc">E. Moses &amp; Son</hi> have no connection with any other house, in or out of London, except the following:--<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">London City Establishments:--154, 155, 156, and 157, Minories; 83, 84, 85, 86, Aldgate, opposite the Church, all communicating.<lb/>London West End Branch:--506, 507, 508, New Oxford-street; 1, 2, 3, Hartstreet, all communicating.<lb/>Bradford, Yorkshire Branch, 19, Bridge-street.<lb/>Sheffield Branch, 36, Fargate.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ac">Tailors, Clothiers, Hatters, Hosiers, Furriers, Boot &amp; Shoe Makers, and General Outfitters for Ladies and Gentlement.</hi><lb/>
               <hi rend="ital">The Establishments are closed from sunset, on Friday, till sunset, on Saturday, when business is resumed till 12 o'clock.</hi><lb/>
            </p>
         </div>        
         <div type="ad" xml:id="healandsons">
            <head><hi rend="ac bigFont sansSerif">Heal and Son's Illustrated Catalogue of Bedsteads,</hi></head><lb/>
            <p>
               Sent free by post.<lb/>
               <graphic url="img/75graphic.png"/><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont sideways right">It contains Designs and Prices of upwards of One Hundred Different Bedsteads, </hi><hi rend="medFont sideways left">In Iron, Brass, Japanned Wood, Polished Birch, Mahogany, Rosewood, and Walnut Tree Woods;</hi><lb/>
                  Also their<lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac bigFont bold">Priced List of Bedding.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="ital">Their New Waverooms enable them to keep one of each design fixed for inspection.</hi><lb/>
                  They have also, in addition to their usual stock, a great variety of the best designs of<lb/>
                  <hi rend="ac bigFont bold sansSerif">Parisan Bedsteads,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Both in wood and iron, which they have just imported.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="hugeFont ac bold">Heal &amp; Son,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont sc">Bedstead and Bedding Manufacturers,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="medFont bold">196, (opposite the Chapel), Tottenham Court Road.</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="sc">Bradbury and Evans, Printers, Whitefriars.</hi>
            </p> 
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">Dickens is not the first author to publish a serialized form of the
               novel, this is attributed to an author known only as <hi rend="italics">Boz</hi>
               through the publishing company Chapman and Hall. Boz's work, popularly known back
               then as the <hi rend="italics">Pickwick Papers</hi>, were selling as much as 40,000
               copies per month in 1836. Nevertheless, Dickens is considered as the first already
               commercially successful author, as he already finished his 8th novel -- <hi
                  rend="italics">David Copperfield</hi>, who then published in serialized form. See
                  <ref type="biblio" target="#steinlight2006">Steinlight, 2006</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Although this appears to be a letter to Charles Dickens, it is an
               adevertisement, nonetheless. In this sort of letter, the company thanked Dickens for
               his work on Bleak House and also mentioned his other popular work such as <hi
                  rend="italics">David Copperfield</hi>, to perhaps show sincerity, and then went on
               to promote and rave about their products. This strategy of connecting the
               advertisement to the source material, either to Bleak House or to Charles Dickens
               himself, is seen in other ads of those days. See for example <ref type="biblio"
                  target="#li2018">Li, 2018</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="byron"><persName><roleName>Lord</roleName><forename>George</forename>
                  Gordon <surname>Byron</surname></persName>, <date type="birth" when="1788-01-01"
                  >January 22, 1788</date>-<date type="death" when="1824-04-19">April 19,
                  1824</date></note>
            <note xml:id="disraeliB"
                     ><persName><forename>Benjamin</forename><surname>Disraeli</surname></persName>,
                  <date type="birth" when="1804-12-21">December 21, 1804</date>-<date type="death"
                  when="1881-04-19">April 19, 1881</date></note>
            <note xml:id="Dick"><persName><surname>Dickens</surname>,
                  <forename>Charles</forename></persName>, <date type="birth" when="1812-02-17"
                  >February 17, 1812</date>-<date type="death" when="1870-06-09">June 9,
               1870</date></note>
            <note xml:id="n3"><persName><roleName>Rev</roleName>. <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname>Cumming</surname>
                  <roleName>D. D.</roleName></persName>, (<date type="birth" when="1807"
                  >1807</date>-<date type="death" when="1881">1881</date>) was a prolific writer and
               a notable minister of the National Scottish Church. He was most known for his
               interest in the prophesied apocalypse, his anti-Catholic views, and his dislike
               towards Rome. See <ref type="biblio" target="#ellisonCarol2002">Ellison &amp; Carol,
                  2002</ref></note>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="steinlight2006" type="article"><author><surname>Steinlight</surname>,
                        <forename>Emily</forename></author>.<title level="a">'Anti-Bleak House':
                     Advertising and the Victorian Novel</title>.<title level="j">Narrative</title>,
                  vol. <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope> no. <biblScope unit="issue"
                     >2</biblScope>, <date>2006</date>, p.<biblScope unit="page"
                  >132-162</biblScope>. <publisher>Project MUSE</publisher>, <ptr
                     target="https://dx.doi.org/10.1353/nar.2006.0007"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="li2018"><author><surname>Li</surname>,
                     <forename>Sumiao</forename></author>.<title level="a">FASHION, FASHIONABLE
                     INTELLIGENCE, AND THE VICTORIAN NOVEL: THE VERSATILE CASE OF BLEAK
                     HOUSE</title>.<title level="j">Victorian Literature and Culture</title>, vol.
                     <biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue"
                     >1</biblScope>, <date>2018</date>, pp.<biblScope unit="page">23-55</biblScope>.
                     <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1060150317000316"/>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ellisonCarol2002"><author><persName><surname>Ellison</surname>,
                           <forename>Robert</forename></persName></author> and
                           <author><persName><surname>Carol</surname>,
                           <forename>Engelhardt</forename></persName></author>. “<title level="a"
                           ><persName><forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Cumming</surname></persName> -- An Introduction.</title>”
                     <publisher>The Victorian Web</publisher>, <date when="2002-08-27">27 Aug.
                     2002</date>, <ptr target="https://victorianweb.org/religion/sermons/rhe12.html"
                  />. </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
