<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bleak House</title>
            <author><ref target="#Dick"/></author>
            <editor>Steven Haker</editor>
            <editor>Karalee Harris</editor>
            <editor>Paul Jason Perez</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Bleak House itself is a fiction about the lives of the rich and poor in London
               society during the Victorian era. However, our main focus is on the advertisements
               appearing before and after the serialized novel. These advertisements are appealing
               to a certain group of consumers during the mid-Victorian era of London. From our
               edition, readers would be able to peek into the world of 1852 when Bleak House was
               being published as a serial. The advertisements present in Bleak House are an
               artifact of that time; though they were likely ignored during it, they now provide a
               unique window into that time period. The audience for this edition would likely be
               people researching this time period rather than people who want to read Bleak House
               as a text; this means that it would lend itself moreso to scholars rather than
               laypeople.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Bleak House</title>
                  <author><ref target="#Dick">Dickens, Charles</ref>, <date type="birth"
                        >1812</date>-<date type="death">1870</date></author>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>illustrated by</resp>
                     <persName xml:id="HKB">Browne, Hablot Knight, <date type="born"
                           >1815</date>-<date type="death">1882</date></persName>
                  </respStmt>
                  <edition>[First edition]</edition>
                  <extent>70 pp</extent>
                  <publisher xml:id="BandE">Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
                  <pubPlace><placeName type="city">London,
                     <country>England</country></placeName></pubPlace>
                  <date><date when="1852">1852</date>-<date when="1853">1853</date></date>
                  <idno type="OCLC">38689984</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>This edition focuses on the advertisements that appeared alongside the original
               serialized publication of Bleak House written by Charles Dickens and illustrated by
               Hablot Knight Browne. This first edition was published in monthly parts between 1852
               and 1853 and a well preserved complete set is available at the Special Collections of
               the University of Washington Libraries. While the novel itself has been widely
               studied for its plot, characters, and social commentary, the ads printed in each
               issue are often overlooked. These advertisements offer a lot of information about
               what people were buying, what they cared about, and how products and services were
               marketed to them. From cures for illnesses to new inventions and fashion trends, the
               ads show what everyday life might have looked like for mid-Victorian era of
               London.</p>
            <p>Our approach treats each advertisement as a single unit of analysis, carefully
               examining its components such as images, product descriptions, catalogs,
               testimonials, and more. What remedies for ailments were marketed to the public 150
               years ago? Do they resemble the products sold to us today? How about their fashion,
               do some of those trends still exists today? What can these advertisements reveal
               about Victorian-era society, and how might those insights still resonate with our
               present-day culture? These are the questions we found compelling, and we hope you, as
               the reader, will find them just as intriguing.</p>
            <p>In creating this edition, our team chose to present a diplomatic transcription to
               preserve the original appearance and appeal of these advertisements as they were seen
               by the public. We maintained the original language and the layout of images alongside
               the text. In cases where words were hyphenated due to space constraints in the
               original print, we have standardized them into single words for clarity. We've also
               highlighted distinctive elements within the advertisements that we believe offer
               valuable opportunities for further analysis of print media from that era. We hope you
               enjoy this unique edition of Bleak House.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="edmiston">
            <pb n="0"/>
            <p><emph rend="ac">To sportsmen, tourist, &amp; travelers.</emph>
               <graphic url="../images/p0_1.png"/>
               <emph rend="ac">Edmiston's pocket siphonia</emph>, or waterproof overcoat. weight 10
                  oz.<graphic url="img/p0_2.png"/>Sole Manufacturer of the celebrated Pocket
               Siphonia, remarkable for its lightness and softness of texture, adapted for
               Sportsmen, Travellers, and Tourists, easily folded to carry in the Pocket or on
               Saddle ; the most important feature in this Waterproofing is being mineralised, which
               effectually resists the powerful heat of the sun and the most violent rains, also
               obviating the stickiness and unpleasant smell peculiar to all other Waterproofs.--
               Price according to size, 40s. to 55s. ; all silk throughout, 50s. to 65s.
               Measurement, length of coat, and size round the chest over the coat <graphic
                  url="img/p0_3.png"/>Notice--Name &amp; address stamped inside. None others are
               genuine. Edmiston &amp; Son, 416 &amp; 69, Strand Near the Adelphi Theatre.</p>
            <p><emph rend="ac">Opinions of the press.</emph>Waterproof--<q type="testimony">The
                  lightest and most effectual, is the Siphonia, made by Edmiston &amp; Son, of 69,
                  Strand ; they can be carried in the hat or pocket.</q>-- Bell's Life, April 20th,
               1851. <q type="testimony">A new waterproof garment adapted to the very changeable
                  weather of the season, has been manufactured by Edmiston &amp; Son. It is
                  remarkably light and soft, and may be carried in the pocket. This is really an
                  ingenious substitute for the cumbersome great coat or the troublesome
                  umbrella.</q>--Home News, May 24th, 1851.</p>
            <p><graphic url="img/p0_4.png"/>Leggings or Overall. Yacht Jackets. Fishing and Shooting
               Hats or Caps Driving Gloves. Cricketing do. Gun Covers. Gig Aprons. Sou-Westers.
                  Goloshes.<graphic url="img/p0_5.png"/>Ladies' Capes, with Hoods. Do. Paletots. Air
               Cushions. Do. Pillows. Do. Beds. India Rubber Portable Folding Baths. Nursing Aprons.
               Crib Sheets.<graphic url="img/p0_6.png"/></p>
            <p>The newly invented Swimming Gloves, Of great propelling power. <emph rend="ac"
                  >Edmiston's life-belts none should be without.</emph>Fishing and shooting boots,
               soft and pliable, require no dressing, and every description of India Rubber and
               Gutta Percha Goods, Piping, Tubing for Watering Gardens, &amp;c. Belfast--Albion
               Cloth Company. Edinbrugh--Grieve &amp; Oliver, Princes-street. Liverpool--Radcliffe
               &amp; Corlet, Castle-street; J.H. Smith, 22, Lord-street. Shaftsbury--Jas. Seagrove,
               Brothers. Southampton--Batten &amp; Lukes. <emph rend="ac">London: Edmiston &amp;
                  Son, 416 &amp; 69, Strand, near Adelphi.</emph></p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="dakinCompany">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <opener><salute><name rend="ac">Chas. Dickens, Esq.</name> Sir,</salute></opener>
            <p>We thank you for your new work. Though its name is <q rend="ac">Bleak House,</q>we
               know well that its inmates will be warm and life-like. We thank you for it, not only
               for the pleasure that we, in common with all its other readers, shall receive in its
               perusal, but we thank you on more solid grounds; ,ve thank you for it as a matter of
               business.</p>
            <p>If it be true, that an observer must know of the existence of a place before he can
               arrange for visiting it, it must be equally true, that the public must be aware of
               the existence of an establishment before they can contemplate patronising it; and
               further, that they must be aware of the advantages offered by a particular concern
               before they will select that in preference to any other. On these grounds, then, we
               thank you for <q rend="ac">Bleak House</q> in a business point of view, because it
               affords us an opportunity of conveying to all its readers the advantages or our
               Establishment, and the principles upon which it continues to be conducted.</p>
            <p>Many thousands of readers have, we doubt not, entered upon their tasks since even <q
                  rend="ac"><name type="person">David Copperfield</name></q> monthly appeared,
               between his <q>green leaves,</q> and some of these readers may note with favour the
               statement we here subjoin.</p>
            <p><q>We keep for the selection of purchaser all kinds or Tea and Coffee fit for use
                  imported into this country, and we supply them at the most moderate cost at which
                  they can possibly be sold.</q></p>
            <p><q>We have endeavoured to render ourselves particularly celebrated for supplying Teas
                  of the most sound and excellent qualities.</q></p>
            <p><q>We have a Patented Invention for Roasting Coffee, Cocoa, &amp;c. in Silver. By
                  this plan the ordinary evils of roasting such produce in a cylinder made of base
                  metal are avoided, whilst the cost of the produce is not increased.</q></p>
            <p><q>We deliver by our Vans all Orders from any part of the <name type="place"
                     >Metropolitan Districts</name>, within eight miles of <name type="place">St.
                     Paul's</name>, on tho day after such orders are given.</q></p>
            <p><q>We also send into the Country, free of carriage, all Orders, if they be
                  accompanied by a remittance for payment, whether by half-notes, Post Office Order,
                  or otherwise, provided the goods ordered amount to £2 or upwards.</q></p>
            <p><q>We sell our goods only for immediate payment. Our tariff of profit is fixed
                  without allowing for the interest on capital necessary to support a heavy amount
                  of debts.</q></p>
            <p>For the facilities that this excellent medium of publicity has allowed us for making
               known the above particulars, we sincerely thank you, and we trust and hope that by
               our care and attention, and by the excellence of the Goods we supply, those readers
               of <q rend="ac">Bleak House</q> who may turn their favourable patronage to <q>Number
                  One</q>, will never regret having glanced over the first page of its white paper,
               on this 1st day of May.</p>
            <p>Wishing that you may long live to give birth to heaps of <q rend="ac">Household
                  Words</q>, and to numerous Brothers and Sisters of <q rend="ac"><name
                     type="person">David Copperfield</name>,</q></p>
            <closer><salute>We remain, Sir, Very respectfully, Your obedient Servants</salute><name
                  type="organization">Dakin &amp; Company</name><location>
                  <address>
                     <street>No. 1, St. Paul's Church-yard</street>
                     <settlement>London</settlement>
                  </address>
               </location><date when="1852-05-01">May 1st, 1852</date></closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ad-group" xml:id="gardeningAndBotany">
            <pb n="2"/>
            <head>Works on Gardening and Botany.</head>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="paxtonFlowerGarden">
               <head rend="ac">Paxton's Flower-Garden.</head>
               <p rend="ac">Edited by <name type="person">Dr. Lindley</name> and <name type="person"
                     >Sir Joseph Paxton</name></p>
               <p rend="ac">Each volume is illustrated by thirty-six highly finished plates and more
                  than two hundred beautiful engravings on wood.</p>
               <p>Volumes I, and II, are published. Price 33s. each, elegantly bound in cloth.</p>
               <p>&#8757;This work is also published in Monthly Parts of which 27 are published, and
                  may be procured by order of any bookseller. Price 2s. 6d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="paxtonBotanicalDictionary">
               <head rend="ac">Paxton’s botanical dictionary.</head>
               <p>Comprising the names, history, and culture of all plants known in <name
                     type="place">Britain</name>; with a full explanation of technical terms. Crown
                  8vo, 16s.</p>
               <p>&#8757;The supplement, containing all the new plants since the first edition, may
                  be had separately, price 5s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="ad" xml:id="theElementsOfBotany">
               <head rend="ac">The elements of botany; Structural and physiological.</head>
               <p>With a glossary of technical terms, and numerous illustrations. By <name rend="ac"
                     type="person">Dr. Lindley</name>. 12s. cloth.</p>
               <p>&#8757;The glossary may be had separately, price 5s. cloth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="nortonPills">
            <pb n="58"/>
            <p>
               <fw type="header"><emph rend="ac hugeFont">Important Family Medicine</emph></fw><lb/>
               <emph rend="ac bold hugeFont">Norton's Camomile Pills,</emph>
               <emph rend="ac medFont">The<lb/> most certain preserver of health; </emph><emph
                  rend="sc">A<lb/>mild, yet speedy, safe, and<lb/></emph><emph
                  rend="ac bold medFont">Effectual Aid in cases of indigestion,<lb/>And all stomach
                  complaints,<lb/></emph><emph rend="sc">And, as a natural consequence,</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="sc medFont">A purifier of the blood, and a sweetener of the whole
                  system.</emph><lb/>Indigestion is a weakness or want of power of the digestive
               juices in the stomach to convert what we eat and drink into healthy matter, for the
               proper nourishment of the whole system. It is caused by every thing which weakens the
               system in general, or the stomach in particular. From it proceed nearly all diseases
               to which we are liable; for it is very certain, that if we could always keep the
               stomach right we should only die by old age or accident. Indigestion produces a great
               variety of unpleasant sensations: amongst the prominent of its miserable effects are
               a want of, or an inordinate, appetite, sometimes attended with a constant craving for
               drink, a distension or feeling enlargement of the stomach, flatulency, heartburn,
               pains in the stomach, acidity, unpleasant taste in the mouth, perhaps sickness,
               rumbling noise in the bowels: in some cases of depraved digestions there is nearly a
               complete disrelish for food, but still the appetite is not greatly impaired, as at
               the stated period of meals persons so afflicted can eat heartily, although without
               much gratification; a long train of nervous symptoms are also frequent attendants,
               general debility, great languidess, and incapacity for exertion. The minds of persons
               so afflicted frequently become irraitable and desponding, and great anxiety is
               observable in the countenance; they appear thoughtful, melancholy, and dejected,
               under great apprehension of some imaginary danger, will start at any unexpected noise
               or occurrence, and become so agitated that they require some time to calm and collect
               themselves; yet for all this the mind is exhilarated without much difficulty;
               pleasing events, society, will for a time dissipate all appearance of disease; but
               the excitement produced by an agreeable change vanishes soon after the cause has gone
               by. Other symptoms are, voilent palpitations, restlessness, the sleep disturbed by
               frightful dreams and startings, and affording little or no refreshment: occasionally
               there is much moaning, with a sense of weight and oppression upon the chest,
               nightmare, &amp;c.<lb/>It is almost impossible to enumerate all the symptoms of this
               first invader upon the constitution, as in a hundred cases of <emph rend="ital"
                  >Indigestion</emph> there will probably be something peculiar to each; but, be
               they what they may, they are all occassioned by the food becoming a burden rather
               than a support to the stomach; and in all its stages the medicine most wanted is that
               which will afford speedy and effectual assistance to the digestive organs, and give
               energy to the nervous and muscular systems,-nothing can more speedily or with more
               certainty effect so desirable an object than <emph rend="ital">Norton's Extract of
                  Camomile Flowers</emph>. The herb has from time immemorial been highly esteemed in
               England as a grateful anodyne, imparting an aromatic bitter to the taste, and a
               pleasing degree of warmth and strength to the stomach; and in all cases of
               indigestion, gout in the stomach, windy colic, and general weakness, it has for ages
               been strongly recommended by the most eminent practitioners as very useful and
               beneficial. The great, indeed only, objection to its use has been the large quantity
               of water which it takes to dissolve a small part of the flowers and which must be
               taken with it into the<pb n="59"/><fw type="page_number" place="top_right">2</fw>
               stomach. It requires a quarter of a pint of boiling water to dissolve the soluble
               portion of one drachm of camomile flowers; and, when one or even two ounces may be
               taken with advantage, it must at once be seen how impossible it is to take a proper
               dose of this wholesome herb in the form of tea; and the only reason why it has not
               long since been placed the very first in rank of all restorative medicines is that in
               taking it the stomach has always been loaded with water which tends in a great
               measure to counteract, and very frequently wholly to destroy the effect. It must be
               evident that loading a weak stomach with a large purpose of conveying into it a small
               quantity of medicine must be injurious; and that the medicines must possess powerful
               renovating properties only to counteract the bad effects likely to be produced by the
               water. Generally speaking, this has been the case with camomile flowers, a herb
               possessing the highest restorative qualities, and when properly taken, decidedly the
               most speedy restorer, and the most certain preserver of health.<lb/>These <emph
                  rend="sc"> pills</emph> are wholly <emph rend="sc">camomile</emph>, prepared by a
               peculiar process, accidentally discovered, and known only to the proprietor, and
               which he firmly believes to be one of the most valuable modern discoveries in
               medicine, by which all the essential and extractice matter of more than an ounce of
               the flowers is concentrated in four moderate-sized pills. Experience has afforded the
               most ample proof that they possess all the fine aromatic and stomachic properties for
               which the herb has been esteemed; and, as they are taken into the stomach
               unencumbered by any diluting or indigestible substance, in the same degree has their
               benefit been more immediate and decided. Mild in their operation and pleasant in
               their effect, they may be taken at any age, and under any circumstance, without
               danger or inconvenience. A person exposed to cold and wet a whole day or night could
               not possibly receive any injury from taking them, but, on the contrary, they would
               effectually prevent a cold being taken. After a long acquaintance with and strict
               observance of the medicinal properties of <emph rend="ital">Norton's Camomile
                  Pills</emph>, it is only doing them justice to say, that they are really the most
               valuable of all <emph rend="sc">tonic medicines</emph>. By the word tonic is meant a
               medicine which gives strength to the stomach sufficient to digest in proper
               quantities all wholesome food, which increases the power of every nerve and muscle of
               the human body, or, in other words, invigorates the nervous and muscular systems. The
               solidity or firmness of the whole tissue of the body which so quickly follows the use
               of <emph rend="ital">Norton's Camomile Pills</emph>, their certain and speedy effects
               in repairing the partial dilapidations from time or intemperance, and their lasting
               salutary in fluence on the whole frame, is most con vincing, that in the smallest
               compass is contained the largest quantity of the tonic principle, of so peculiar a
               nature as to pervade the whole system, through which it diffuses health and strength
               sufficient to resist the formation of disease, and also to fortify the consitution
               against contagion; as such, their general use is strongly recommended as a
               preventative during the prevalence of malignant fever or other infectious diseases,
               and to persons attending sick rooms they are invaluable as in no one instance have
               they ever failed in preventing the taking of illness, even under the most trying
               circumstances.<lb/> As <emph rend="ital"> Norton's Camomile Pills</emph> are
               particularly recommended for all stomach complaints or indigestion, it will probably
               be expected that some advice should be given respecting diet, though after all that
               has been written upon the subject, after the publication of volume upon volume, after
               the country has, as it were, been inundated with practical essays on diet, as a means
               of prolonging life, it would be unnecessary to say more, did we not feel it our duty
               to make the humble endeavor of inducing the public to regard them not, but to adopt
               that course which is dictated by nature, by reason, and common sense. Those persons
               who study the wholesomes, and are governed by the opinions of writers on diet, are
               uniformly both unhealthy in body and weak in mind. There can be no doubt that the
               palate is designed to inform us what is proper for the stomach, and of course that
               must best instruct us what food to take and what to avoid: we want no other adviser.
               Nothing can be more clear than that those articles which are agreeable to the taste
               were by nature intended for our food and sustenance, whether liquid or solid, foreign
               or of native production: if they are pure and unadulterated, no harm need be dreaded
               by their<pb n="60"/><fw type="page_number" place="top_right">3</fw> use; they will
               only injure by abuse. Consequently, whatever the palate approves, eat and drink
               always in moderation, but never in excess; keeping in mind that the first process of
               digestion is performed in the mouth, the second in the stomach; and that, in order
               that the stomach may be able to do its work properly, it is requisite the first
               should be well performed; this consists in masticating or chewing the solid food, so
               as to break down and separate the fibres and small substances of meat and vegetables,
               mixing them well, and blending the whole together before they are swallowed; and it
               is particularly urged upon all to take plenty of time to their meals and never eat in
               haste. If you conform to this short and simple, but comprehensive advice, and find
               that there are various things which others eat and drink with pleasure and without
               inconvenience, and which would be pleasant to yourself only that they disagree, you
               may at once conclude that the fault is in the stomach, that it does not possess the
               power which it ought to do, that it wants assistance, and the sooner that assistance
               is afforded the better. A very short trial of this medicine will best prove how soon
               it will put the stomach in a condition to perform with ease all the work which nature
               intended for it. By its use you will soon be able to enjoy, in moderation, whatever
               is agreeable to the taste, and unable to name one individual article of food which
               disagrees with or sits unpleasantly on the stomach. Never forget that a small meal
               well digested affords more nourishment to the system than a large one, even of the
               same food, when digested imperfectly. Let the dish be ever so delicious, ever so
               enticing a variety offered, the bottle ever so enchanting, never forget that
               temperance tends to preserve health, and that health is the soul of enjoyment. But
               should an impropriety be at any time, or ever so often, committed, by which the
               stomach becomes overloaded or disordered, render it immediate aid by taking a dose of
                  <emph rend="ital">Norton's Camomile Pills</emph>, which will so promtly assist in
               carrying off the burden thus imposed upon it that all will soon be right
               again.<lb/>It is most certainly true that every person in his lifetime consumes a
               quantity of noxious matter, which if taken at one meal would be fatal; it is these
               small quantities of noxious matter, which are introduced into our food, either by
               accident or wilful adulteration, which we find so often upset the stomach, and not
               unfrequently lay the foundation of illness, and perhaps final ruination to health. To
               preserve the constitution, it should be our constant care, if possible, to counteract
               the effect of these small quantities of unwholesome matter; and whenever, in that
               way, an enemy to the consitution finds its way into the stomach, a friend should be
               immediately sent after it, which would prevent its mischievous effects, and expel it
               altogether; no better friend can be found, nor one which will perform the task with
               greater certainty, than <emph rend="sc">norton's camomile pills</emph>. And let it be
               observed that the longer this medicine is taken the less it will be wanted; it can in
               no case become habitual, as its entire action is to give energy and force to the
               stomach, which is the spring of life, the source from which the whole frame draws its
               succour and support. After an excess of eating or drinking, and upon every occasion
               of the general health being at all disturbed, these <emph rend="sc">pills</emph>
               should be immediately taken, as they will stop and eradicate disease at its
               commencement. Indeed it is most confidently asserted, that by the timely use of this
               medicine only, and a common degree of caution, any person may enjoy all the comforts
               within his reach, may pass through life without an illness, and with the certainty of
               attaining a healthy <emph rend="sc">old age</emph>.<lb/> On account of their volatile
               properties, they must be kept in bottles; and if closely corked their qualities are
               neither impaired by time nor injured by any change of climate whatever. Price 13 1/2
               d. and 2s.9d.each, with full directions. The large bottle contains the quantity of
               three small ones, or <emph rend="sc">pills</emph> equal to fourteen ounce of <emph
                  rend="sc">camomile flowers</emph>. <lb/><emph rend="medFont">Sold by nearly all
                  respectable Medicine Vendors.</emph><lb/><emph rend="bold medFont">Be particular
                  to ask for "<emph rend="ac">norton's pills</emph>," and do not be persuaded to
                  purchase an imitation.</emph>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="godfreyFlowers">
            <pb n="61"/>
            <p>
               <fw type="header"><emph rend="bold sc MedFont">A Clear
                  Complexion.</emph></fw><lb/><emph rend="ac fancyFont medFont">Godfrey's Extract of
                  Elder Flowers</emph><lb/>is strongly recommended for Softening, Improving,
               Beautifying, and Preserving the SKIN, and giving it a blooming and charming
               appearance; being at once a most fragrant perfume and delightful cosmetic. It will
               completely remove Tan, Sunburn, Redness, &amp;c.; and, by its Balsamic and Healing
               qualities, render the skin soft, pliable, and free from dryness, scurf, &amp;c.;
               clear it from every humour, pimple, or eruption; and, by continuing its use only a
               short time, the skin will become and continue soft and smooth, and the complexion
               perfectly clear and beautiful. In the process of shaving it is invaluable, as it
               allays the irritation and smarting pain, annihilates every pimple and all roughness,
               and renders the skin smooth and firm. It protects the skin from the effects of the
               cold winds and damp atmosphere which prevail during the winter months, and will be
               found beyond all praise to use as a Family Lotion on all occasions.<lb/>Sold in
               Bottles, price 2s.9d., with Directions for using it, by all Medicine Vendors and
               Perfumers. </p>

         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="simcoGout">
            <p>
               <fw type="header"><emph rend="bold sc medFont">A Cure for Gout and
                  Rheumatism.</emph></fw><lb/><emph rend="normFont"><emph rend="ital">"The Eighth
                     Plague,"</emph> said the learned Dr. Johnson, <emph rend="ital">"is the Gout,
                     and that man who discovers a Medicine to alleviate its torments deserves well
                     of his country; but he who can effect a cure should have a Monument raised to
                     his memory as high as St. Paul's, as wide as the Thames, and as lasting as
                     time."</emph></emph><lb/><emph rend="ac fancyFont medFont">Simco's Gout and
                  Rheumatic Pills</emph><lb/>are sold by nearly all Medicine Venders at <emph
                  rend="ital">1s. 1 1/2d., and 2s.9d. per Box; the former containing does for</emph>
               five <emph rend="ital">and the latter for</emph> fifteen <emph rend="ital"
                  >days</emph>; and so many individuals, who considered themselves martyrs to Gout
               or Rheumatism, are now ready and willing to bear testimony of the wonderful effects
               of Simco's Pills, that the Proprietor fearlessly challenges the whole world to
               produce Medicine which at all deserves to be compared to them. There are <emph
                  rend="ital">many</emph> instances in which person have been completely restored to
               health and activity by taking <emph rend="sc">Simco's Gout Pills</emph>, who have
               suffered from Rheumatic Gout for several years, and had drawn on a miserable
               existence, having lost the use of their limbs, believing that death alone could
               terminate their sufferings.<lb/> Whilst taking the Pills, no particular rules or
               restrictions are necessary, as they are warranted not to contain any preparation of
               Mercury whatever; they seldom produce perspiration, purging, or sickness, but
               invariably improve the general health, sharpen the appetite, and facilitate
               digestion. Those periodically subject to Gout, Rheumatic Gout, Rheumatic Fever,
               &amp;c., should keep these Pills by them, as by their timely use an approaching
               attack may always be averted, and the tendency of these complaints to attack a vital
               part be effectually counteracted. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="simcoLinseed">
            <p>
               <fw type="header"><emph rend="bold sc medFont">Influenza, Coughs, and
                  Colds.</emph></fw><lb/><emph rend="ac fancyFont medFont">Simco's Essence of
                  Linseed</emph><lb/>is the most efficacious remedy ever discovered for the relief
               of persons suffering from Influenza; the first two doses generally arrest the
               progress of this distressing complaint, and a little perseverance completely removes
               it. Children's Coughs, as well as recent ones in Adults, will be removed by a few
               doses (frequently by the first); and Asthmatic persons, who previously had not been
               able to lie down in bed, have received the utmost benefit from the use of<lb/><emph
                  rend="ac medFont">Simco's Essence of Linseed.</emph><lb/>Sold in Bottles at <emph
                  rend="ital">1s 1/2d.</emph>, and <emph rend="ital">2s. 9d.</emph> each. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="ad" xml:id="williamAuto">
            <pb n="62"/>
            <p>
               <fw type="header"><emph rend="fancyFont hugeFont">The Autobiograph of William
                     Jerdan;</emph></fw><lb/>
               <emph rend="sc">with his</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="bold medFont">Literary, Political, and Social Reminiscences</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="fancyFont medFont">And Correspondence,</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="sc medFont">During the last forty years</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="bold medFont">As Editor of the "Sun" Newspaper, 1812-17, &amp; of the
                  "Literary Gazette," 1817-50,</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="sc">IN CONNECTION WITH MOST OF THE EMINENT PERSON WHO HAVE BEEN
                  DISTINGUISED IN THE PAST HALF CENTURY AS STATESMEN, POETS, AUTHORS, MEN OF
                  SCIENCE, ARTISTS, ETC.</emph><lb/>The First Volume, price 5s., with a Portrait of
               the Author, Engraved by <emph rend="sc">Robinson</emph>, from a Painting by <emph
                  rend="sc">Harlowe</emph>, will appear on the <date when="1852-05-01">1st of
                  May</date>, and it is proposed to complete the Work in Four or Six Volumes, to be
               published Quarterly.<lb/>
               <emph rend="ital bold">Among many Distinguished Names introduced in the Narrative and
                  Correspondence will be found,</emph>
               <list>
                  <item><surname>Ainsworth</surname>, <forename>W. Harrison</forename>, and
                        <forename>W. Francis</forename></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Arbuthnot</surname>,
                        <forename>Charles</forename></persName></item>
                  <item><persName>Bangor, <roleName>Bishop</roleName> of
                     (Magendle)*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bannister</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Barham</surname> (Ingoldsby)*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Barrow</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        John</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Barry</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                     C.*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Blackwood</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Blessington</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lady</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bowles</surname>, Lislo*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Braham</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bray</surname>,
                     <roleName>Mrs</roleName>.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bristol</surname>, <roleName>Bishop</roleName> of
                        (Gray)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Brougham</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Bulwer</surname>, Lytton <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        E.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Burgess</surname>, <roleName>Bishop</roleName> of
                        Sallisbury</persName></item>
                  <item><ref target="#byron"/><persName><surname>Byron</surname>,
                           <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Campbell</surname>, Thomas</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Canning</surname>, George</persName></item>
                  <item><surname>Chambers</surname>, <forename>W.</forename> &amp;
                        <forename>R.</forename></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Chantrey</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        F.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Clarendon</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Coleridge</surname>, S.T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Colman</surname>, G.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Colton</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Cooke</surname> (tragodian), Tom*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Cooke</surname>, T.P.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Croly</surname>,
                     <roleName>Dr.</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Cunningham</surname>, Allan</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>De Tabley</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><ref target="#Dick"><persName><surname>Dickens</surname>,
                        Charles</persName></ref></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Disraeli</surname>, Isaac and <ref target="#disraeliB"
                           >Benjamin</ref></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Eldon</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Erskine</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Essex</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lady</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Faraday</surname>,
                        <roleName>Professor</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Farnborough</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Freeling</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        Francis</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Galt</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Godwin</surname>, William</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Grenville</surname>, T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Griffin</surname>, G.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Guizot</surname>, M.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hall</surname>, <roleName>Mr.</roleName> and
                           <roleName>Mrs.</roleName> S.C.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hallam</surname>,</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hemans</surname>,
                     <roleName>Mrs</roleName>.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hogg</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hood</surname>, Thomas</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hook</surname>, Theodore</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Hunt</surname>, Leigh</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Huskisson</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Irving</surname>, Washington</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>James</surname>, G.P.E.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Keats</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Kemble</surname> (family)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lamb</surname>, Charles</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Landon</surname> (L.E.L.)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Landseers</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lansdowne</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Laurence</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lockhart</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Londesborough</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Longman</surname>, Thomas Norton</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Lover</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>M'Clise</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Macintosh</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        J.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Macready</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Maginn</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Marryat</surname>,
                        <roleName>Captain</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Mathews</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Milman</surname>, Ian*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Milnes</surname>, Monckton*</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Mitford</surname>,
                     <roleName>Miss</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Montomgery</surname>, James</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Moore</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Munden</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Munster</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Murchison</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        R.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Murray</surname>, John</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Nares</surname>, Archdescon</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Normanby</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Northampton</surname>,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Orme</surname>, Cosmo</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ousely</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName> Wm. and
                           <roleName>Sir</roleName> Gore</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Owen</surname>,
                     <roleName>Professor</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Perceval</surname>, Spencer</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ferry</surname>, James</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Pollock</surname>, <roleName>Lord Chief</roleName>
                        Baron</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Proctor</surname>, B.W. (Barry
                           <surname>Cornwall</surname>)</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ripon</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Roberts</surname>, D.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ross</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName> James
                        Clark</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Russell</surname>, <roleName>Lord</roleName>
                        John</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Scott</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        Walter</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Sedgwick</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Shelley</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Sheridan</surname>, R. Brinsley, Tom &amp;
                        Frank</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Smith</surname>, James</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Smith</surname>, Sydney</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Southey</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Stanfield</surname>, Clarkson</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Swain</surname>, Charles</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Talfourd</surname>, Justice</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Thackeray</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Truro</surname>,
                     <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Turaer</surname>, Sharon</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Tytler</surname>, P.P.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Ward</surname>, R. Plumer</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><roleName>Wellington, Duke of</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>West</surname>, B.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Westmacott</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        R.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Whewell</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Wilkie</surname>, <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                        David</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Willoughby de Eresb</surname>y,
                        <roleName>Lord</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><roleName>Winchester, Biship of
                     (Summer)</roleName></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Wordsworth</surname></persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Wright</surname>, T.</persName></item>
                  <item><persName><surname>Young</surname>, (tragedian)</persName></item>
               </list>
               <emph rend="sc bold">Subscribers' Names Received by All Booksellers.</emph><lb/>
               <emph rend="sc">Arthur Hall, Virtue, and Co., 25, Paternoster Row.</emph>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <note xml:id="byron"><persName><roleName>Lord</roleName><forename>George</forename> Gordon
                  <surname>Byron</surname></persName>, <date type="birth" when="1788-01-01">January
               22, 1788</date>-<date type="death" when="1824-04-19">April 19, 1824</date></note>
         <note xml:id="disraeliB"
               ><persName><forename>Benjamin</forename><surname>Disraeli</surname></persName>, <date
               type="birth" when="1804-12-21">December 21, 1804</date>-<date type="death"
               when="1881-04-19">April 19, 1881</date></note>
         <note xml:id="Dick"><persName><surname>Dickens</surname>,
               <forename>Charles</forename></persName>, <date type="birth" when="1812-02-17"
               >February 17, 1812</date>-<date type="death" when="1870-06-09">June 9,
            1870</date></note>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
