<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Digital Edition of Bleak House and its Advertisements</title>
            <author>Charles Dickens</author>
            <editor xml:id="AC">Aries Chen</editor>
            <editor xml:id="JN">Jessica Nero</editor>
            <editor xml:id="LVH">Luke VanHouten</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and metadata collection by</resp>
               <name ref="#AC">Aries Chen</name>
               <name ref="#JN">Jessica Nero</name>
               <name ref="#LVH">Luke VanHouten</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.8">First draft of the full XML.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded in Oxygen, distributed via Github. For educational, non-commercial use only.
               The purpose of this text is to track the differences in publishing from a serial
               format to one of the more standard novel, including all that comes with that. With
               serial publications, the texts we know today were separated into brief chapters and
               periodicals, only publishing a small section of the final text monthly over a large
               time span. Once the periodical had finished, advertisements began getting published
               for the full text edition of the novel, including in the final periodical of Bleak
               House. With this edition, we aim to display the functional differences in
               publicaition of different mediums of text, particularly focusing on the publication
               elements of the texts individually as well as the advertisements used in the
               periodicals and how these additions affected readership and the reader experience. </p>
            <p>Our digital edition focuses on Charles Dickens’ Bleak House, specifically the last
               few volumes of the 1852 serialized edition, and the 1853 complete first edition.
               Dickens wrote the book in twenty installments throughout 1852 and 1853, with the last
               published serial containing the 19th and 20th installments combined. Each serial
               publication has several pages of advertisements in the front matter of the text,
               which helped fund Dickens’ efforts. In particular, one of the advertisements found in
               the final serialized volume advertises the forthcoming first edition, and contains
               information regarding the copyright and printing information of that edition. A fair
               share of this advertising can also be found in the first novel edition, but not all
               of it. </p>
            <p>The focus of our edition is to compare the publication and copyright information
               shared between the serialized editions (especially the final one that advertises the
               complete edition) and the complete first edition of the book. The advertisement in
               the serial provides a great deal more information regarding the timeline, setting,
               and cost of the printing and publication of the first edition than what the complete
               book provides in its copyright pages. Readers should come away from our edition
               having a better understanding of how the publication process between serials and
               complete volumes, as well as how the documentation of these efforts was less robust
               and more scattered between different sources than with today’s methods (such as
               detailed copyright pages). </p>
            <p>We are using a diplomatic transcription for our edition, and we are trying to
               recreate exactly what is shown on the key pages of the serial and complete editions
               of Bleak House which we are transcribing. We will not be making editorial
               corrrections to any of the text, although there is not too much text itself given the
               relative sparseness of the pages we have chosen to transcribe. </p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Bleak House</title>
               <author>Charles Dickens</author>
               <publisher>
                  <name>Bradbury and Evans</name>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>11 Bouverie Street</addrLine>
                     <settlement>London</settlement>
                     <country>England</country>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
               <date notBefore="1853-09-01" notAfter="1853-09-11">September 1853</date>
               <note>The nineteenth serial</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Bleak House</title>
               <author>Charles Dickens</author>
               <publisher>
                  <name>Bradbury and Evans</name>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>11 Bouverie Street</addrLine>
                     <settlement>London</settlement>
                     <country>England</country>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
               <date when="1853-09-12">12 September 1853</date>
               <note>The full novel</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="Bleak_House_Ad">
            <head style="font-weight:bold;text-transform:uppercase;">Bleak House Advertisers.</head>
            <lb/>
            <p style="font-size:20px;font-weight:bold;">Completion of Bleak House.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>On Monday, 12th September will be published,</p>
            <p><hi style="font-style:italic;">Complete in One thick Volume, 8vo, with Forty Illustrations
                  by</hi>
               <ref target="#HKBrowne_note">H.K. Browne</ref>,</p>
            <p style="font-size:30px;text-transform:uppercase;">Bleak House.</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;">By</p>
            <p style="font-size:16px;text-transform:uppercase">Charles Dickens.</p>
            <p>The Publishers beg to inform the Public and the Trade that <hi style="font-variant:small-caps;">Bleak
                  House,</hi>complete in One Volume, will be ready for delivery on the 12th
               September.</p>
            <p>Price, <ref target="#cloth_binding_note">neatly bound in cloth</ref>. . . . . . . .
               . &#163;1 1 0 </p>
            <p>&quot; &quot; &quot; Half morocco, marble edges . . . . 1 4 6</p>
            <p>(<hi style="font-style:italic;">Cloth Cases for binding the above may be had at the
                  Publishers.</hi>)</p>
            <p><hi style="font-variant:small-caps;">Subscribers</hi>desirous of having their copies bound in
               a similar style can have them at their Booksellers, at the following prices:——</p>
            <p>Whole bound, morocco gilt edges . . . . . . . . <ref target="#price_note">6s.
                  6d.</ref></p>
            <p>Half bound, &quot; . . . . . . . . 4 6</p>
            <p>In cloth, lettered . . . . . . . . . . 1 6</p>
            <p style="font-size:16px;text-transform:uppercase;">By the same author.</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;">Price <hi style="font-style:italic;">3s. 6d.</hi>each, neatly bound in
               cloth,</p>
            <p style="font-size:20px;text-transform:uppercase;">The first and second volumes</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;">Of</p>
            <p style="font-size:25px;text-transform:uppercase;font-weight:bold;">A Child's History of
               England.</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;">With frontispieces from drawings by F.W.
               Topham.</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;">Corrected and revised from &quot;Household
               Words,&quot; with a table of dates.</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;font-style:italic;">The History will be completed in Three
                  Volumes.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Encyclopedia_Ad">
            <head style="text-transform:uppercase;"><ref target="#Encyclopedia_note">English Cyclopædia.</ref></head>
            <ab style="font-type:gothic;">A New Dictionary of Universal Knowlege.</ab>
            <ab style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;font-weight:bold;">And Illustrated with Five
               Thousand Wood Engravings.</ab>
            <ab style="text-transform:uppercase;">Conducted by Mr. Charles Knight.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab style="text-transform:uppercase;">Opinions of the Press</ab>
            <p><quote>Among serials, the most important in our eyes is the new edition of the
                  <hi style="font-style:italic;">Penny Cyclopædia</hi> issued in separate divisions
                  under the name of the <hi style="font-style:italic;">English Cyclopædia</hi>.
                  </quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Leader</hi></p>
            <p><quote>We do not feel that it is employing the language of exaggeration to say that
                  the issue in a cheap and greatly improved form of the English Cyclopædia, under
                  the editorship of Mr. <hi style="font-variant:small-caps;">Charles Knight</hi>, and with the co-operation of Messrs.
                  <hi style="font-variant:small-caps;">Bradbury &amp; Evans</hi>, dedicated by permission to Her Majesty, partakes of the
                  character of a national undertaking.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Weekly News and Chronicle</hi>.</p>
            <p><quote>The mass of information here presented in a beautiful type and a readable
                  form, the cleverness and value of the illustrations, and the extraordinary
                  cheapness of the whole, combine, with the publication advantages we have
                  explained, to render the <hi style="font-style:italic;">English Cyclopædia</hi> the best thing of its class, and one
                  which we can conscientiously recommend to our readers.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">The Field</hi>.</p>
            <p><quote>This invaluable work has now reached the twelfth number ; and the public have
                  been afforded ample opportunity of testing its merits as one of the most copious
                  and complete Cyclopædias, and certainly the cheapest that has ever been
                  issued.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Dublin Evening Post</hi>.</p>
            <p><quote>The <hi style="font-style:italic;">English Cyclopædia</hi>, Part II., is occupied with Natural History and
                  Geography. The effect of skilful [sic] printing is here more than ever apparent.
                  Dr. <hi style="font-variant:small-caps;">Lankester</hi> has undertaken to bring the botanical articles up to the present
                  state of knowledge.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Gardener’s Chronicle</hi>.</p>
            <p><quote>Three parts are now before us; and, while they show perfection in typography,
                  they evince the utmost fulness [sic] of knowledge in the writers— discoveries and
                  details being brought down to the present day. The <hi style="font-style:italic;">Penny Cyclopædia</hi> was
                  undoubtedly the best general dictionary ever published; but we can say that this
                  one promises to be still better.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Liverpool Journal</hi>.</p>
            <p><quote>Of the First Part we have at present to speak, and from the specimen before
                  us, we most conscientiously and emphatically recommend these ample dictionaries
                  upon special subjects of almost universal interest, as by far the best that are
                  likely to be procurable for many years, equally full-and published for a price
                  which, at the present cost of production, after allowing for a most extensive
                  sale, can be taken strictly as the minimum of cheapness possible in our
                  day.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Examiner</hi>.</p>
            <p><quote>The first six numbers of this publication are now before us, and if they are
                  to be taken as a sample of the remaining numbers, it may truly be described as a
                  wonderful production in a variety of ways; accuracy, the beauty and correctness of
                  the wood engravings, in the Natural History portion; and though last not least its
                  amazing cheapness.</quote>—<hi style="font-style:italic;">Dumfries Courier</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">Bradbury &amp; Evans, 11, Bouverie Street.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Water_Ad">
            <head style="text-transform:uppercase;">Descriptive Particulars</head>
            <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">Of</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">Hansome's Patent Stone Filters</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">For</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">Purifyin Water,</hi></p>
            <p>Manufactured in the Patent Stone which has obtained the Medal of the Society of Civil
               Engineers, the Medal of the Great Exhibition of 1851, the approval of the most
               distinguished Men of Science, as <hi style="font-weight:bold;">Faraday, De la Beche, Buckland,
               Cubitt, Ansted, Phillips,</hi>&amp;c. &amp;c., of the most eminent Men in the
               Medical Profession, and of the leading journalists whose Testimonials are
               annexed.</p>
            <p style="font-weight:bold;">The Advantages of the Patent Stone Filter are,—</p>
            <p>1st. <hi style="font-weight:bold;">Simplicity</hi>of construction, and a never-failing supply of water.</p>
            <p>2nd. <hi style="font-weight:bold;">The purity</hi>of the filtered water, arising from the thickness and
               density of the stone through which it passes.</p>
            <p>3rd. <hi style="font-weight:bold;">Coolness</hi>of the water in summer; the apparatus, being completely
               immersed, is not liable to be affected by atmospheric temperature.</p>
            <p>4th. It is equally applicable to Wells, Ponds, or large Reservoirs, as to the common Cistern
               or Water-butt.</p>
            <p>5th. The water thus filtered is freed from the insipid flatness peculiar to that passin through
               the ordinary filters.</p>
            <p>6th. <hi style="font-weight:bold;">Its cheapness</hi>over other filters, when estimated by the amount of water
               it is capable of filtering.</p>
            <p>7th. It is eminently adapted for the filtration of other liquids, which it renders fine and
               transparent, without depriving them of their essential properties, or exposing them to the action
               of the atmosphere, as is the case with most other filters.</p>
            <p>8th. The absence of <hi style="font-weight:bold;">Sponge</hi>or any other matter liable to decomposition or
               decay. Experience has proved that the ordinary filters after a short space of time frequently
               render the water more disagreeable and impure than before, owing to the putrid state of the
               very medium that is used for filtration.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Cheap_Edition">
            <head><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;"><ref target="#Cheap_Edition_note">Cheap
                  Edition</ref></hi></head>
            <p style="font-size=12px;text-transform:uppercase;">Of The</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">Works of Mr. Charles
               Dickens.</p>
            <p>In compliance with the general wish of the purchasers of this Edition of the Works of
                  <hi style="font-variant:small-caps;">Mr. Charles Dickens</hi>, terminating with <quote><hi
                  style="font-variant:small-caps;"> Martin Chuzzlewit,</hi></quote> it is intended to include within
                  it the five Christmas Books :—</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">A Christmas Carol.</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">The Chimes.</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">The Cricket on the Hearth</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">The Battle of Life.</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">The Haunted Man.</p>
            <p>These will form, together, when their publication in Numbers shall be completed, <hi
                  style="font-variant:small-caps;">One additional Volume of the Cheap Edition.</hi></p>
            <p>This additional Volume, like its predecessors (and printed to range with them), will
               be issued in Weekly Numbers, price 1 ½ d. each, and in Monthly Parts. The first
               Weekly Number will be published on the 1st of June.</p>
            <p style="font-size=16px;text-transform:uppercase;">Chapman and Hall, 193,
                  Piccadilly</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Chapman_and_Hall">
            <p style="class:pagenumber">3</p>
            <p style="class:runningheader">Advertisements.</p>
            <p>Cheap editions.</p>
            <div>
               <p style="text-transform:uppercase;">The</p>
               <p>Works of Mr. Charles Dickens.</p>
               <p style="font-style:italic;">Uniformly printed in crown 8vo, Corrected and Revised throughout, with new
                  prefaces by the Author.</p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>Cloth, gilt backs.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell style="font-style:italic;">s.</cell>
                     <cell style="font-style:italic;">d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Pickwick Papers</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Nicholas Nickleby</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Old Curiosity Shop</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Barnaby Rudge</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Martin Chuzzlewit</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Oliver Twist</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">American Notes</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Sketches by Boz</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell style="text-transform:uppercase;">Christmas Books</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*** Any of the above volumes may be had separately, half-bound in
                        morocco, for 2s. 6d. extra.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div>
            <div>
               <ab style="class:publisher">London: <ref target="#Chapman_and_Hall_note">Chapman and
                     Hall</ref>, 193, Piccadilly.</ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Dedication">
            <p style="text-transform:uppercase;text-align:center;">Dedicated,</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;text-align:center;">As a remembrance of our
               friendly union.</p>
            <p style="font-size:16px;text-transform:uppercase;text-align:center;">To My Companions</p>
            <p style="font-size:12px;text-transform:uppercase;text-align:center;">In the</p>
            <p style="text-transform:uppercase;text-align:center;"><ref target="#guild_note">Guild of Literature
                  and Art</ref></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Table_of_Contents_1">
            <head style="font-variant:small-caps;">Contents.</head>
            <table>
               <row style="font-size:10px;text-transform:uppercase;">
                  <cell>Chap.</cell>
                  <cell/>
		            <cell>Page</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>I.</cell>
                  <cell style="font-variant:small-caps;">In Chancery</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>II.</cell>
                  <cell>In Fashion</cell>
                  <cell>5</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>III.</cell>
                  <cell>A Progress</cell>
                  <cell>10</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>IV.</cell>
                  <cell>Telescopic Philanthropy</cell>
                  <cell>24</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>V.</cell>
                  <cell>A Morning Adventure</cell>
                  <cell>33</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>VI.</cell>
                  <cell>Quite at Home</cell>
                  <cell>42</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>VII.</cell>
                  <cell>The Ghost's Walk</cell>
                  <cell>57</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>VIII.</cell>
                  <cell>Covering a Multitude of Sins</cell>
                  <cell>65</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>IX.</cell>
                  <cell>Signs and Tokens</cell>
                  <cell>79</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>X.</cell>
                  <cell>The Law-writer</cell>
                  <cell>89</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>XI.</cell>
                  <cell>Our dear Brother</cell>
                  <cell>97</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>XII.</cell>
                  <cell>On the Watch</cell>
                  <cell>107</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>XIII.</cell>
                  <cell>Esther's Narrative</cell>
                  <cell>117</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>XIV.</cell>
                  <cell>Deportment</cell>
                  <cell>129</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Title_Page">
            <head style="text-transform:uppercase;">Bleak House.</head>
            <div rend="spacing">
               <p>BY</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="smallspacing">
               <p><seg source="boldtext" style="text-transform:uppercase;">Charles Dickens.</seg></p>
            </div>
            <div rend="spacing smalltext">
               <div type="rule"/>
               <div>
                  <p style="text-transform:uppercase;">With illustrations by H. K. Browne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rule"/>
            </div>
            <div rend="spacing">
               <p style="text-transform:uppercase;">London : <lb/>Bradbury and Evans, 11, Bouverie Street.
                  <lb/>1853. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Chapter_I">
            <div rend="spacing">
               <head style="text-transform:uppercase">Bleak House.</head>
            </div>
            <div rend="smallspacing">
               <div type="rule"/>
               <div rend="smallspacing">
                  <p style="text-transform:uppercase">Chapter I.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div rend="smallspacing smalltext">
               <p style="text-transform:uppercase;">In Chancery.</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="booktext smallspacing smalltext">
               <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">London.</hi> Michaelmas term lately over, and the Lord
                  Chancellor sitting in Lincoln's Inn Hall. Implacable November weather. As much mud
                  in the streets, as if the waters had but newly retired from the face of the earth,
                  and it would not be wonderful to meet a Megalosaurus, forty feet long or so,
                  waddling like an elephantine lizard up Holborn-hill. Smoke lowering down from
                  chimney-pots, making a soft black drizzle, with flakes of soot in it as big as
                  full-grown snow-flakes—gone into mourning, one might imagine, for the death of the
                  sun. Dogs, undistinguishable in mire. Horses, scarcely better; splashed to their
                  very blinkers. Foot passengers, jostling one another's umbrellas, in a general
                  infection of ill-temper, and losing their foot-hold at street-corners, where tens
                  of thousands of other foot passengers have been slipping and sliding since the day
                  broke (if the day ever broke), adding new deposits to the crust upon crust of mud,
                  sticking at those points tenaciously to the pavement, and accumulating at compound
                  interest.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="Chapter_LX">
            <div rend="spacing">
               <div type="rule"/>
               <div type="rule"/>
               <div rend="smallspacing">
                  <p style="text-transform:uppercase;">Chapter LX.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div rend="smallspacing smalltext">
               <p style="text-transform:uppercase;">Perspective.</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="booktext smallspacing smalltext">
               <p><hi style="text-transform:uppercase;">I proceed</hi>to other passages of my narrative. From
                  the goodness of all about me, I derived such consolation as I can never think of
                  unmoved. I have already said so much of myself, and so much still remains, that I
                  will not dwell upon my sorrow. I had an illness, but it was not a long one; and I
                  would avoid even this mention of it, if I could quite keep down the recollection
                  of their sympathy.</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="spacing">
               <div type="rule"/>
               <div type="rule"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <note xml:id="HKBrowne_note">H.K. Browne, or Hablot Knight Browne, was Charles Dickens’ main
         illustrator, creating illustrations for ten out of fifteen of Dickens’ works. Sometimes he
         worked under the pseudonym Nemo or Phiz, but later changed to his real name in his later
         works. Originally, an artist named Robert Seymour created illustrations for Dickens but
         then committed suicide, causing Dickens’ to look for a new artist for his work. Browne
         started by working on The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club and continued for Dickens
         as his primary illustrator until he was passed over to create illustrations for Our Mutual
         Friend to Marcus Stone who then surpassed Browne in popularity.</note>
      <note xml:id="Encyclopedia_note">The Cyclopædia is a different way of saying an English
         Encyclopedia. The first English encyclopedia was published in the late 1700s, later
         developing with illustrations, covering every subject from arts to sciences. The efforts to
         compile the first Encyclopedia are attributed to Diderot, taking a great amount of effort
         to compile all the necessary information to an inital 2000 subscribers which later expanded
         exponentially.</note>
      <note xml:id="Chapman_and_Hall_note">Chapman and Hall published another edition of Bleak
         House in 1873.</note>
      <note xml:id="cloth_binding_note">During the late 19th century, cloth binding became more
         popular, but it was not the norm. It was popular during the 17th and 18th century, with
         books bound in either leather or in a “temporary envelope of paper wrappers” (Carter). The
         development of cloth binding made literature more accessible as it was cheaper than its
         leather counterparts so a wider range of people from varying social strata could purchase
         books.</note>
      <note xml:id="price_note">“s” denotes the cost of an item in shillings, while “d” denotes the
         cost in pennies. Shillings were the main form of currency in England in 1850 when Bleak
         House was published. It would take 20 shillings to make a pound and 12 pence to make a
         shilling, showing the cheapness of this text at the time.</note>
      <note xml:id="Cheap_Edition_note">Publishers created cheap editions of books or compendiums
         of books in this case in order to increase affordability and accessibility of literature to
         ensure it was reaching as many people as possible. The creation of these editions
         contributed to various developments in the 19th century, however the most important was the
         Industrial Revolution which made printing easier and a much quicker process, therefore
         publishers could print at higher rates and in denser volumes. The main difference between
         cheap and regular editions at this time was the materials that were used in its production,
         with the regular editions having much more expensive paper, binding, etc., meaning that
         cheap editions would degrade quicker but were more affordable to lower classes.</note>
      <note xml:id="guild_note">The Guild of Literature and Art was an organizati  on co-founded by
         Dickens along with John Forster and Edward Bulwer Lutton, to fund art projects for authors
         and artists who didn’t have enough money to pursue their art. As a cofounder, Dickens
         dedicated his novel to the organization to further promote it in order to spread more
         awareness of underfunded artists. The group was funded through various fundraising efforts
         including theatrical performances.</note>
      <bibl>
         <bibl>Carter, John. “Origins of Cloth Bindings.” Denis Gouey Bookbinding Studio,
            bookbinding.com/origins-of-cloth-bindings/. Accessed 19 May 2025.</bibl>
         <bibl>“Currency, Coinage and the Cost of Living.” The Proceedings of the Old Bailey,
            Digital Humanities Institute, www.oldbaileyonline.org/about/coinage. Accessed 19 May
            2025.</bibl>
         <bibl>“Dickens’s Launches the ‘Cheap Edition’ of His Works, Beginning with ‘Pickwick.’”
            History of Information, www.historyofinformation.com/detail.php?id=4506. Accessed 19 May
            2025.</bibl>
         <bibl>“Hablot Knight (Phiz) Browne (1815 - 1882).” Royal Academy of Arts, Royal Academy of
            Arts, www.royalacademy.org.uk/art-artists/name/hablot-knight-phiz-browne. Accessed 19
            May 2025.</bibl>
         <bibl>“History of Encyclopaedias.” Encyclopædia Britannica, Encyclopædia Britannica, inc., www.britannica.com/topic/encyclopaedia/History-of-encyclopaedias. Accessed 2 June 2025. </bibl>
         <bibl>Schlicke, Paul, editor. The Oxford Reader’s Companion to Dickens, 2000,
            https://doi.org/10.1093/acref/9780198662532.001.0001.</bibl>
      </bibl>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
